[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50'S Introduction
to Programming with Python.
My name is David Malan.
And over these past many
weeks have we focused
on functions and variables early
on, then conditionals, and loops,
and exceptions, a bit of
libraries, unit test file
layout, regular expressions,
object-oriented programming,
and really, et cetera.
And indeed, that's
where we focus today, is
on all the more that you can
do with Python and programming
more generally beyond some of
those fundamental concepts as well.
In fact, if you start to flip
through the documentation for Python
and all of its form, all of which is as
always accessible at docs.python.org,
you'll see additional documentation
on Python's own tutorial and library,
its reference, its how-to.
And among all of those various
documents as well as others more online,
you'll see that there's some tidbits
that we didn't quite touch on.
And indeed, even though we
themed these past several weeks
of around fairly broad topics that
are rather essential for doing
typical types of problems
in Python, it turns out
there's quite a number of other features
as well, that we didn't necessarily
touch on, that didn't
necessarily fit within any
of those overarching
concepts, or might have
been a little too much too soon if we
did them too early on in the course.
And so, in today, our
final lecture, well, we
focus really on all the more
that you can do with Python
and hopefully whet your appetite for
teaching yourself all the more to.
For instance, among
Python's various data types,
there's this other one that we haven't
had occasion to yet use, namely, a set.
In mathematics, a set is
typically a collection of values
wherein there are no duplicates.
So it's not quite a list.
It's a bit more special than that
in that somehow any duplicates are
eliminated for you.
Well, it turns out within Python,
this is an actual data type
that you yourself can use in your code.
And via the documentation
here, might you
be able to glean that
it's a useful problem
if you want to somehow
automatically filter out duplicates.
So let me go ahead and
go over to VS Code here.
And let me go ahead and show you a file
that I created a bit of in advance,
whereby we have a file
here called houses.py.
And in houses.py, I already
went ahead and whipped up
a big list of students
inside of which is
a number of dictionaries, each of
which represents a student's name
and house respectively.
Now, this is a pretty
sizable dictionary.
And so, it lends itself to
iteration over the same.
And suppose that the goal here
was quite simply to figure out,
well, what are the unique houses at
Hogwarts in the world of Harry Potter?
It would be nice, perhaps, to not
have to know these kinds of details
or look them up online.
Here we have a set of students, albeit
not exhaustive, with all of the houses.
But among these students here, what are
the unique houses in which they live?
Well, I could certainly, as
a human, just eyeball this
and tell you that it's, well,
Gryffindor, Slytherin, and Ravenclaw.
But how can we go about doing it
programmatically for these students
as well?
Well, let's take one
approach first here.
Let me go into houses.py.
And let me propose that we first
how about create an empty list
called houses in which I'm going to
accumulate each of the houses uniquely.
So every time I iterate through
this list of dictionaries,
I'm only going to add a house to this
list if I haven't seen it before.
So how do I express that?
Well, let me iterate over all of the
students with for student in students,
as we've done in the past.
And let me ask you a question now.
So if the current student's house--
and notice that I'm indexing
into the current student
because I know they are a
dictionary or dict object,
and if that student's house
is not in my house's list,
then, indented, am I going
to say houses.append,
because again, houses is a list.
And I'm going to append that
particular house to the list.
Then at the very bottom
here, let me go ahead
and do something somewhat interesting
here and say, for each of the houses
that I've accumulated in,
I could just say houses.
But if I just say houses, what was the
point of accumulating them all at once?
I could just do this
whole thing in a loop.
Let's at least go about
and sort those houses
with sorted, which is going
to the strings alphabetically.
And let's go ahead therein
and print each of the houses.
Let me go ahead now
in my terminal window
and run Python of
houses.py and hit Enter.
And there we have it.
Gryffindor, Ravenclaw,
Slytherin in alphabetical order,
even though in the list
of dictionaries up here,
technically the order in which we
saw these was Gryffindor, Gryffindor,
Gryffindor, Slytherin, Ravenclaw.
So indeed, my code seems to
have sorted them properly.
So this is perfectly fine.
And it's one way of
solving this problem.
But it turns out we could use more
that's built into the language Python
to solve this problem ourself.
Here I'm rather reinventing a
wheel, really the notion of a set
wherein duplicates
are eliminated for me.
So let me go ahead and
clear my terminal window
and perhaps change the type
of object I'm using here.
Instead of a list, which
could also be written
like this to create an
empty list, let me go ahead
and create an empty set,
whereby I call a function called
set that's going to return
to me some object in Python
that represents this notion of a set
wherein duplicates are automatically
eliminated.
And now, I can tighten up my code.
Because I don't have to use
this if condition myself.
I think I can just do
something like this.
Inside of my loop, let me do houses.add.
So it's not append for a
set, it's append for a list.
But it's add to a set
per the documentation.
Then let me go ahead and add
this current student's house.
And now, I think the rest
of my code can be the same.
I'm just now trusting per the
documentation for set in Python
that it's going to filter
out duplicates for me.
And I can just blindly add, add, add,
add all of these houses to the set
and any duplicates already
there will be gone.
Python of houses.py and Enter.
And voila, we're back in business
with just those three there as well.
Let me pause here to see if there's any
questions now on this use of set, which
is just another data type
that's available to you,
another class in the world of
Python that you can reach for when
solving some problem like this.
STUDENT: How can we
locate an item in a set,
for example, find
Gryffindor in that set?
DAVID J. MALAN: How do
you find an item in a set?
You can use very similar syntax
as we've done for a list before.
You can use syntax like if
Gryffindor in houses then,
and you can answer a
question along those lines.
So you can use in and not in
and similar functions as well.
Other questions on set?
STUDENT: Look what happens if
you have a similar house name?
Let's say instead of
Slytherin, it is maybe
an O instead of an I.
Will the for loop loop
throughout each of those
letters in the house name?
DAVID J. MALAN: It would
compare the strings.
So if Slytherin appears
more than once but is
slightly misspelled or
capitalized, if I heard you right,
those would appear to
be distinct strings.
So you would get both versions
of Slytherin in the result.
However, we've seen in the past
how we can clean up users' data
if indeed it might be messy.
We could force everything to
uppercase, or everything to lowercase,
or we could use capitalize
the function built into strs,
or title case that would handle
some of the cleanup for us.
In this case, because the data is not
coming from humans using the input
function, I wrote the code
in advance, it's safer
to assume that I got the houses right.
But that's absolutely a risk
if it's coming from users.
Allow me to turn our attention
back to some of the other features
here that we can leverage in Python if
we dig further into the documentation
and read up more on its features.
Well, in some language,
there's this notion
of global variables, whereby you
can define a variable that's either
local to a function, as
we've seen many times,
or if you put a variable outside
of all of your functions,
perhaps near the top of your
file, that would generally
be considered a global variable.
Or in the world of Python, it
might be specific to the module.
But for all intents and purposes, it's
going to behave for a given program
as though it is global.
However, it turns out
that if you do this
when solving some problem down the line,
whereby you have multiple functions
and you do have one or more variables
that are outside of those functions,
you might not be able to change those
variables as easily as you might think.
So indeed, let me go
back to VS Code here.
And in just a moment, I'm going to go
ahead and create a new file, how about
called bank.py.
Let's go ahead and implement
the notion of a bank
wherein we can store things
like money in various forms.
And let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and
implement a very simple bank
that simply keeps track of my total
balance, the number of dollars or cents
or whatever I might be
storing in this bank.
And I'm going to give myself a variable
called balance at the top, which
is an integer, a set to zero.
Now let me go ahead and define
a main function as we often do.
And inside of my main function, let me
go ahead and print out, quote unquote,
balance, and then print out
the value of balance itself.
Passing to print, as we've often done,
more than one argument so that they get
separated by a single white space.
And now, since I have a main
function, really setting the stage
for doing more interesting
things soon, let
me go ahead and do our usual
if the name of this file
equals equals underscore underscore
main, then go ahead and call main.
So this is a terribly short
program, but it's perhaps
representative of how you might
solve some future problem in Python.
Whereby you have a main function
that's going to eventually do
some interesting stuff.
And at the top of your file,
you have one or more variables
that are just useful to keep there
because then you know where they are.
And perhaps not just main but other
functions can access them as well.
So let's see.
When I run this program,
Python of bank.py,
I would hope based on my own
intuition thus far that I'm going
to see that my current balance is zero.
That is to say, even though the balance
variable is defined on line one,
hopefully I can still print
it online five inside of main,
even though balance was not
defined in my main function.
Here we go.
Hitting Enter.
And voila, balance zero.
So it does seem to work.
Even if you declare a variable in
Python outside of your functions,
it appears that you can access it.
You can read the value of that variable
even inside of a function like main.
Well, let's get a little
more adventurous now.
Because this program really
isn't solving anyone's problems.
Let's go ahead and
implement more of a bank,
like the ability to
deposit money into the bank
and to withdraw money from the bank.
Thereby giving me some more
functions that might very well
need to access that same variable.
Let me clear my terminal window here.
And let me go ahead and
pretend for the moment
that I have the ability to
deposit, say, $100 or 100 coins,
whatever the unit of currency is here.
And then, maybe I want
to withdraw straight
away 50 of those same dollars or coins.
And now, let me go ahead and just
print out at the bottom of main
what my new balance should
be so that in an ideal world,
once I have deposited 100 then
withdrawn 50, after starting at 0,
I'd like to think that my new balance
on line eight should indeed be 50.
All right.
But I haven't implemented
these functions yet.
So let's do that as
we've done in the past.
Down here, I'm going to go ahead
and define another function deposit.
I'm going to say that it takes an
argument called n for a number of coins
or dollars or the like.
And I'm just going to do this.
I'm going to go ahead and
say, balance plus equals n,
thereby changing the value of n.
I could do it more verbosely,
balance equals balance plus n.
But I'm going to use the shorter
hand notation here instead.
And now, let's implement withdraw.
So define a function called withdraw.
It too is going to take
a variable-- an argument
n for number of dollars or coins.
And now, I'm going to go ahead
and subtract from balance
using minus equals n as well.
And I'm still going to call main
if the name of this file is main.
So what have I done?
I've just added not just one but
three functions total, all of which
apparently need to access balance
by printing it, incrementing it,
or decrementing it, as we've seen here.
All right.
Let me go ahead and focus on
these three functions here.
Let me go back to my terminal window
and run Python of bank.py and hit Enter.
And wow.
Seems like we've introduced
some number of problems here.
And what are these problems?
Well, unbound local error is perhaps
the first time we've seen this one here.
Local variable balance
referenced before assignment.
And that's a bit misleading,
definitely confusing.
Because I absolutely assigned balance
of value on the top of my code.
And indeed, if I scroll back up, nothing
has changed or been lost up there.
It's definitely been assigned to value.
And now on line 12, it would
seem, that when deposit is called
I'm just trying to access
that variable again.
So intuitively, what might explain this
error message, unbound local error?
What is Python telling us
there that Python can or can't
do when it comes to these
so-called global variables that
are at the top of my file?
STUDENT: So if you want
to change this variable,
you should write an
inside left function main.
And the global variable unchangeable.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So if you
want to change the value,
it might need to be
local to the function.
If you are trying to change a global
variable though in a function,
it clearly does not work.
So it's OK to read a global variable.
Read meaning access it
and print it and so forth.
But apparently, you can't write to
a global variable in the same way
from within one of these functions.
All right.
Well, maybe the fix is to do this.
Let me clear my terminal
window and that error.
And maybe I could just do this.
Let's get rid of the global variable.
And let's go ahead and put it,
for instance, inside of main.
Might this now work?
Well, let me try this now.
Python of Bank.py Enter.
That alone did not solve it.
I still have an unbound local error.
This time though, it's
for a different reason.
It turns out now that balance on line
two is by definition a local variable.
A local variable is one that exists
in the context of a function, at least
in this case.
A global variable is the
opposite, one that does not,
for instance at the top of my file.
So here is another
distinction in Python.
If you declare a variable
in a function, like main,
just as I've done on
line two with balance,
it is indeed local to that function.
Deposit and withdraw do not have
access to that same variable.
Why?
Because it's local to main.
And so, you would think now we're
kind of stuck in this vicious cycle.
Well, maybe the solution then
is to move balance globally
so all three functions can access it.
But clearly, where we began, as Elena
noted, we can't therefore change it.
So it turns out the solution
to this problem in Python
is ironically exactly this keyword here.
It's a little different as
you might have seen if you've
programmed before in other languages.
But there's indeed a
keyword in Python called
global that allows you to tell
a function that, hey, this
is not a variable that's local to you.
I mean it to be a global
variable that I want you to edit.
So if I go back to VS Code
here, clearing my terminal
window to get rid of that error.
Let me go ahead and undo
the change I just made
and put balance back
at the top of my file.
But this time, what
I'm going to do is I'm
going to inform my two functions that
need to change the value of balance,
that it is indeed global, by typing
global balance again here as well as
here.
Global balance.
I still leave the same lines of code
now on lines 13 and 18, that increment
and decrement balance.
But this now use of keyword global is
a little bit of a clue to Python that,
oh, OK.
It's not a local variable.
This is not a bug that
you've introduced.
You mean for me to edit
this variable up above.
So now, let me go ahead in my terminal
window and run Python of bank.py.
I'm hoping to see that my balance
is zero plus 100 minus 50 is 50.
And indeed, it now is.
It starts off at zero per my first
print statement on line five.
But it ends up at 50 total
at below that on line eight.
Let me pause here to see if
now there's any questions
on these global or local variables.
STUDENT: What happens when you
declare a variable globally, and as
in the same variable
globally and in a function?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
You're always thinking about
the so-called corner cases.
So if you declare a variable both
globally, like at the top of your file,
and then an identically named variable
inside of a function, same name,
the latter will shadow,
so to speak, the former.
That is, you'll be able to use the
latter, that is the local variable.
But it will have no effect
on the global variable.
Temporarily, Python will only know
that the local variable exists.
So in general, the rule of
thumb is, just don't do that.
Not only might it
create bugs in your code
because you don't quite change
what you intend to change.
It's also perhaps non-obvious
to other readers as well.
Other questions on globals or locals?
STUDENT: OK, what if we
decide to add balance
as an argument inside the main function?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
another good instinct.
But in this case, that also is
not going to solve the problem.
Because if you pass in a variable
like balance to each of the functions
and then change it within
that function, it's
only going to be changing in
effect a local copy thereof.
It's not going to be changing
what's outside of those functions.
So I think we actually need
a better way altogether.
And in fact, allow me to transition
to perhaps a modification
of this same program.
Recall that we looked most
recently at this notion
of object-oriented programming.
Whereby you can model real world
entities, for instance a bank,
and you can model and
encapsulate information
about that real world
entity, for instance,
like someone's account balance.
So let me propose that
we actually do this.
Let me start from scratch with bank.py.
Get rid of the global
variable altogether.
And actually use some
object-oriented code.
Let me define a class called account
to represent someone's bank account.
And then, let me go ahead and
initialize with my init method, which
again, takes by convention at
least one argument called self.
Let me go ahead and initialize
every person's bank account
to some value like zero.
Now, how can I do that?
Well, I'm going to go ahead and
do self.balance equals zero.
Thereby giving me an
instance variable called
balance initialized for
this account to zero.
But I'm going to proactively
remember how we also
introduced this notion of
properties which might otherwise
collide with the names
of my instance variables.
So just by convention
I'm going to do this.
I'm going to rename this
instance variable proactively
to underscore balance to effectively
indicate that it's private, even
though that's not enforced by Python.
It's just a visual clue
to myself that this
is something that really I should
not-- or other code should not touch,
just functions in this class.
Now, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and
define an actual function
called balance that really is going
to be a property whose purpose in life
is just to return self.balance.
And I'm going to go explicitly
and say this is indeed
a property of this class.
Now, let me go ahead and re-implement
those other two functions,
deposit and withdraw, but in
the confines of this class.
So I'm going to say, define deposit.
It's going to take in an
argument self as always,
but an additional one n, a number
of dollars or coins to deposit.
And how do I now manipulate this?
Well, I'm going to do
self._balance plus equals n.
And now down here, I'm going to do def
withdraw self n, just like for deposit.
But here, I'm going to do
self.balance minus equals n.
And now, if I go down
below this class, I'm
going to go ahead and define
myself a main function
just so I can try this now out.
I'm going to go ahead and create an
account object by calling the account
constructor, that is the name of
the class with two parentheses
if I'm not passing in
any arguments to init.
I'm going to go ahead now and print out
as before the balance of my account.
But to do that, I'm going to access
the property of that account like this.
And I'm going to go ahead now and
say, deposit another $100 or coins
with deposit 100.
And I'm going to go ahead, like before,
and also now immediately withdraw
for whatever reason 50 of the same.
And now, I'm going to
print one last time
balance followed by account.balance,
again, accessing that property.
And for this whole thing to work,
of course, I need one of these
if name equals equals underscore
main, then go ahead and call main.
Now, before I run this, you'll see
that it rather escalated quickly.
I had a very simple goal at hand
to implement the notion of a bank.
And I was able to implement
that perfectly fine ultimately
by declaring balance to be global
but then to tell each of my functions
that it is indeed global.
But that's not really the best form of
encapsulation we have at our disposal
now.
Per our focus on
object-oriented programming,
if we're trying to implement some real
world entity like an account at a bank,
that's what classes allow us to do.
And it allows us to solve that
same problem perhaps a little
more cleanly, certainly if we're going
to accumulate more and more functions
or methods over time.
So if I didn't make any mistakes here,
if I run Python of bank.py and hit
Enter now, you'll see that
it just works just fine.
Because in the world
of classes in Python,
these so-called instance
variables are by definition
accessible to all of the
methods in that class
because we're accessing them all by
way of that special parameter self.
So which way to do it?
For a reasonably small
script wherein you are simply
trying to implement a script
that has some global information,
like an account balance that you
then need to manipulate elsewhere,
the global keyword is a
solution to that problem.
But generally speaking,
in many languages,
Python to some extent among
them, using global variables
tends to be frowned upon only
because things can get messy quickly.
And it can become less obvious quickly
exactly where your information is
stored, if some of it's up here,
some of it's in your function.
So generally, the rule of thumb is
to use global variables sparingly.
Though technically speaking, in
Python these global variables
are technically local to our module
if we were indeed implementing
a library and not just a program.
So in short, try to use
global variables sparingly.
But when you do, there is a
solution to these same problems.
Questions now on globals or our
reimplementation of the same idea
but using full-fledged
object-oriented programming?
STUDENT: I just would like to
ask, what this property does?
DAVID J. MALAN: What this property does.
So if I go back to VS
Code here, you'll see
that this was a technique
we looked at in our lecture
on object-oriented programming.
Whereby a property is a instance
variable that somehow protected.
It allows me to control it
can be read and written.
So in this case, I only have
what's called generally a setter.
And or sorry.
In this case, I only have what's
generally called a getter.
And there's no mention
of the word getter here.
This is just @property means.
That function balance
will allow me, recall,
to use syntax like this,
where I can pretend
as though balance is indeed with
no underscore an instance variable.
But I can now prevent code like mine
in main from trying to change balance.
Because I do not have
a setter, I would not
be able to do something like
account balance equals 1,000
to just give myself 1,000 or coins
because I have not defined a setter.
So again, per our focus on
object-oriented programming,
these properties just allow
me some finer-grained control.
Some languages allow you to define
variables that are, so to speak,
constant.
That is, once you have
set a value to them,
you cannot change the
value of that variable.
And that tends to be a
good thing because it
allows you to program defensively.
Just in case you
accidentally, or someone else,
accidentally tries to modify
the value of that variable,
if you have declared it in some language
as a constant, it cannot be changed,
or usually cannot be changed
without great effort.
Unfortunately, in Python, we're again
on the sort of honor system here.
Where we have conventions
to indicate that something
should be treated as
though it's constant.
But that's not actually
enforced by the language.
So for instance, let me
go back here to VS Code.
And let me create a new file,
for instance, called meows.py.
And let's see if we can't implement the
notion of a cat meowing on the screen.
So I'll do code of meows.py.
And in meows.py, let me
go ahead for instance
and implement a very simple program
that just has a cat meowing three times.
So how about this.
For i in the range of three, go ahead
and print out, quote unquote, meow.
All right.
Well, we've seen in the past how
we can clean this up a little bit.
For instance, if I'm
not actually using i,
I might as well Pythonically
just change the name
of that variable to underscore
even though that has no functional
effect here.
But here we have this three
randomly hardcoded, that is,
typed explicitly into my code.
And it's totally not a big deal
when your code is only two lines.
But imagine that this is a
much bigger program with dozens
or even hundreds of lines.
And imagine that one of those lines
just has a three in there somewhere.
You're never going to find
that three very easily.
And it's going to be
very easily overlooked
by you or colleagues
or others that you've
hardcoded some magic value like
a three right there in your code.
So it tends to be best practice, not
just in Python but other languages
as well, any time you have
what is essentially a constant,
like a number three that
shouldn't ever change,
is to at least let it bubble up,
surface it to the top of your code,
so that it's just obvious what
your code's constant values are.
And so, by that I mean this.
At the top of this
file, it would probably
be a little clearer to colleagues,
and frankly, me tomorrow
after I've forgotten what I did
today, to define a variable like meows
and set it equal to three.
And then, instead of hardcoding
three here or even lower
in a much bigger program, let me just go
ahead and pass in that variable's value
to my loop.
So that now it's just
kind of obvious to me
that meows is apparently
the number of times to meow.
And if I ever want to change it,
the only code I have to change
is at the very top of my file.
I don't need to go fishing around
or figure out what's going to break,
what do I need to change.
I just know that I can change
these constants up at the top.
The problem though with Python
is that Python doesn't actually
make variables constant.
It's indeed a convention in
Python and some other languages
to at least capitalize your variables
when you want to indicate to the world
that you should not touch this.
It is constant.
But there is literally nothing in
my code preventing me from saying,
you know what?
Today I feel like four meows instead.
That would work.
In other languages
though there's typically
a keyword or some other
mechanism syntactically that
would allow you to prevent line
three currently from executing.
So that when you try to run your code,
you would actually get an error message
explicitly saying, you cannot do that.
So Python, again, is a bit
more on the honor system
when it comes to these
conventions instead.
Now, it turns out there's other
types of constants, quote unquote,
that Python typically manifests.
And in fact, let me go ahead and
change this around a little bit.
Let me delete this version of meows.
And let me introduce, again,
a class from our discussion
of object-oriented programming,
like a class representing
a cat, another real-world entity.
Recall that within classes,
you can have not just
instance variables but class variables.
That is variables inside of the class
that aren't inside of self, per se,
but they're accessible to all of
the methods inside of that class.
Here too, there's a
convention but not enforced
by Python of having class constants,
whereby inside of the class,
you might want to have a variable that
should, should, should not be changed.
But you just want to indicate that
visually by capitalizing its name.
So for instance, if the default
number of meows for a cat
is meant to be three, I can
literally inside of my class
but outside of any of
my defined methods just
create a class variable all
capitalized with that same value.
And then, if I want to
create a method, like meow,
for instance, which as an instance
method might take in self as we know.
And then, I might have my loop here
for underscore in the range of--
and now I need to access this.
The convention would be to
say cat.meows to make clear
that I want the meows variable that's
associated with the class called cat.
Then I'm going to go ahead and
print out one of these meows.
And now, at the bottom of my code,
outside of the class, let me go ahead
and do something like this.
Let me instantiate a cat
using the cat constructor.
Notice this is important.
Per our discussion of OOP, the
class is capitalized by convention.
But the variable over here is lowercase.
And I could call it
just C or anything else.
But I kind of like the symmetry of
calling it little cat here and big cat,
so to speak, over here.
And now, if I want this
particular cat to meow
that default number of three times,
I can just do cat.meow like this.
And that method meow is going to, per
line five, access that class constant.
But again, it's constant
only in the fact--
only in the sense that you should not
touch that, not that it's actually
going to be enforced by the language.
Let me go ahead then and run
this with Python of meows.py.
And there it is, three
of our meows, meow, meow.
It turns out that Python is
a dynamically typed language.
That is to say, it's not strongly typed.
Whereby when you want an int,
you have to tell the program
that you are using an int.
You don't have to tell the program
that you are using a str, or a float,
or a set, or anything else.
Generally speaking, to date, you and
I, when we're creating variables,
we just give a variable a name.
We frequently assign it using in
the equal sign some other value.
And honestly, Python
just kind of dynamically
figures out what type of variable it is.
If it's, quote unquote Hello, world,
the variable is going to be a str.
If it's 50, the integer the
variable is going to be an int.
Now, in other languages, including
C, and C++, and Java, and others,
it's sometimes necessary for the
programmer to specify what types
of variables you want something to be.
The upside of that is that it
helps you detect bugs more readily.
Because if you intend for a variable
to store a string or an integer,
but you accidentally store an integer
or a string, the opposite, or something
else altogether, your language can
detect that kind of mistake for you.
When you go, for instance,
to run the program,
it can say, no, you've made a mistake.
And you can fix that before your
actual users detect as much.
In Python too here, it's again,
more of a friendly environment
where you can provide
hints to Python itself
as to what type a variable should be.
But the language itself does
not strongly enforce these.
Rather, you can use a tool that
will tell you whether or not
you're using a variable correctly.
But it's typically a tool you
would run as the programmer
before you actually release
your code to the world.
Or if you have some kind of automated
process, you can run this kind of tool
just like you could reformat or link
to your code with some other program
before you actually
release it to the world.
So how might we go about using
these so-called type hints?
Well, they're documented in the usual
place in Python's own documentation.
And it turns out
there's a program that's
pretty popular for checking
whether or not your code is
adhering to your own type hints.
And that program here is called mypy.
And it's just one of several.
But this one is particularly
popular and can be easily installed
in the usual way with pip install mypy.
And its own documentation
is at this URL here.
But we'll use it quite simply to check
whether or not our variables are indeed
using the right types.
So how can we go about doing this?
All right, let me go back here to
VS Code, clear my terminal window,
and in fact erase meows.py
as it currently was.
And let's implement a different
version of meows that quite simply
has a function called meow that does
the actual meowing on the screen.
And then, I'm just going to go
ahead and call that function down
toward the bottom.
I'm not going to bother with a
main function just for simplicity
so that we can focus as
always only on what's new.
So here we are defining
a function called meow.
It's going to take a number of times
to meow, for instance n for number.
And inside of this
function, I'm going to do
my usual for underscore in the range
of n go ahead and print, quote unquote,
meow.
So based on our earlier code,
I think this is correct.
I've not bothered defining
the variable as i.
I'm instead using the underscore
because I'm not using it anywhere.
But I think I now have a working
function whose purpose in life
is to meow zero, or one, or
two, or three, or more times.
Well, let's use this function,
again, not bothering with main.
I'm just going to keep my function at
the very top because there's only one.
And I'm going to write
my code here on line six.
So I'm going to give myself--
I'm going to ask the user for a number.
And I'm going to go
ahead and prompt them
in the usual way for that
number of times to meow.
And now, I'm going to go ahead
and call meow on that number.
Now, some of you might see
what I've already done wrong.
But perhaps I myself don't.
So let me go into my terminal
window and run Python of meows.py,
the goal being to prompt me.
This seems to be working.
I'm going to type in three.
And I would expect now the meow
function to print out meow three times.
Enter.
But no.
There's some kind of type error here.
str object cannot be interpreted
as an integer.
Why might that be?
STUDENT: Because the input function
returns a string instead of an integer.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
The input function returns a
string or a str, not an int.
So in the past, of course,
our solution to this problem
has just been to convert the string
to an int by using the int function.
But now, let me start
programming more defensively
so that honestly, I don't even find
myself in this situation at all.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me add what's called a
type hint to my function that
explicitly specifies for meow what
type of variable should be passed in.
I'm going to go ahead now and change
the very first line of my code
and my function to specify
that n colon should be an int
and this is a type
hint, the fact that I've
added a colon, a space, and
the word int is not creating
another int or anything like that.
It's just a hint, an annotation,
so to speak to Python,
that this variable on the left
called n should be an int.
Now, unfortunately, Python
itself doesn't care.
Because again, these type hints
are not enforced by the language.
And that's by design.
The language itself and
the community prefers
that Python be dynamically
typed, not so strongly typed
as to require these things to be true.
But if I run meows.py, type in three
again, the same error is there.
But let me go about trying this mypy
program, an example of a program that
understands type hints.
And if I run it proactively myself
can find bugs like this in my code
before I, or worse, a user, actually
runs and encounters something cryptic
like this type error here.
Let me clear my terminal window and
this time run mypy space meows.py.
So I'm going to run mypy on my program,
but I'm not running Python itself.
When I hit Enter, we'll see this.
All right.
We see now that mypy found
apparently an error on line seven.
Error, argument one to meow has
incompatible type str expected int.
So it's still an error message.
But mypy is not a program
that my users would use.
This is a program that you and
I as programmers would use.
And because we have run this code
now before we, for instance, released
this program to the world, I can now see
even before the code is called or run,
oh, I seem to be using my
argument to meow wrong.
I had better fix this somehow.
Well, I can actually go
about in hints adding
type hints even to my own variables here
so as to catch this another way too.
If I know on line six that I'm creating
already a variable called number,
and I know already that I'm assigning
equal to the return value of input,
I could give mypy and tools like it
another hint and say, you know what?
This variable called number
should also be an int.
That is to say, if I now start
getting into the habit of annotating
all of my variables and
arguments to functions,
maybe mypy can actually
help me find things
quite quickly as well before I get to
the point of running Python itself.
Let's go ahead and try this again.
Mypy of meows.py and hit Enter.
And this time, notice
that mypy actually found
the mistake a little more quickly.
Notice this time it found on line
six that, error, incompatible types
and assignment expression has
type str, variable has type int.
So before I even got to
the point of calling meow,
line six, via this type hint,
when used and analyzed by mypy
has helped me find, oh, wait a minute.
I shouldn't be assigning
the return value of input
to my variable called
number in the first place.
Why?
Mypy has just pointed out to
me that one returns a str.
I'm expecting an int.
Let me fix this now instead.
So let me clear my terminal window.
And now, let me do what
most of you were probably
thinking I should have done in the
first place after all of these weeks.
But now, let me go ahead and convert
the return value of input to an integer.
For today's purposes,
I'm not going to try
to catch any exceptions or the like.
We're just going to assume that
the user types this in properly.
And now, let me go ahead
and run mypy of meows.py,
having not only added to type hints
to my argument, to my function,
to my variable down here on line six.
And I've also now fixed
the problem itself.
Let me go ahead and run mypy.
And success, no issues
found in one source file.
Now, it's more reasonable for
me to go and run something
like Python of meows and just trust
that when I type in three, at least
I'm not going to get a type error.
That is, I didn't mess up
as a programmer with respect
to the types of my variables.
Why?
Because when I wrote the
code in the first place,
I provided these
annotations, these hints
that inform tools like mypy
that my intention had better
line up with what the actual code does.
Let me pause here and see if there's
now any questions on type hints or mypy.
STUDENT: Is it common or how
common is it for those to be used?
Or is it just that it's more
used in more complex code
where it's more difficult to
ensure that you're actually
using the correct type in the way
that you're using the variables?
DAVID J. MALAN: It's a good question.
And it's rather a matter of opinion.
Python was designed to be a little
more versatile and flexible when
it comes to some of these details,
partly for writeability, to make
it easier and faster to write
code, partly for performance
so that the program
like Python doesn't have
to bother checking
these kinds of details,
we can just get right into the code.
The reality, though, is
that strong type checks
do tend to be a good thing for
the correctness of your code.
Why?
Because programs like mypy can
find, before your code is even run,
if there's already known to be an error.
And it tends to be good
for defensive programming.
So the situation essentially is
that within the Python ecosystem,
you can annotate your types in this way.
You can use tools to
use those type hints.
But to date, Python
itself does not enforce
or expect to enforce these conventions.
In larger code bases, in
professional code bases,
commercial code bases, probably
depending on the project manager
or depending on the engineering
team they may very well
want themselves to be using type hints.
Why?
If it just decreases
the probability of bugs.
In fact, let me propose now that
I-- imagine a situation where
instead of expecting that meow prints
meow, meow, meow some number of times,
suppose that I accidentally
assume that the meow function
just returns meow some number of times.
We saw, for instance when
focusing on unit tests
that it tends to be a good thing to
have functions that return values,
be it an int or a string, rather
than just having some side effect
like printing things out themselves.
So perhaps I'm still in that mindset.
And I've just assumed
mistakenly for the moment
that meow returns a value, like meow,
or meow meow, or meow meow meow,
a big string of some number of meows,
rather than just printing it itself,
as it clearly does at
the moment on line three.
And therefore, suppose that I
accidentally did something like this.
Rather than just getting the number and
passing it to meow, suppose I did this.
Suppose I declared a number of--
a new variable called meows,
the type of which I think should be str.
And suppose, again,
I assume accidentally
that meow returns to me a string
of those meows so that I myself
can then print them later.
This would be a little more conducive,
arguably, to testing my meow function.
Why?
Because I could expect that it's
returning meow, or meow meow,
or meow meow meow,
separated by new lines,
returning a str that I
could then assert equals
what I expect it to be in
something like a unit test.
I'm not going to bother
writing any unit tests now.
But let's just suppose that's
the mindset I'm now in.
And so, on line seven
I'm assuming that I
want to assign the return value of meow
to a new variable called meows which
I've annotated with this
type hint as being a str,
just so we can see another variable.
This one is not an
int but a str instead.
Well, let me go ahead and run
this code now, Python of meows.py,
Enter, typing in three.
And you'll see a curious bug.
Meow meow meow none.
Well, why is that?
Well, it turns out at the moment, my
meow function only has a side effect.
It just prints out meow
some number of times.
It doesn't explicitly
return a value as it
would if there were literally
the return keyword there.
By default then, when
a function in Python
does not explicitly return a
value, its implicit return value
is in effect none.
And so, what we're seeing
here is this-- on line eight,
because I'm assigning the return
value of meow, which is none,
to my meows variable, line three is
what's still printing meow meow meow.
And line eight is what's now
incorrectly printing none.
Because I accidentally thought that
meow returns a value, but it doesn't.
So its return value is effectively none.
So I'm printing very weirdly
the word none at the bottom.
So how could I go about catching
this kind of mistake too?
I might make this mistake.
But maybe with less
frequency if I'm in the habit
of annotating my code with this
new feature called type hints.
What you can do here is this.
Let me clear my terminal window
to get rid of that artifact.
And up here, let me additionally
specify with some funny looking syntax
that my meow function actually
by design returns none.
So you literally use
this arrow notation.
In Python when hinting what the
return value of a function is,
you would do this.
After the parentheses, a space,
a hyphen, a greater than symbol,
like an arrow, and then another space,
and then the type of the return value.
For now, it's indeed going to--
[SWALLOWS] excuse me, return none.
But now, at least I
can catch it like this.
If I now run not Python but mypy
on my code, which would be a habit
I'm now getting into
if using type hints.
Check that I'm using all of my types
correctly before I even run my program.
We'll see that now mypy has found
online seven that meow, quote unquote,
does not return a value.
And mypy knows that because I have
proactively annotated my meow function
as having none as its return value.
So now, mypy can detect that.
I should now realize, oh, wait a minute.
I'm being foolish here.
Meow clearly does not return a value.
I should not be treating it
like it does on line seven.
Let me go about actually
fixing this now.
So how do I go about fixing this?
Well, let's practice what we
preached in our focus on unit tests,
having a function like meow not have
side effects like printing itself.
But let's have it return
the actual string.
And I can actually do
this kind of cleanly.
Let me clear my error message
in my terminal window here.
Let me get rid of the loop here.
Let me say this time that OK,
fine, meow is going to return
a value, an actual str or string.
So I've changed none to str.
And now, I can implement
this in any number of ways,
maybe even using a loop.
But recall that we have this syntax
in Python, which will, I think,
solve this problem for us.
If I want to return a string of
n meows, what I can actually do,
recall, is this.
Return quote unquote meow,
backslash n, times that number n.
So it's kind of a
clever one-liner, avoids
the need for a for loop or
something more involved than that,
to just say, multiply meow backslash n
against itself three times, or n times,
in this case, in general, so that I get
back a big string of zero meows, one,
two, three, or many more meows instead.
I think now my code on line
six is actually correct.
Now I've changed meow
to behave the way I was
pretending to assume it always worked.
So I'm storing in meows plural
a variable that's of type str.
Because now, meow does have a
return value of type str itself
per this type hint as well.
All right.
Let me go ahead now and print meows.
But because each of my meows comes with
a trailing new line, the backslash n,
I'm going to proactively fix what
would be a minor aesthetic bug.
And I'm just going to avoid
outputting an extra new line
at the end of those three.
So if I run Python of meows.py now, type
in three, there's my meow meow meow.
And now, no mention of none.
Questions now on type hints,
and these annotations in mypy,
and using them to defensively write
code that just decreases hopefully
the probability of your own bugs?
STUDENT: Is the return three
set have double quotes that
have meow slash n, why the program
don't take it as a [? string? ?]
DAVID J. MALAN: Why does the program
not take it as a-- as strange?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE], yeah.
DAVID J. MALAN: So recall
that early on in the class
we looked at plus as a
concatenation operator that
allows you to join a string
on the left and the right.
Multiplication is also an
overloaded operator for strings.
Whereby if you have a string on
the left and an int on the right,
it will multiply the string, so to
speak, by concatenating or joining
that many meows all together.
So this is a feature of
object-oriented programming
and an operator overloading
as we saw it in the past.
Other questions on type hints or mypy.
STUDENT: Can we not typecast this
data type of this variable number?
DAVID J. MALAN: No.
You still-- and let me
correct the terminology.
It wouldn't be called typecasting in
this context because it's not like C
or C++ where there's an
equivalence between these types.
You're technically converting
on line five a str to an int.
You do still have to do this.
Because mypy, for
instance, would yell at you
if you were trying to assign a str
on the right to an int on the left.
You must still use the int function.
Int itself is still a function.
It's not a type hint.
But the word int is being used in
another way now in these type hints.
So this int is still a function
call as it always has been.
This syntax on the left is
another use of the keyword int
but in the form of these type hints.
So you still have to do
the conversion yourself.
All right.
Let me propose that we transition to
another feature of Python that's worth
knowing, especially since it's
one that you'll see in the wild
when you see code or libraries
that other folks have written,
namely something known as a
doc string or document strings.
It turns out in the
world of Python there
is a standardized way per another pep,
Python Enhancement Proposal, this one
257, that essentially standardizes
how you should document your functions
among other aspects of your code.
And so, for instance, let me go
back to my meows.py file here.
And let me propose that we now
start documenting this code
too so that I know what
the meow function does.
And in fact, the standard way of
doing this using doc string notation
would be as follows.
To comment this function,
not above it, as you
might be in the habit of doing with code
in general, but actually inside of it.
But instead of commenting it like
this with the usual hash comment sign,
like meow n times, it turns out
that when you're formally docking--
when you're formally documenting
a function like meow in this case,
you don't use regular inline
comments, so to speak.
You use this syntax instead.
You use triple quotation
marks, either double or single.
Then you write out your
comment, meow n times.
And then you write the
same again at the end.
So either three double quotes
at the start and the end
or three single quotes
at the start and the end.
And Python has built
into it certain tools
and certain assumptions that if it
detects that there is a comment using
this doc string format triple
quotes on the left and the right,
it will assume that that's indeed
the documentation for that function.
And it turns out in the Python
ecosystem, there's a lot of tools
that you can then use to analyze
your code automatically, extract
all of these document strings
for you, and even generate
web pages or PDFs of documentation
for your own function.
So there's these conventions
via which if you adhere to them
you can start documenting
your code as for other people
by generating automatically the
documentation from your own code
without writing something
up from scratch manually.
Now, it turns out if your
function does take arguments
and perhaps does a bit more, there
are multiple conventions for how
you can document for the
human programmers that
might be using your function,
whether it's you, or a colleague,
or someone else on the internet,
to actually use these docs
strings to standardize
the information therein.
So you might see this instead.
Using these same triple
quotes above and below now,
you might see your one-sentence
explanation of the function, meows--
meow n times.
Sometimes depending
on the style and use,
it might actually still be on the first
line but with a blank line below it.
But I'll keep everything
uniformly indented.
And this is a convention used by some
popular Python documentation tools
as well.
You would say syntax like this-- param n
colon, and then a description of what n
is, number of times to meow.
Then colon type n colon int, which
just indicates that the type of n
is an integer.
Then, if this function could
actually raise an exception,
you can document that too.
And actually, it's not really--
well, it's arguably my mistake here.
If n comes in as an argument
and is not, in fact, an int,
maybe it's a float, or a
string, or something else,
the multiplication sign
here is not going to work.
It's not going to multiply the string.
It's going to trigger what I know
from experience to be a type error.
So I'm going to go ahead and
proactively say in my own documentation
that this function, technically, if you
use it wrong could raise a type error,
even though I'm hinting up
here with this annotation
that you should pass in an int.
Again, Python doesn't enforce that.
So if you pass in a float,
this might, in fact,
raise this function a type error.
And so, that might happen
if n is not an int.
And then, lastly, I might say for
clarity's sake for other programmers,
this function returns a string
of n meows, one per line.
And the return type of that
value, r type, is going to be str.
Now, all of this syntax here as
I've used it is not Python per se.
This is a convention known
as restructured text, which
is a form of markdown-like
language that's
used for documentation, for
websites, for blogs, and even more.
But it's one of the popular
conventions within the world of Python
to document your own functions.
So this does not have anything to
do fundamentally with type hints.
Type hints are a feature of Python.
What I'm doing here is just
adhering to a third party convention
of putting in between a Python
doc string from the start
to the end a certain standard format
so that these third party tools can
analyze my code for me top
to bottom, left to right,
and ideally generate
documentation for me.
It can generate a PDF, a
web page, or something else,
so that I or my colleagues don't
need to not just only write
code but also manually create
documentation for our code.
We can keep everything together and
use tools to generate the same for us.
Any questions now on
these doc strings, which
again are a convention of
documenting your own code often
following some standard syntax?
STUDENT: Yeah.
So when you say you would
document it and put it in a PDF,
is the purpose of doing this to
publish it and share your function
so other users can use it?
DAVID J. MALAN: Absolutely.
In the past, when we have installed some
third party libraries, for instance,
cowsay a few weeks back.
Recall that I showed you
what functions it had.
But if you read the
documentation, you might actually
see that it was documented for
us by the author of that program.
Now, I don't believe they were
using this particular syntax.
But it was definitely
useful for you and me
to be able to read some web page or
PDF telling us how to use the library
rather than wasting time reading
through someone else's code
and trying to infer what functions
exist and how to use them.
It just tends to be much more
developer-friendly to have
proper documentation for our
own code or libraries as well.
Other questions?
STUDENT: Yeah.
When with doc strings, when it's
used to generate a PDF or whatever,
does it include any of the code?
So if you're referencing
in your comment,
if you're referencing the
code in the comment itself and
might not make sense
without seeing the code.
Does it-- do these include it?
DAVID J. MALAN: Short
answer, you can do that.
Not in the convention I'm using here.
But there's actually a clever
way to write in your doc strings
sample inputs to your functions and
sample outputs for your functions.
And if you use a different
tool that we've not discussed,
that tool will run your code
using those sample inputs.
It will check that your outputs
match your sample outputs.
And if not, the program will yell at
you saying, you've got a bug somewhere.
So this is just another
way where you can
use doc strings to not only document
but even catch errors in your code.
This has been a lot.
And there's a bit more to go.
Why don't we go ahead here
and take a five-minute break.
And when we resume, we'll take a look
at yet another feature of Python, yet
another library to write code faster.
All right.
Suppose we want to modify this meows
program to actually take its input not
from the input function in the blinking
prompt but from the command line.
Recall in our discussion of libraries,
that you could use something
like sys.argv to get at
command line arguments
that a human has provided when
you're running your program.
So why don't we whip
up a version of meow
that uses command line arguments
instead of, again, input.
So I'm going to go ahead and delete
what we've done here thus far.
And let me propose that we import
sys as we've done in the past.
And let's do this.
How about if the user does not
type any command line arguments.
Then my program will just
meow once, just so that it
does something visually interesting.
Otherwise, let's also
give the user an option
to specify how many times
I want the cat to meow.
So let's start simple.
Let's first of all go ahead and do this.
If the length of sys.argv
equals equals one,
that is the user only typed the name
of the program and nothing else after
the--
in their command, then let's go ahead
and just print out one meow like this.
Else for now, let's go ahead and
print out something like this.
Else go ahead and print
out, let's say, usage
for the program, which
will be usage of meows.py,
just so that the user knows that the
program itself is called meows.py.
Now let me go down to my terminal window
and start to type Python of meows.py.
And at this point, notice
that the length of sys.argv
should indeed be one.
Why?
Well, Python the name doesn't
end up in sys.argv at all ever.
But meows.py, the name of the file does.
And it's going to go in sys.argv zero.
But that's only one element.
So the length of this thing is one.
There's nothing more to the right.
So when I hit Enter now we
should see, indeed, one meow.
If I don't cooperate, suppose I do
something like meows three Enter.
Then I'm going to see a reminder
that this is how you use the program.
And this is a common convention
to literally print out
the word usage, a colon,
then the name of the program,
and maybe some explanation
of how to use it.
So I'm keeping it very simple.
But let's be a little fancier.
What if I really wanted the user to
type in maybe not three, but something
more sophisticated.
And in fact, when controlling
programs from the command line,
it's very common to provide what
are often called switches or flags,
whereby you pass in something like
dash n, which semantically means
this number of times,
then often a space,
and then something
like the number three.
This still allows me to do other
things at the command line if I want.
But the fact that I've standardized
on how I'm providing command line
arguments to this
program with dash n three
is just a more reliable
way now of my program
knowing what does the three mean.
It's a little less obvious if
I just do meows.py space three.
Well, what does the three mean?
At least with syntax like
dash n three, especially
if you've read the
documentation for this program,
ultimately, oh, dash n
means number of times.
Got it.
It's a way of passing in
two additional arguments
but that have some
relationship between them.
So how do I modify my program
to understand dash n three?
Well, if I'm using sys
like this, I could do this.
elif the length of sys.argv
equals this time three.
Because notice, there's one,
two, three things at my prompt.
So sys.argv is zero, one, and two,
three things total separated by spaces.
If it equals three--
and let's be safe, and sys.argv
bracket one equals equals dash n,
then let's go ahead and do this.
Let's go ahead and convert
sys.argv of two to an integer
and assign it to a variable,
for instance, called n.
And then, let's go ahead and do this.
For underscore in the
range of n, let's go ahead
and print out some of these meows.
Now, there's still an opportunity
maybe to consolidate my print lines
with meow.
But for now, I'm going to
keep these ideas separate.
So I'm going to handle the default case
with no arguments up here as before.
And now, more interestingly, I'm
going to do this to be clear.
I'm going to check if the user gave me
three command line arguments, the name
of the program, dash n, and a number.
If indeed the second thing they gave me
in sys.argv of 1 equals equals dash n,
then I'm going to assume that
the next thing, sys.argv of two
is going to be an integer.
And I'll convert it to such and
store it in this variable n.
And now, just using a loop, I'm going
to print out meow that many times.
All right, so it's kind of a combination
of our earlier focus on loops,
our earlier focus on
command line arguments,
just creating a program
that allow me to claim
is representative of how a lot
of command line programs work,
even though we've typically
not used many like this.
But it's very common to
configure a program, one,
you're about to run it at the
command line with something
like these command line arguments
like dash n or dash something else.
Now, I'm going to go
ahead and hit Enter.
And I think I should
see, indeed, three meows.
By contrast, if I do two at the
end, I should see two meows.
If I do one, I should see one meow.
And frankly, if I just
omit this altogether,
I should see one meow as well, because
that was my default case earlier.
And now, let me allow us to assume
that this program eventually
gets more complicated.
Let's imagine a world where I
don't want to support just dash n.
Maybe I want to support dash
a, and dash b, and dash c,
and dash d, and a whole lot of others.
Or heck, at that point, I
should maybe give them words.
So maybe it's a dash, dash, number.
It's indeed a convention
in computing typically
to use single dashes with a single
letter, like n, but use double dashes
if you're actually using
a whole word like number.
So the command line argument
might be dash n, or maybe
it's dash, dash number.
But you can imagine just how
complicated the code gets
if now you want to support dash n,
dash a, dash b, dash c, and so forth.
You're going to have to be
checking all over the place.
And what if they come
in a different order?
You're going to have to
check is dash n first,
or is it second, or is it
third, or is it's fourth?
I mean, this just becomes
very painful very quickly
just to do something relatively simple
like allow the user to pass command
line arguments into your program.
Well, this is why, as always,
there exist libraries.
And another library
that comes with Python
that's probably worth knowing something
about is this one here called argparse.
In fact, with a lot of the tools I
myself or CS50's team writes in Python,
we very frequently use
argparse whenever they
are more complicated than a lot of our
class demos and a little more similar
to this one where we want to allow the
user to pass in configuration options
at the command line.
And by supporting things like dash
n, or dash a, or dash b, or dash c,
argparse is a library
that per its documentation
just handles all of this parsing so to
speak, this analysis of command line
arguments for you
automatically so you can focus
on writing the interesting parts of
your program, not the command line
arguments part.
So how might we use this?
Well, let me go back to VS Code here.
Let me clear my terminal window.
And let me propose that I
rewrite this using not sys
but actually using argparse.
And I'm going to start a little
simple and then build back up.
So let me throw all of this away
for now and instead import argparse.
Argparse stands for argument parser.
To parse something means to read it,
kind of pick it apart to analyze it.
So this is indeed going
to do just that for me.
Now, let me go ahead and do this.
And for this library,
it's helpful to know
a little object-oriented
programming like we all now do.
I'm going to create a
variable called parser.
Though I could call it anything I want.
I'm going to set it equal to the return
value of argparse.ArgumentParser,
with a capital A and a
capital P. A constructor
for a class called argument parser
that comes with Python itself
within this library here.
Now, I'm going to configure
this argument parser
to know about the specific
command line arguments
that I myself want to
support in my program.
So I'm going to do this,
parser.add_argument.
So that's apparently a
method in the parser object.
I'm going to add an argument of dash n.
Easy enough.
Now I'm going to go ahead and actually
parse the command line arguments.
I'm going to do args, or I
could call the variable anything
I want, parser.parseargs.
And by default, parseargs is going to
automatically look at sys.argv for me.
I don't need to import sys myself.
I can leave the argument parser, its
code to import sys, look at sys.argv,
and figure out where dash n
or anything else actually is.
And what's nice now,
because this line of code
here results in the parser having parsed
all of the command line arguments,
I now have this object in this
variable called args inside
of which are all of the
values of those command
line arguments, no matter
what order they appeared in.
Not such a big deal when I've
only got one because it's only
going to go in one place at the end.
But if I've got dash n,
dash a, dash b, dash c,
you could imagine them being
in all different orders.
They definitely don't
have to be alphabetical.
The user should be able to type
them in any order they want.
That's better for usability.
Arg parser is going to figure
all of that out for me.
And all I have to do now is this.
If I want to iterate over
that many numbers of arguments
and that many meows
rather, I can do this.
For underscore in the range of
the int conversion of args.n.
So dot is the syntax we
kept using to access things
like properties inside of an object.
And that's what args is.
It's the object returned by
the parse args function for me.
I'm going to go ahead now and print out,
quote unquote, meow this many times.
So it's not super simple.
These are three new lines of code I
need to write and rather understand.
But it's already a little
simpler and more compact
than my if, and my elif, and my ors, and
my ands, and all of that Boolean logic.
It's handling a lot of this for me.
So if I didn't make any mistakes, let
me run Python now of meows.py Enter.
And I did make a mistake here.
I did make a mistake.
What's wrong here now?
What's wrong?
Well, I definitely didn't
run it the way I intend.
So dash n three Enter.
So it does work.
But if I don't cooperate, this
actually seems to be a worse version.
If I don't pass in dash n and a number,
it just errors with a type error.
Int must be a string.
None is what came back.
So there's clearly an error here.
But the library is more flexible.
I can actually provide some
documentation on how to use this thing.
So how do I know how to use this?
Well, typically it's
conventional in Python
and in a lot of programming
environments to run a program
with a special argument,
dash h or dash dash help.
And almost always I
will claim you'll then
see some kind of usage information.
And indeed, that's what
I'm looking at now.
I just ran Python of
meows.py space dash h.
I'll do it again.
Let me clear my screen and this time
do dash dash help in English, Enter.
And I see the same thing.
It's not very useful at the moment.
It just shows me what
the usage is up here.
And this is kind of interesting.
This is a standard syntax in computing.
And we've kind of seen it in
Python's documentation before.
This just means that the program's
name is, of course, meows.py.
Square brackets as almost always in
documentation means it's optional.
So I don't have to
type dash h, but I can.
I don't have to type dash n
and another value, but I can.
And then, down here is some
explanation of these options,
and more verbosely
showing me that I can also
do dash dash help and not just dash h.
But this is so generic.
This has nothing to do with my program.
This is not going to help
my users when I actually
release this software for the world.
So let me go ahead and improve it.
Let me add a description to my argument
parser that the humans will see.
Meow like a cat, quote unquote, is
going to be the value of this named
parameter called description.
And let me also add a help
parameter to my dash n
argument that just explains what dash
n means, number of times to meow,
quote unquote.
I'm not going to change anything else.
But I am going to go back to my
terminal window and run Python of meow.
I'm going to run Python of meows.py
dash h, or equivalently dash dash help.
And now notice that this is
a little more user friendly.
If I scroll up, we still
see the same usage.
But there's a quick sentence
in English of explanation
that this program meows like a cat.
And if I look at the options
now, oh, that's what n means.
It's the number of times to meow.
And this capital N, a mental
variable, if you will,
is just indicating to me that I
need to type a number by convention
after the lower case dash n.
So it would be nice
though, all that said,
if my program still didn't just break
when I run it without any command line
arguments.
Ideally, my program would handle
this just like my manual version
did when I used sys.argv myself.
So we just need to add a little
more functionality to this library.
And if I read the documentation,
I'll see that add argument
takes yet another named argument.
If you want, you can specify a default
value for dash n, for instance, one.
And I'll do that there.
And you can further specify
that it's got to be an int.
And what this will
additionally allow me to do
is if I tell arg parser to make sure
that the value of dash n is an int,
I don't need to do the
conversion manually.
I can just trust down
on line seven that when
I access the property called
n inside of my args object,
it's going to be
automatically an int for me.
And again, this is the
value of a library.
Let it do all of the work
for you so you can get back
to focusing on the
interesting project at hand,
whatever problem it is
you're trying to solve.
In this case, granted, not that
interesting, but meowing like a cat.
Let me go ahead now and run
Python of meows.py and hit Enter.
This time, no arguments.
And now it meows.
Why?
Because I specified that if I
don't, as a user, specify dash n,
it's going to have a default
value of one apparently.
And I don't have to convert
that value from a str to an int
because I told arg parser please
just make this an int for me.
Any questions now on argparse,
or really this principle
of just outsourcing the commodity
stuff, the stuff that everyone's program
eventually needs to do so that you
can focus on the juicy part yourself.
STUDENT: What does args.n contain?
DAVID J. MALAN: What
does args.n contain?
It contains the integer that the human
typed after a space after dash n.
Good question.
Other questions?
STUDENT: Yeah.
When you specify the type
for the argument, what
happens if-- does that basically
handle the exception if the user inputs
a string in this case?
DAVID J. MALAN: A really good question.
Suppose that the human does not type
a number and therefore not an in.
Well, let's see what happens.
So Python of meows.py dash n dog,
where dog is obviously not a number.
Enter.
And voila, we see an automatically
generated error message.
A little cryptic, admittedly.
But I'm seeing a reminder
of what the usage is
and a minor explanation of
what is invalid about this.
And again, this is what
allows you, this is
what allows me to focus on writing
the actual code we care about
and just letting the library
automate some of this stuff for us.
All right.
Well, allow me to propose now that
we take a look at one other feature
of Python that we've seen before.
But it turns out we can use it even
more powerfully as our programs become
more sophisticated and the problems
we're trying to solve themselves become
more involved.
Let me go ahead and turn to
VS Code, closing out meows.py,
and creating a new file for
instance, called unpack.py.
So code of unpack.py.
And let me just remind us
what we mean by unpacking.
Because this is actually a feature
of Python that we've seen before.
For instance, suppose that
I write a program that
prompts the user for their
name, like David space Malan.
Wouldn't it be nice if we
could split the user's name
into two separate variables?
And when we've done this in the past,
we've done it in a few different ways.
But one of them involved unpacking a
single value that comes back from that,
like a list or some
other data structure,
and putting it immediately
into two variables.
So let's do this here.
Let me go ahead and
call the input function,
asking someone what's
your name, question mark.
Then, let me go ahead and just split
a little naively on a single space.
So I'm assuming that the
only users at the moment
are people like me, David space Malan.
No middle names, no multiple names.
It's just one and two, which itself
could be buggy for other users.
But for now, I'm keeping it
simple, just to remind us
that I can now unpack that return
value with something like first
underscore last equals
the return value of input.
And now I can go ahead and
do something like this,
like printing out with an f string,
Hello, comma, and then in curly braces,
first.
If I just want to greet myself or
any other user as, Hello, David,
without the last name.
And frankly, if I'm not
using the last name,
recall that a Python convention is just
to name it underscore to make clear
that you know you're
not using that value.
But it does need to be there because
you're unpacking two values at once.
So if I run this, it won't
be all that unfamiliar.
I'm just going to run
now Python of unpack.py.
I'll type in David Malan,
which has a single space.
And there we have it,
Hello, comma, David.
Well, it turns out that there's
other ways to unpack values.
And there's other features
that Python offers, especially
when it comes to defining
and using functions.
And this is slightly more
intermediate functionality,
if you will, that's
useful, because you can
start to write even more elegant
and powerful code once you
get comfortable with syntax like this.
So let me go ahead and propose
that we not just play with,
Hello names anymore, but
instead do something maybe
involving some coinage again.
So maybe not dollars
and cents, but maybe,
again, as in the past,
some galleons, and sickles,
and knuts which among which there's
a mathematical relationship as
to how many of those in the
wizarding world equal each other.
And let me go ahead and do this.
Let me define a simple function
called total that just tells me
the total value of someone's vault in
Gringotts, the wizarding bank, based
on how many galleons, sickles,
and knuts that they have,
which again, are currencies from
the wizarding world as opposed
to our actual human world.
So this total function might take a
variable like galleons and sickles
and knuts like this.
And then, it's going to return
the formula, which I admittedly
had to look up myself.
And it turns out that the formula
for converting galleons and sickles
to knuts would be this.
Galleons times 17 plus sickles, then
times all of that by 29 and then
add in the individual knuts.
Not sure in what detail this
came up in the books or movies.
But here we have it,
the official formula.
All right.
Now let's go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and call the total
function with just some sample inputs.
Suppose that someone like Harry has
100 galleons, 50 sickles, and 25 knuts.
Let me go ahead and print
that out on the screen.
Well, if total returns an integer,
which I think this arithmetic expression
will do, let me go ahead and store,
rather, pass the return value of total
to print.
And then just for clarity, let
me write knuts at the end So?
I know that the unit of measure
here is indeed knuts in total.
Now, let me go ahead
in my terminal window
and run Python of
unpack.py and hit Enter.
And it turns out mathematically
that if I got my math correct,
100 galleons plus 50 sickles plus 25
knuts equals in total 50,775 knuts.
Just avoiding having to use
our own human currency here.
But I'm not doing anything along the
lines of unpacking at least just yet.
Let me propose now that I do this.
Just for the sake of
discussion, let me propose
that I leave the total function as is.
But let me go ahead and just
store all of my coins in a list.
So coins in order from left
to right, 100, 50, 25, it
just because for whatever
purposes in this story
I have all of my coinage
in a list in this order.
Kind of a purse or wallet of sorts.
Well, how can I pass this in?
Well, I'm not going to
hard-code the same values twice.
Just for the sake of
discussion, how could I
pass in the individual elements
of a list to my total function?
Well, of course, I could
treat this list as I always
do using numeric indices by
doing coins bracket zero,
coins bracket one, coins bracket two.
So this is old-school stuff with lists.
If I've got a list called coins
and there's three elements,
the indices or indexes of those elements
are zero, one, and two respectively
from left to right.
So all I'm doing here now is
passing in the first element
from that list as galleons, the second
element of that list as sickles,
and the third element of
this list as my knuts.
And that lines up with,
of course, the signature
of this function, which as total
expects that I've passed in those three
things in that order left to right.
Let me go ahead and run, just
to make sure I haven't broken
anything, unpack.py and hit Enter.
And the math still checks out.
But this is getting a little verbose--
a little verbose.
And wouldn't it be nice if I
could just pass the list of coins
to this total function?
Wouldn't it be nice if I could just
say something like this, coins.
But let me pause and ask the group,
why would this not actually work as is?
It technically is passing in all three.
But why would I get some kind
of error when I run this?
Eric?
STUDENT: Because you are
passing a list to galleons.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I'm passing a list to galleons
and nothing for sickles and knuts.
And notice, those don't
have default values.
There's no equal signs
on that first line
of code, which means
Python is not going to know
what value should be assumed there.
So it just seems like
it's not going to work.
Plus, it's the wrong
type, as Eric notes.
It's a list and it's not an
integer as it was before.
So let's actually run
this incorrect version,
Python of unpack.py Enter, type error.
And that is probably
what you might expect,
like I'm messing up with the types here.
And I am required to pass in two
positional arguments, sickles
and knuts, that were not even passed.
So I've definitely erred here.
But it certainly seems unfortunate
if the only solution to this
is to do what I previously did, which
is index into the first element, index
into the second element,
index into the third.
You can imagine, with bigger
fancier functions that
take even more arguments, this is
going to get very verbose and honestly
very vulnerable, potentially, to
just mistakes, typos on my part.
But here too is where you
can do what's known, again,
as unpacking a value in Python.
Right now, a list is packed
with multiple values.
My current list has these three
values, 100, 50, and 25 respectively.
But they're all packed
up in this one list.
Wouldn't it be nice if I
could unpack that list,
just like I previously unpacked the
return value of the str class's split
function into multiple things too.
And indeed, I can do just that.
Python actually allows me to
pass in not coins but star coins.
So if you use a single asterisk
at the beginning of your variable,
that will unpack it.
And it will take one sequence,
in this case coins of size three,
and explode it, if you will, unpack
it into three individual arguments.
No commas are needed.
Python just handles this for you.
But the effect of
passing in star coins is
to pass in the individual
members of that list.
Which in this case are going to
be 100, 50, and 25 respectively.
Which is perfect, because now it's
going to line up with galleons,
sickles, knuts respectively.
So now when I run Python of
unpack.py, we're back in business
and the math checks out.
But I've cleaned up my code by just
introducing this new symbol, which
we've used, of course, in other contexts
for multiplication and the like.
But now, it's also used
for unpacking in this way.
Questions on what we've just done?
It's a single operator, but
it's already quite powerful.
Because it allows us to take
a data structure and unpack it
and pass it in individually.
STUDENT: Does that work for tuples,
sets, dicts, dictionaries as well?
DAVID J. MALAN: Tuples, yes.
Sets I don't know.
[? Ranshin? ?] I don't
know if order is preserved.
No.
Oh, is that no it does
not, or you're checking?
Order's not preserved.
So it wouldn't work with set?
It does not work with set.
Does not work with set.
Sorry, I'm verbally googling here
just to save us some keystrokes.
So it would work for enumerations
that where order is indeed preserved.
And we'll see another
example in a moment
where it actually can be used in
a different way for dictionaries,
which nowadays do preserve order.
Other questions on
unpacking in this way?
STUDENT: Yes.
Hi.
DAVID J. MALAN: Hello.
STUDENT: Can you use unpacking to
get the value, for example 10 plus 50
plus 25 instead of a for
loop and then result plus?
DAVID J. MALAN: Short answer, no.
If you want the individual values, you
should be just indexing, in this case,
into those specific locations.
This is returning multiple values, the
equivalent of a comma separated list.
So you would use the
earlier approach if you
cared about the individual locations.
How about one other
question on unpacking?
STUDENT: What if we have declared--
we declare some default values.
And if you use this as two points, will
it go out right, or will it skip it?
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
If I heard you right,
what if, for instance,
the list has four values like this
here and you're still unpacking it
when it's only three that's expected.
Well, let's try it.
Python of unpack.py Enter.
Another type error.
This time it takes three positional
arguments but four were given.
So the onus is on us as the programmer
not to do that in this case.
So potentially fragile,
but avoidable if I'm
controlling the contents of this list.
In fact, let me propose now that we
take a look at another variant of this.
Whereby we use not just
positional arguments,
whereby we trust that the first is
galleons, the second is sickles,
the third is knuts.
Suppose that we actually passed in the
names as we're allowed to do in Python.
And then, technically, we
could pass them in in any order
and Python would figure it out
using named parameters instead.
Well, how might I do this?
Well, it's going to be a bit
of a regression at first.
So let me get rid of this list here.
Let me change this now to just manually
passing the values I care about.
Galleons I want to still equal 100.
Sickles I want to equal 50.
And knuts I want to equal 25.
So this is old-school parameter passing.
It's no longer positional.
I'm explicitly specifying
the names of these arguments.
But that's just going
to work because that's
exactly what the names of these
parameters are in my total function
as before.
Let's make sure I, nonetheless,
did not break anything.
Let's run Python of unpack.py Enter.
And there we have it,
still 50,775 knuts.
Well, once you start giving things
names and values, names and values,
that probably should bring to mind
one of our most versatile data
structures in Python and even other
languages, that of a dictionary.
Remember that a dictionary is just a
collection of key value pairs, names
and their respective values.
So this kind of opens up an opportunity.
What if I did this.
What if I actually had for some
reason in my program on a variable
as before called coins.
But instead of making it a list
of three values like before,
what if it's a proper dictionary?
So what if it's galleons, quote
unquote, colon 100 for 100 of those,
sickles quote unquote and 50 of those,
and knuts quote unquote 25 of those,
each of those separated by colons.
And let me fix my square
brackets to this time
be curly braces, which, recall, is
the symbol we use for dictionaries
or dict objects in Python.
So now, I have a
dictionary called coins.
Not a list.
It's a collection of keys and values,
three keys, galleons, sickles, knuts,
and three values, 100,
50, and 25 respectively.
If I were to now pass these individual
values into my total function,
I could do it as always
with my dictionary.
So I'm doing it old-school now.
Coins is the name of my dictionary.
I index into it not with numbers
like with lists, but with words.
So galleons, strings like
this, coins, quote unquote,
sickles in square brackets there.
And then lastly, coins, square
brackets, quote unquote, knuts.
So it's getting-- it's verbose again.
This is not maybe the
best road to go down.
But we'll backpedal in a moment.
This is just how, if you happen
to have all of your coins stored
in a dictionary, you could pass
the galleons, sickles, and knuts
into your function respectively.
Let's make sure I didn't break anything.
Let's rerun Python of
unpack.py, and we're still good.
Now, how could we get to
a situation like this?
Well, as always, imagine this program
is a little longer than this one here.
And somehow you're
using a dictionary maybe
just to keep track of
someone's purse or wallet,
like how many coins of
each type that they have.
And as such, it's perfectly
reasonable to use a dictionary.
But then you want to
print out the total.
And darn it.
If that total function does not expect
a dictionary so you cannot just do
something nice and simple
like pass in coins.
For reasons we saw earlier,
that would be a type error.
Total expects three
arguments, three integers.
You can't just pass in a dictionary.
But if that's the data structure you're
using to store the person's purse
or wallet, well, it's
kind of unfortunate
that we have this clash
between these data types.
Well, here's what we can do.
We can't pass in coins.
Because watch, if I try doing
that and run Python of unpack.py,
we're getting another type error.
Missing two required
positional arguments.
Sickles and knuts, I have
to pass in three things.
But, wonderfully, Python allows
you to unpack dictionaries as well.
For a dictionary, you don't use
a single asterisk, you use two.
And what this syntax
has the effect of doing
is passing in three values with names.
It has the effect of passing
in galleons equals 100 comma,
sickles equals 50
comma, knuts equals 25.
And so, it has the similar
effect to the list unpacking.
But that just passed in the values, 100,
50, 25 separated by commas in effect.
When unpacking a dictionary,
it passes in the keys
and the values separated
conceptually with equal signs
just like our function expects.
So if I now run Python of
unpack.py again, we're still good,
but we've tightened our code up again.
And now, I'm giving
myself yet another option.
I can either store a wizard's
purse or wallets in their--
in a list as we did earlier.
Or I can store it in a little
more versatility-- with even more
specificity using a dictionary instead.
And so, to be clear, let me rewind.
Star star coins is the
same thing if I rewind
a little bit to our first
example of named arguments
is equivalent to what
I've highlighted here.
When you unpack a dictionary,
it passes in all of the keys
and all of the values
much like the syntax here.
But let me tighten it up
and go to where we left off.
Questions now on unpacking?
STUDENT: Can we have
a-- in this dictionary,
can we have instead of having a
constant name value pair, can we have
a variable number of name value pairs?
DAVID J. MALAN: Short answer, yes.
You can have more than three
key value pairs as I have here.
But it's not going to work unpacking
it if the total function is
expecting only three.
So if I were to add something
here, like let me introduce pennies
to the wizarding world.
And suppose I have one
penny, for instance.
And now I run this same code, Python of
unpack.py, we're back to a type error
again.
Whereby I got an unexpected
keyword argument pennies,
because that is not expected
by the total function.
We will see in just a moment,
wonderfully, a solution though to that.
But for now, it does not work.
Other questions on unpacking
with dictionaries or lists?
STUDENT: In list-- in list values,
we gave the same number of arguments
and we declared a default
value in the function.
Now, if you use this asterisk,
will it overwrite that value
or will it skip that default value?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
If we did have default
values up here, for instance,
equals zero, equals zero,
equals zero, the upside of that,
recall, from our discussion of
arguments to functions a while back,
is that now you don't have to
pass in all of those values.
They will default to those zeros.
Therefore, you could pass
in fewer than three values,
either using a list or a dictionary
that's unpacked in this scenario.
I deliberately did not do that
because I wanted us to encounter
this specific error in this case.
But you could absolutely go
back and add those defaults.
So it turns out that this single
asterisks or this double asterisk
is not only used in the
context of unpacking.
That same syntax is actually used
as a visual indicator in Python
when in a function
itself might very well
take a variable number of arguments.
That is to say, a
function can be variadic.
Which means that it doesn't
necessarily have to take, say,
three arguments specifically.
Even if they do or don't
have default values,
it can take maybe zero,
or one, or two, or three.
And it turns out the syntax for
implementing the same idea is
quite similar in spirit.
In fact, let me go back to VS Code here.
And let me propose that we
start over with this code
and get rid of our notion of
galleons, and sickles, and knuts,
and do something just a little
more generic just so that we've
seen the syntax for this.
Suppose that I define
a function as follows.
Define a function, let's call it f.
And that function is not going to
take a specific number of arguments
but a variable one.
And so, I'm going to go ahead
and use this syntax here,
star args, which indicates that
this function is indeed variadic.
It takes some variable number
of positional arguments.
Positional in the sense that they
go typically from left to right.
But I don't know how many
just yet I want to support.
Suppose that I additionally
want to support
some number of keyword
arguments, that is,
named parameters that
can be called optionally
and individually by their own name.
Well, the convention
syntactically here would
be to use two stars and then kwargs.
I could call args, or kwargs,
anything else that I want.
But a convention you'll frequently
see in Python's own documentation
is that when you have placeholders
like this for some number of arguments
and some number of keyword arguments,
the world tends to use args and kwargs.
Well, inside of this function, let's
do something super simple just for now.
Let me go ahead and print out
literally quote unquote positional,
just to indicate to myself while
wrapping my mind around what's
going on here what the
positional arguments are.
And let me quite simply
print out those args.
This is not something
you would typically do.
You don't typically just
take in these arguments
and print them, no matter
how many there are.
I'm just doing this diagnostically for
now to show you how the syntax works.
Now, let me go ahead at
the bottom of my file--
and I won't bother with a main
function this time so we can focus only
on this function f.
Let me go ahead and just
call f with three arguments.
I'll use the same arguments as before.
But I didn't bother giving them
names just yet, like galleons,
and sickles, and knuts, and the like.
So what do I have?
A program that no matter
what calls this function f,
but it first defines f
at the top of the file.
It's taking some number
of positional arguments,
some number of named arguments.
And for the moment, I'm just
printing out the positional ones.
Let me go ahead and
in my terminal window
run Python of unpack.py and hit Enter.
And you'll see that the
positional arguments passed in
are apparently this--
a sequence, 100, 50, 25.
But notice this.
If I clear my terminal window
there and pass in something else,
like five, a fourth argument.
Previously, if I tried to
change the number of arguments
I'm passing in to my total function,
which was only defined as taking three,
I would have gotten a type
error, some visual indication
that, no, you can't pass
in more or fewer arguments
than is actually in the
function's definition.
But now watch.
If I run Python of
unpack.py, this time passing
in 100, 50, 25, and 5, a fourth
argument, all four of those
went through just fine.
I can get rid of all of those but one,
for instance now, rerun my program
after clearing my screen.
And now, I'll see just
one argument here.
And even though there's a
comma and nothing after it,
this is actually the syntax when
seeing a tuple, in effect, whereby
the comma just indicates
this is indeed a list,
but there's only one element therein.
Well, let's get a
little more curious too.
Let me go ahead and
rewind here to where we
started with just those three values.
And this time, let me go ahead and print
out my named argument, so to speak,
which isn't args but kwargs.
Again, the positional args
in this syntax come first.
The named arguments, kwargs come second.
That's what Python prescribes.
So now, let me go ahead and
not pass in just these numbers.
Let me go ahead and pass in
actually named arguments.
So let me do something now more
specifically, like galleons equals 100,
and sickles equals 50,
and knuts equals 25.
I'm not going to bother
doing any math with total.
I just want to poke around right
now at this functionality of having
a variable number of arguments.
And what's neat now is if I run Python
of unpack.py and hit Enter, no problem.
What kwargs is, is
automatically a dictionary that
contains all of the named arguments
that were passed to my function.
Which is to say, when
designing your own functions,
if you want to support
more than one argument,
maybe more than two, or three, or four,
maybe a variable number of arguments,
indeed, you can support both a
variable number of positional arguments
that are just value comma value
comma value, or any number of named
arguments, where you actually
put the name of the parameter
equals the value and then maybe a
comma and some more of the same.
So now, it turns out we have seen
this before in some of the functions
we've used to date.
We didn't necessarily see it called args
or necessarily see it called kwargs.
But we have seen at least one
example of this in the wild.
Recall our old friend print, which
we've been using now for weeks.
And when we first looked at
the documentation for print way
back when, it looked a
little something like this.
The first argument to print was objects.
And I waved my hand at the
time at the asterisk that
was at the start of that variable name.
But then we had sep for separator, the
default value of which was a space.
We had n, the default value
of which was a new line.
And then some other names arguments
that we waved our hands at then
and I'll again do now.
But what you can now perhaps
infer from our emphasis
on these asterisks today, the
single stars or the double stars,
is that you know what?
This is the convention
in Python's documentation
to indicate that print takes a
variable number of arguments.
So if we were to look at the
actual implementation of the print
function implemented by
Python's own authors,
it might very well look
something like this.
Def print, and then
the first our argument
would be star objects,
thereby indicating that print
takes a variable number of arguments.
The next one of which might
be sep equals quote unquote
either using double quotes or as in
the documentation single quotes too.
The next one of which might be n, the
default value of which is a new line.
And then some of those
other named arguments
that we've not looked at as well.
And then, maybe inside
of the print function
implemented by the
authors of Python, maybe
there's a for loop like
for object in objects
that allows them to iterate over each
of those variable number of objects
and print each of them.
And this is why in
programs past, you and I
have been able to do just print
open parentheses close parenthesis
with nothing inside.
Or you and I have been
able to print out something
like, Hello, world, a single
string inside of those parentheses.
Or you and I have been able
to do a single string, Hello,
and then another string
quote unquote world,
thereby passing in two
arguments or even more.
So we've long had this ability
to use variadic functions,
whereby you can pass in a
variable number of arguments.
What you now have via this
args and kwargs syntax--
but again, they do not
need to be called that-- is
the ability using that star or two stars
to implement those kinds of functions
yourself.
My own f function a moment ago did
not do anything all that interesting.
But it hints at how you
could, if in the future
you have a use case, for taking zero or
one or more of either type of argument.
Any questions now on
these types of arguments?
STUDENT: What will happen if you print
kwargs and the argument is like a list?
DAVID J. MALAN: Ah.
So what would happen if you print
the argument like it's a list?
So I think we saw that.
If I roll back in my history here
to when I had that f function.
Which I called f just to
be very generic just so
we could play around with the syntax.
This is what I had here.
So this is a--
I passed in 100 comma 50 comma 25.
That gets automatically stored in args.
And when I run it, you can actually
see that sequence of values
by running Python of unpack.py.
There is that sequence all in
the form of one single variable.
I'm printing it just
for diagnostic purposes.
This is not really a
useful or pretty program.
But it hints at how we can access
that whole sequence of values.
Other questions on this approach here?
STUDENT: Can we pass the kwargs from
one function to another function?
DAVID J. MALAN: Absolutely.
You can pass either of those
to another function, which
you might want to do if you
want to wrap another function,
provide some additional
functionality, but still
pass in all of the supported arguments
to the underlying function as well.
All right.
How about this next.
It turns out that a few other
tools we can add to your tool kit
relate to the types of programming
models that Python supports.
We started out quite some
time ago focusing really
on procedural programming in Python.
Whereby we wrote code top to bottom,
left to right, defining some functions,
or if you will,
procedures along the way,
defining variables, and
having side effects,
and assigning values as needed.
But we then eventually
introduced or really revealed
that Python is also very
much object-oriented.
And a lot of those variables,
a lot of those types
that we were using all that
time were in fact objects,
objects that came from certain classes.
And those classes were
templates of sorts, blueprints,
via which you could encapsulate
both data and functionality therein.
Well, we also saw along
the way some hints
of a third paradigm of
programming that Python also,
to some extent, supports, which is
known as functional programming.
Whereby functions are
ever more powerful in that
they tend not to have side effects, no
printing or changing of state globally.
But rather, they're
completely self-contained
and might take as inputs
and return values.
And that's generally a paradigm we
saw when we started sorting things,
particularly with functions
like our sort function
or Lambda function when
we passed in the function
we wanted to use to sort
a list way back when.
Well, it turns out Python
has other functionality that
is reminiscent of functional
programming and indeed is a powerful way
to solve problems a little
more differently still.
Let me propose this.
Let me propose that I whip up
a new program here in VS Code
by closing our unpack.py and this time
creating another program called yell.
Suppose the goal at hand is to implement
some program that allows the user
to pass an input, and
then it yells the response
by forcing everything to uppercase.
My apologies to those
with headphones there.
I'll modulate.
So let me go ahead and
run code of yell.py.
And within yell.py, let's
go ahead and implement
a program that really does just that.
Let's go ahead and define
a main function up here.
And let's assume for the moment that
this yell function already exists
and yell something like, This is CS50,
properly capitalized, not in all caps.
Now, let's go ahead and implement
this yell function with def yell.
It's going to take, for now,
a single word or phrase.
And let's go ahead.
And I'll call it phrase here.
And I'm going to go ahead and
just print out the phrase.upper.
So phrase.upper is going to force
the hole thing to uppercase.
And as usual, down here if
the name of this file equals
equals quote unquote main, then let's
go ahead, as always, and call main.
So let's just run this.
But for the most part, it should
be fairly straightforward.
When I run Python of yell.py, THIS
IS CS50 is yelled on the screen.
All right, that's nice.
But it's not great that yell
only expects a single phrase.
Wouldn't it be nice,
like print, if I could
pass in one phrase, or two, or three,
or really multiple words more generally
but as individual words themselves.
So let me retool this a little bit and
change yell to take in not a phrase
but how about something
like a list of words.
So that ultimately, I
can call yell like this.
Quote unquote, this inside of a list,
quote unquote, "This" inside of a list,
and, quote unquote,
"CS50" inside of a list.
I'm not going to bother with type
hints or annotations for now.
But I'll just assume that yell has been
defined now as taking a list of words
as defined here.
But now I want to force
them all to lowercase.
So I don't quite want to do
something as simple as this.
Like for word in words, I could,
for instance, print that given word
and maybe end the line
with nothing right now.
But I think if I do this, Python
of yell.py, no, that's not right.
I haven't forced anything to uppercase.
So let's fix this.
Well, let's go ahead
and do the following.
Let me go ahead and accumulate
the uppercase words as follows.
Let me create a variable
called uppercase
and initialize it to an empty list
using square brackets or our more
verbose list syntax.
And now, let me go ahead and iterate
over each of those words in words.
And for each of them, let's go into
our upper cased list, append to it
the current words uppercase version.
So this is a way of creating
a new list called uppercase
that is just appending,
appending, appending to that list
each of the current words in
the loop but uppercased instead.
And now, just let me go ahead and
print out the uppercased list.
This isn't quite right.
Let's see what happens here.
Python of yell.py, OK.
It's not quite right,
because I don't think I want
those quotes or those square brackets.
What am I seeing?
I'm actually printing a list.
But, but, but, here's where some of
our unpacking syntax now can be useful.
I don't have to change my
approach to this problem.
I can just unpack uppercase
by adding a single star.
And now, let me go ahead
and rerun Python of yell.py.
And now, it's actually just English.
There's no remnants of Python
syntax like the quotes,
and the commas, and the square brackets.
I've now unpacked, this is CS50 as
three separate arguments to print.
So already now, this unpacking
technique would seem to be useful.
Well, it's a little
unfortunate that I now
need to call yell though with
a list of values in this way.
This is just not the norm.
Or it's at least, it's not
nearly as user-friendly
as something like the
print function where
I can pass in zero, or one, or two,
or three, or any number of arguments.
Why are you making me for your
yell function pass in only a list?
Well, we can do better.
Let's adopt some of the new
conventions we've learned.
And let's go ahead and get rid of the
list by removing the square brackets.
And let's just pass
yell three arguments.
Now, I don't want to do something
like change the definition of words
to take in word one, word two.
That's not going to
scale and it's not going
to handle different number of words.
But we have a technique now.
We can say star args, which
will allow the yell function
to accept any number of arguments.
And just for specificity, let's
not call it generically args.
Let's name it something a little more
self explanatory like star words.
This just means I have a variable
number of words being passed in.
Now, I think, I've made
a marginal improvement.
Let me run this again,
Python of yell.py.
This is CS50 is in all caps.
But it's just a little better.
Because now I can treat yell just
like I've long treated print,
pass in as many things as you
want, and print will deal with it.
Now, my yell function is just
as powerful it would seem.
And better still, it also
forces everything to uppercase.
Well, it turns out Python
comes with this function called
map, whose purpose in life is to
allow you to map, that is, apply
some function to every element
of some sequence like a list.
So for instance, if we want to force
to uppercase each of the words,
this is CS50 in the list of words
that's been passed in, well,
we essentially want to map the upper
case function to each of those values.
So using map in Python
can I do just that?
Let me go back here to VS Code.
And let me propose now that I
re-implement this as follows.
I get rid of all three of these
lines here, getting rid of that loop
in particular.
Let me still declare a
variable called uppercased.
But let me set it equal to the return
value of this new function called map.
Map takes two arguments here.
In this case, the name of
a function that I want to
map on to a sequence of values.
Well, what function do I want to apply
to every word that's been passed in?
Well, it turns out,
thanks to my knowledge
now of object-oriented programming,
I know that in the str class
there is a function called upper.
We've usually called it by
using the name of a string
variable.upper open paren close paren.
But if you read the
documentation for the str class,
you'll see that the function is
described indeed as str.upper.
I'm not using parentheses, open
and close, at the end of str.upper.
Because I don't want to call it now.
I want to pass this function
to the map function,
so that map can somehow add those
parentheses, so to speak, and call it
on every one of these words.
And this is what map
does quite powerfully,
and is an instance, indeed,
of functional programming.
Whereby I'm passing to this
map function another function.
Not calling it.
I'm just passing it in
by a reference of sorts.
And what map is going to do for me
is iterate over each of those words,
call str.upper on each of
those words, and return
to me a brand new list containing all
of those results together in one list.
It completely obviates the need for
me to do this more manually using
that list.
I'm still going to print the
whole thing using star uppercase.
So that if I get back a list
of three uppercase words,
I'm going to unpack them
and print them all out.
So let's run this again.
Python of yell.py Enter.
And voila, it's still working.
But the code now is even more tight--
even tighter than before.
So it turns out there's
another way we can
solve this problem in
a way that's even more
Pythonic, or at least quite common.
And that's using a feature
known as a list comprehension.
And it's a big phrase, if you will.
But it refers to the
ability in Python for you
to very easily construct a list
on the fly without using a loop,
without calling append and
append, but to do everything
in one, daresay, elegant one-liner.
So how can I go about using this
notion of a list comprehension?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
In yell.py, in VS Code
here, let me go ahead
and change my approach as follows.
Instead of using map, which is
perfectly fine and correct in this way,
let me just show you
this other way as well.
A list comprehension is the
opportunity to create a list like this,
using square brackets like this.
But inside of those square brackets
to write a Python expression,
that in effect is going to dynamically
generate a brand new list for you
using some logic you've written.
And the approach I
might take here is this.
If I want to store in this list
the uppercase version of every word
in that words list, I can do this--
word.upper for word in words.
Now, this is a mouthful.
But I dare say Python
programmers love this capability
of being able to define on
the fly a list inside of which
is any number of values that you would
ordinarily, at least as we've done it,
construct with a loop and again
calling append, and append, and append.
But that usually takes two,
three, four or more lines.
This list comprehension
that I've highlighted here
is now an alternative way to
create the exact same thing--
a list inside of which are a
whole bunch of uppercased words.
Which words?
For each word in the words
list that was passed into yell
is what ends up in this list.
Questions on this syntax here?
It definitely takes a little
bit of getting used to.
Because you've got this value on
the left, this function call here.
You've got this loop inside
of the square brackets.
But if you become accustomed to
reading the code in this way from left
to right, this means give
me the uppercase version
of the word for each
word in my words list.
Questions here on list comprehensions?
STUDENT: Hi.
Can you do conditionals also, like
if else, or combine if, elif, else?
DAVID J. MALAN: Indeed, you can.
And let me come back to that,
where we'll see an opportunity
to do things conditionally.
But for now, I'm just uppercasing
every word in the list.
Good question.
Other questions?
STUDENT: Yeah.
Is this functional programming?
Or I mean, this particular thing, we are
using words.upper for a word in words?
DAVID J. MALAN: Not necessarily.
This is more of a feature
of Python, I would say.
STUDENT: OK.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Map was one very specific incarnation
of thereof our use of Lambda
and passing it in as a key
attribute to the sort function,
sorted function a while
back was an example.
And we're about to see one other.
So we can even use
these list comprehension
to filter values in or
out of our resulting list.
So in fact, in VS Code here, let me
close yell.py and close my terminal
window.
And let me create a new program
here whose purpose in life
maybe is to take a same list of students
as before with a shorter version
thereof, and just filter out all
of the students in Gryffindor.
So let me go ahead and create
a file called Gryffindors.py.
I'm going to go ahead and copy paste
from before really my list of students,
at least Hermione, Harry,
Ron, and Draco from the start
here, just so that I can
focus on one student who
happens not to be from Slytherin.
And what I'm going to
do here now, if I want
to filter out only the Gryffindor
students, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me create another variable
called Gryffindors, which
is going to equal the following list.
And this is going to be
a bit of a longer line.
So I'm going to proactively
move my square brackets
onto two separate lines.
And I'm going to create
now a list comprehension.
I want to do this.
I want this new list called Gryffindors
to contain every student's name
for each student in the student's list.
But, but, but, if the student's house
equals equals quote unquote Gryffindor.
So this is nearly identical in
spirit to what I just did earlier
to create a list comprehension
out of each of the words passed
to my yell function.
But here, I'm doing so conditionally.
And so, I'm borrowing inspiration
from our focus on loops,
borrowing some inspiration
from our focus on conditionals,
combining that into this
same square bracket notation.
So that what Gryffindors ultimately
is, is zero or more students' names.
And the names that are
included are the result
of iterating over each of those students
and only including in the final result
the students whose house
happens to be Gryffindor.
So when I go ahead and run this
with Python of Gryffindors.py
and hit Enter, you'll see, huh,
nothing actually happened here.
Well, that's because I
didn't finish the program.
Let me go ahead and actually
finish the program with this.
How about for each Gryffindor
in Gryffindors plural--
and better yet, so that it's sensible
that I did all of this work in advance,
let me go ahead and
sort all of those names
with our familiar sorted function.
Let's go ahead now and print
out each of these Gryffindors.
So now, notice, if familiar
with the books and the movies,
you'll know that only three
of these four students
are actually in Gryffindor.
And if I run Python of Gryffindor.py,
there we see Harry, Hermione, and Ron,
but now in sorted order as well.
So that's just one way we can solve
this same problem using not just a list
comprehension but a list comprehension
that has this conditional therein.
But there's yet other ways to
solve this same problem too.
And we come back to some
functional features of Python.
In addition to functions
like map, there's
also this one called filter that can
be used to achieve the same effect,
but with a more functional
approach, if you will.
Let me go back to VS Code here.
And with the same
example, let me do this.
Let me leave the original list of
above as before, including Draco,
who's not in fact from Gryffindor.
And let me temporarily
define a function called
is Gryffindor that takes in as a
value something like a student S.
And then, let's do this.
Let's go ahead and say if s quote
unquote house equals equals Gryffindor,
then go ahead and return true.
Otherwise, go ahead and return false.
Now, we've seen before
conditionals like this
that are a bit unnecessarily verbose.
I don't need to have a
conditional if I'm already
asking a Boolean question up here.
So I can actually tighten this
up as we've done in the past
and just return does the student's
house equal equal Gryffindor?
Either it does and it's true,
or it doesn't in it's false.
I don't need to explicitly
return true or false.
I can just return the
value of that Boolean.
Let's go ahead now and do this.
I'm going to create,
as before, a variable
called Gryffindors, a list for
all of my Gryffindor students
that equals to, this time,
the result of calling filter.
Filter takes at least
two arguments here,
one of which is the name of a
function to call is Gryffindor.
And I'm going to apply that function to
each of the elements of this sequence
here.
So similar in spirit to map,
I'm passing in a function
that's going to be applied to each
of the elements in the sequence.
But map returns one value for
each element in the sequence.
That's how we forced all
of the words to uppercase.
But if I want to conditionally include
a student in my resulting Gryffindors
list, I can use filter instead.
Filter expects its first function
to be not something like str.upper,
but a function that
returns true or false.
Tell me whether or not I should include
or not include the current student
from the final list.
And the question being asked
is, do they live in Gryffindor?
We're checking the dictionary's
house key for that answer.
And so, ultimately, I think we'll be
left with something quite similar.
For Gryffindor in the sorted version--
let's do for Gryffindor in Gryffindors,
let's go ahead then and print out the
current students, Gryffindor name.
It's not going to be sorted just yet.
But when I run this version here
Python of Gryffindors.py and hit Enter,
we're back in business.
It's unsorted.
But we have Hermione, Harry,
and Ron, but not Draco.
And if you recall from
a few weeks back, if we
want to even a list of dictionaries,
we can still do that too.
I can call sorted on Gryffindors plural.
And I can pass in a key.
And that key can have a
anonymous function, a.k.a.
A Lambda function, that
takes in a student as input,
call it s, and then returns the value
s quote unquote name, if my goal is
to sort by, indeed, students own names.
If I go ahead now and run
Python of Gryffindors.py,
I see the same list of students.
But this time, it's sorted.
So here we've seen two approaches
to this particular problem
of Gryffindor students.
Whereby we can either use something
like a list comprehension,
and inside of that list
comprehension do a bit of filtration,
including an if conditional as I did.
Or we can take a more
functional approach
by just using this filter function,
passing into it the function
that I want to make
these decisions for me,
and then include only those
for whom true is returned.
Any questions on either
of these two approaches?
STUDENT: Yeah.
I just had a question,
that if we write a code
like in the previous version, where
everything is stuffed into one line,
won't the--
if we check for the style of the code,
then won't it have a problem with it
because it's less readable?
DAVID J. MALAN: So would
a formatter like black
have a problem with the
style of some of this code?
STUDENT: The previous one, where the
everything was tucked into one line.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, a good question.
Would something like Black
have a problem with this code?
Well, let me rewind
to that version, which
was using the somewhat longer
list comprehension, which
looked like, if we go far enough
back, give me a few more undoes,
which looked like this ultimately.
Let me go ahead and run
Black on Gryffindors.py.
And you'll see that I actually--
it reformatted ever so slightly.
But I proactively fix this myself.
Had I done this and done
it on just one line,
but I knew that Black might not like
that, it would have fixed it for me.
So I just proactively fixed it
before writing the code myself.
How about time for one other
question on Gryffindors.py
and this approach of using a
list comprehension or filter?
STUDENT: Yeah.
When using filter, instead of
calling the function is Gryffindor,
can you use it right
there inside filter?
DAVID J. MALAN: Can you use
the function is Gryffindor?
So you don't want to call it like this.
Because you don't want to call it then.
You want filter to call the function
for you, if that's what you mean.
So I pass it in only
by its name instead.
STUDENT: No, I mean, if you can
write the return as house equals
equals Gryffindor inside [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yes, indeed.
In fact, so recall that we indeed
used these Lambda functions way back
when we wanted to pass in a quick
and dirty function anonymously
to allow sorted to filter by a
different key of a dictionary.
We can do that here.
I can actually take the essence
of this is Gryffindor function.
I can change the name of this
function in my filter call
to be another Lambda function,
passing in an argument like s,
and returning exactly that.
I can now delete my is
Gryffindor function all together.
And now, when I run
Python of Gryffindors.py,
I still get the same answer.
And I've not bothered defining
a function only to then use it
in one and only one place.
Well, let me propose
too that we equip you
with one other tool for your
toolkit, namely dictionary
comprehensions as well.
And admittedly, the syntax is
starting to get even weirder.
But as you get more comfortable with
all of these primitives and others,
these are just tools that you can
optionally but perhaps powerfully use
to solve future problems down the road.
And with a dictionary comprehension, we
have the ability to create on the fly
a dictionary with keys and
some values without having
to do it old-school by creating an empty
dictionary, and creating a for loop,
and iterating over that loop,
and inserting more and more keys
and values into the dictionary.
We can rather do it all at once.
So in fact, let me go
back to VS Code here.
And let me propose now that I do this.
Let me go ahead and initially do it
the old-fashioned way here as follows.
Let me go ahead and simplify
and get rid of the houses
all together so that we can focus for
now just on a list of students' names.
I'm going to go ahead and run students.
I'm going to go ahead and write students
equals quote unquote Hermione, quote
unquote Harry, and we'll keep
it even shorter this time,
quote unquote Ron, only those
three students in Gryffindor.
I'm going to now proactively
as we've done in the past
give myself an empty list, so that
I have something to accumulate
some answers to this problem in.
And now, I'm going to
do something like this.
For students and students, so I
can iterate over each of them,
Let's go ahead and with
the Gryffindors list
append to it the name of the student.
So quote unquote name
and then student, which
is indeed their name from that list.
And now, let's go ahead and just put
these students all in Gryffindor.
I know these three
students are in Gryffindor.
So suppose that the
problem at hand is that I
want to build up a list of dictionaries
that only contains the Gryffindor
students.
So it's sort of a step back
from the previous version
where I already had the
names and the houses.
For now, just assume that the
problem is I have all of their names,
but I don't yet have the
student dictionaries themselves.
So I'm rebuilding that same structure
that I previously took for granted.
Now, let's go ahead and just
for the sake of discussion just
print out these Gryffindors so
we can see what we've built.
If I run Python of
Gryffindors.py in my prompt,
I see a bit of a cryptic syntax.
But again, look for our little hints.
I've got a square bracket at the end
and a square bracket at the beginning.
And that indicates, as
always, this is a list.
I then have a whole
bunch of curly braces
with a whole bunch of quoted keys.
They happen to be single
quotes by convention
when using print on a dictionary.
But that's just a visual
indicator that that is my key.
And the first value thereof is Hermione.
Second key is a house.
This value thereof is Gryffindor.
Then there's a comma, which separates
one dict object from the next.
And if we look past
Harry and Gryffindor,
there's a second comma which separates
Harry and Gryffindor from Ron
and Gryffindor as well.
So in short, here is some
code whereby I fairly manually
built up with a for loop in an
otherwise initially empty list
the same data structure as before minus
Draco just for Gryffindor students.
But here's where, again, with
dictionary comprehensions
or really list comprehensions first,
can we do this a little more succinctly?
Let me clear my terminal window.
Let's get rid of this initially
empty list and this for loop
that appends, appends, appends to it.
And let's just do this.
A Gryffindors variable will equal
the following list comprehension.
Inside of that list, I want
a dictionary structured
with someone's name and their name.
Someone's house and
only for now Gryffindor.
And that's it.
But I want one of these dict
objects here in these curly braces
for each student in students.
So here too, inside of my list
comprehension with my square brackets,
I want an object as indicate--
I want a dictionary as
indicated by the curly braces.
I want each of those
dictionaries to have two keys--
name and house respectively,
the values thereof
are the student's name from
earlier here and Gryffindor only.
Which students do I want to
create those dict objects from?
Well, for student in students.
So again, on the left I have
what I want in the final list.
And on the right, I have a loop,
and this time, no conditional.
I want all of these students
in Gryffindor as their house.
Now, let's print this again, Python
of Gryffindors.py and hit Enter.
And now, we have the exact same output.
So instead of three lines it's just one.
It's a little more cryptic
to read at first glance.
But once familiar with list
comprehensions and this sort of syntax,
it's just another way of
solving that same problem.
What if I want to change
this and simplify?
What if I don't want a list of
dictionaries, which I now have.
Again, per the square brackets I have
a list of three dict objects here.
What if I just want
one bigger dictionary
inside of which is a key like
Hermione colon Gryffindor, Harry colon
Gryffindor, Ron colon Gryffindor.
I don't need a list.
I don't need separate
objects per student.
I just want instead one
big dictionary where
the keys are the students' names
and the values of their house.
And I'm assuming for now
no one's going to have
the same first name in this world.
Well, I can do this.
Let me get rid of this here and not
create a list comprehension, but again,
this thing known as a
dictionary comprehension.
And the visual indicator
or difference here
is that instead of being square
brackets on the very outside, this time
it's going to be curly braces instead.
So inside of these curly braces,
what do I want every key to be?
I want every key to
be the student's name.
I want every value for
now to be Gryffindor.
And I want to do this for
each student in students.
And now, things are
getting really interesting.
And this is another manifestation
of Python in some views being
very readable from left to right.
Absolutely takes practice and comfort.
But this is creating a
variable called Gryffindor
which is going to be a dictionary
per these curly braces.
Every key is going to be
the name of some student.
Every value is going to be Gryffindor.
What names of what students?
Well, this dictionary
comprehension will be
constructed from the list
of students one at a time.
So when I print this now, the
syntax will look a little different
because it's not a list
of dictionary objects.
It's just one bigger
dictionary object itself.
But now printing Gryffindors gives me
Hermione colon Gryffindor, Harry colon
Gryffindor, and Ron
colon Gryffindor as well.
Any questions now on what we've called
dictionary comprehensions as well?
Any questions on here?
No?
Well, let's introduce one other
function from Python's toolkit followed
by one final feature and flourish.
And then you're off on your way.
Well, let's go ahead
and think back to this.
Recall some time ago that we had
just a simple list of students
as we have here,
Hermione, Harry, and Ron.
And for instance, way back
when, we wanted to print out,
for instance, their ranking
from one, to two, to three.
Unfortunately, when you do something
like this for student in students,
you can print out the
student's name quite easily.
Of course, if I do
Python of Gryffindors.py,
I get Hermione, Harry,
Ron in that same order.
But I don't see any numerical rank.
I see no number one, two, or three.
So I could maybe do this with
maybe a different type of for loop.
Instead of this, why don't I try this?
So maybe I could do for i in the range
of the length of the students list--
and we've done something
like this before.
And then I could print out i, and I
could print out the student's name
by indexing into that
list at location i.
Well, what does this look like?
If I run Python of
Gryffindors.py it's close.
But these aren't programmers.
They don't necessarily think
of themselves as zero-indexed.
Hermione he probably wants
to be first not zero.
So how can we fix this?
Well.
Just a little bit of arithmetic.
I could print out i plus one, of
course, and then the student's name.
So if I clear my terminal window and
run Python of Gryffindors.py doorstop
once more, now we have
this enumeration, one, two,
three of each of these students.
But it turns out that
Python actually has
had all this time
another built-in function
that you might now find useful.
That is namely enumerate.
And enumerate allows you to
solve this kind of problem
much more simply by
iterating over some sequence
but finding out not each
value one at a time,
but both the value one at a
time and the index thereof.
It gives you back two answers at once.
So if I go back to VS Code here
now and take this approach,
I don't need to do this
complicated range, and length,
and then i all over the place.
I can more succinctly do this.
I can say for i comma student
in the enumerate return
value passing in students.
So this gives me back an
enumeration, if you will.
And now, I can go about
printing i plus 1 as before.
And I can print out the student.
So I don't need to index into
the list with bracket i notation.
I don't need to call range.
I don't need to call length.
Again, enumerate takes a sequence
of values like these students,
and it allows me to get back the
current index zero, one, two,
and the current value Hermione,
Harry, Ron respectively.
So now, just tighten things up further.
And indeed, that's been our theme here.
Can we solve the same problems
as we've been solving for weeks
but tighten things up using
just more of this toolkit?
Allow us to equip you with one
final tool for your tool kit,
namely this ability to generate
values in Python from functions.
This is not a problem that we've
necessarily encountered before.
But it turns out, if you're writing
a function that reads or generates
lots of data, your
function, your program,
your computer might very
well run out of memory.
And your program might not
be able to run any further.
But it turns out there's a
solution to this problem that's
something you might have
in your back pocket,
particularly if after this course you
start crunching quite a few numbers
and analyzing all the more data.
In fact, let's go back to VS Code here.
And let's go ahead and
create a program that's
perhaps timely at this
time of day, particularly
depending on your time zone, you
might be feeling all the more sleepy.
But here in the US,
it's quite common to be
lulled to sleep when
you're struggling otherwise
by counting sheep in your head.
And typically, as
depicted in cartoons, you
might see in your mind's eye one sheep
jumping over a fence, and then two,
and then three sheep, and then four.
And then, eventually, you
presumably get so bored
counting these sheep you
actually do fall asleep.
So in VS Code here, let's
create a program called sleep.py
that allows me to print
out some number of sheep
as though I'm counting
them in my mind's eye.
And via this program, let's do this.
Let's prompt the user
for a variable n, setting
it equal to the integer conversion
of the return value of input,
asking the user what's n?
For how many sheep do
they want to try counting?
And then, let's do a
familiar for loop here.
And we'll start counting
from zero as always.
So we'll first have zero sheep, then
one sheep, then two sheep, and so
on for i in the range of that value n.
Go ahead and print out.
And I'll paste here an emoji
representing a sheep times i.
So the first iteration
I'll see zero sheep.
The second iteration you'll see one,
and then two, and then however many
specified by n ultimately minus one.
Let's go down into my terminal window
here and run Python of sleep.py.
And I should see, indeed,
after typing in, say, three
for my value of n, zero sheep, then one
sheep, then two sheep, and so forth.
And if I make my terminal
window even bigger here,
we can, of course, do many more than
this, typing in, for instance, 10.
And you'll see that we get more
and more sheep as time passes,
presumably becoming all the more
tedious to envision in my mind's eye.
So let's now go ahead
and practice what we've
been preaching when it comes
to the design of this program
and see if and when we
actually run into a problem.
Let me go ahead here now and put
all of this in a main function
by defining main up here as always.
Let me go ahead and indent
all of this code here.
And then, let me just do
this conditionally as always,
if the name of this file equals equals
quote unquote main, let's go ahead
and call main.
Let's make sure I didn't break anything
just yet, even though functionally this
should be nearly the same.
And if I type in three, I
still have zero, then one,
then two sheep on the screen.
But we've been in the habit of
course of creating helper functions
for ourselves.
That is, factoring
our code in a way that
allows us to abstract away certain
functionality, like generating
some number of sheep
into separate functions.
So that, one, they're indeed abstracted.
And we no longer have to think
about how they're implemented.
And we can even reuse them
in projects as in libraries.
But we've also been in the habit
too of now testing those functions
as with unit tests.
So I probably shouldn't keep
all of my logic anyway in main.
And let's factor some of this out.
Wouldn't it be nice if I could, for
instance, just call a sheep function
as by taking this line of code here.
And instead of just printing
it here, let's print
out the return value of
a new function called
sheep that tells the function how
many sheep to print, i in this case.
Let's go down as always and create
another function here called sheep.
The sheep function now will take
a parameter n that specifies
how many sheep do you want to return.
And so, that we can test
this as with a unit test,
though we won't do that here, let me go
ahead and not print the number of sheep
as via a side effect.
But let me go ahead and return
one of those sheep times n
so that the user gets back a
whole string of sheep that's
the appropriate number to print.
So here too functionally,
I don't think we've
changed anything too fundamentally.
Python of sleep.py typing
three still gives us
zero, then one, and then two sheep.
But now, we at least have a framework
for focusing on the implementation
of this sheep function.
But it's a little inelegant now that
it's still up to the main function
to do this iteration.
We've seen in the past
way back in week zero,
wouldn't it be nice to define a
function that actually handles
the process of returning
the entire string
that we want rather than just
one row of sheep at a time.
Well, I think we can do this.
Why don't I go ahead and
change sheep as follows.
Let me go ahead here and first create
a flock of sheep that's initially empty
using an empty list.
Then for i in the range of n, let's
go ahead and append to that flock,
for instance, one sheep
times i, so that I
keep adding to this list zero sheep,
then one sheep, then two sheep, then
three, and so forth.
And then, ultimately, I'm going
to return the whole flock of sheep
at once.
So this is going to return
the equivalent of all
of those strings of sheep so that, ah,
main can handle the printing thereof.
So back up here in main, let's do this.
How about for each sheep,
I'll call it s since sheep
is both singular and plural, for s
in sheep of n, which again returns
to me a list of all of the sheep,
the whole flock, let's just print
out each sheep, s, one at a time.
So, so far so good here, I think.
Let me go ahead and run Python
of sleep.py and hit Enter.
What's n three.
And that's still seems
to work just fine.
But let me get a little
creative here and see
not just three sheep on my screen
but maybe 10 rows of sheep.
And that too seems to work fine.
Let me get a little more adventurous
and type in maybe 100 sheep.
And it's starting to
look ugly, to be fair,
but they're all printing
out pretty fast.
Let me go ahead and try again with
maybe 1,000 sheep on the screen.
And they flew by pretty fast.
It's still pretty messy.
But they're all there.
We could count them all up.
How about not just
1,000 but 10,000 sheep?
Well, that too seems OK.
It's taking like 10 times as long.
And that's why you see this
flickering on the screen.
All of the sheep are still printing.
But, but, but, it's a lot
of data being printed.
If I hang in there a little
longer, hopefully we'll
see all 10,000 sheep coming to pass.
This is here in the video where we
will speed up time, a real online.
Oh my God.
This is a lot of sheep.
There we go.
OK.
And now all of my sheep
have been printed.
So it seems to be working just fine.
Well, let me just be
even more adventurous
and, OK, let me try my luck.
Let me try, how about one million
sheep this time and hit Enter?
Ha.
Something's no longer working.
While we wait for a
spoiler here, does anyone
have any intuition for why my program
suddenly stopped printing sheep?
What is going wrong in this
version, wherein I'm generating
this really big flock of sheep?
STUDENT: We might have run out
of memory or computation power.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So maybe we're actually
pushing the limits of my Mac,
my PCs, my cloud server's memory or
CPU, the brains of the computer's
capabilities because it's
just trying to generate
massive, massive, massive
lists of sheep, one million
of those rows of sheep, each of
which has a huge number of sheep.
And it seems that my computer here
is honestly just really struggling.
And this is really unfortunate now.
Because it would seem that even
though this program clearly
works pretty well for 1,000
sheep, 10,000 sheep, once
you cross some threshold, it
just stops working altogether.
Or it just takes way too long for
the program to be useful anymore.
But this seems a little silly, because
theoretically, I should absolutely
be able to print all of these
same sheep if I just printed one
right away, then print two right away,
then print three, then four, then five.
It seems that the essence of this
problem, if I go back to my code,
is that per my best practices that I'm
trying to practice what I'm preaching,
it seems that the fundamental
problem is that I've
modularized my code by creating
this helper function called sheep,
whose purpose in life is to do
all of the generation of sheep
and then return all of them at once.
Wouldn't it be better--
and I can actually hear my
fan turning on now even just
trying to generate these sheep--
wouldn't it be better then to just
print the sheep one, two, three,
four at a time?
Well, we could do that.
But that's really a step backwards.
That rather contradicts all of the
lessons learned of the past few weeks.
Where generally not putting
everything in main is a good thing.
Generally having an additional function
that you can then test separately
with unit tests is a good thing.
Do we really need to give up
all of those best practices just
to print out some sheep
and here fall asleep?
Well, it turns out there's
a solution to this problem,
and namely in the form of
these generators in Python.
You can define a
function as a generator,
whereby it can still generate a
massive amount of data for your users.
But you can have it return just a
little bit of that data at a time.
And you yourself can implement
the code in almost the same way.
But you don't have to worry about too
much getting returned all at once.
These two, like all features
of Python, are documented
in the official documentation therein.
But what you'll find, ultimately, that
it all boils down to this keyword here,
yield.
Up until now, when we've
been making functions,
we have been defining functions
that return values, if at all,
using the keyword return.
And indeed, if we go
back to our code here,
that's exactly what
I've been waiting for.
I've been waiting to return
the whole flock at once.
Unfortunately, if you wait
too long, and here we have it,
my program was quote unquote killed.
That is to say, my computer got so
fed up with how much memory and CPU
it was trying to use it just said,
nope, you're not going to run at all.
And that's unfortunate.
Now my program no longer
works for large numbers
of sleeps-- sheeps, which is not
good if I'm really having trouble
falling asleep some night.
So how can I use yield to
solve this problem instead?
Well, let me do this.
Instead of building up this massive list
of sheep in this big list called flock,
let's just do this instead.
Let me go ahead and
simplify this whole function
as follows, whereby I iterate
for i in the range of n.
And then on each
iteration, in the past I
might have been inclined
to use return and return
something like one sheep times i.
But this won't work here.
Because if you want a
million sheep and you
start a for loop saying for
i in the range of a million,
you're going to return
accidentally zero sheep right away.
And then this function
is essentially useless.
You shouldn't return a value in
the middle of a loop like this
because you're not going to get to
any of these subsequent iterations
of the loop.
It's going to iterate
once, and boom, you return.
But thanks to this
other keyword in Python
called yield, you can tell Python
to effectively return just one
value at a time from this loop.
So if I go back to this
version of my code here.
And I say not return but yield, this is
like saying return one value at a time,
return one value at a time,
return one value at a time.
The for loop will keep
working and I will
keep counting from zero, to one, to
two, all the way up toward one million.
But each time, the function
is just going to hand you
back a little piece of data.
It's going to generate, so to speak,
just a little bit of that data,
not all of the data at once.
And that's good.
Because my computer has a decent
amount of RAM, certainly enough to fit
one row of sheep.
It just doesn't have enough
memory to fit, apparently,
one million rows of so many sheep.
So now, if I go to my terminal window
and run Python of sleep.py and hit
Enter, what's n?
Three would still work--
zero, then one, and then two.
Let me go ahead and increase the size
of this here and run Python of sleep.py.
Let's try one million
as before and hit Enter.
And now I immediately see results.
I don't think we'll wait
for all of these sheep
to be printed, because then we
will literally all be asleep.
But what you'll notice happening
now is the program is not hanging,
so to speak.
It's not waiting, and waiting,
and thinking, and thinking,
and trying to generate
the entire flock at once.
It's just generating one
row of sheep at a time.
And it's flickering on the screen
because there are so many of them.
And that's all thanks to yield.
It's generating a little bit of
data at a time, not all at once.
Any questions now on this
feature called generators?
Any questions at all?
To add one more piece of terminology
to the mix, just so you've heard it.
This same feature here is returning what
we'll technically now call an iterator.
Yield is returning an
iterator that allows
your own code, your own for loop in main
to iterate over these generated values
one at a time.
STUDENT: How does this yield
actually works under the hood?
I mean, is it using multithreading?
DAVID J. MALAN: You can
think of the implementation
as being asynchronous in this sense.
Whereby the function is returning
a value immediately and then
subsequently giving you
back another one as well.
Underneath the hood,
what's really happening
is the generator is just
retaining state for you.
It does not going to run the
entire loop from top to bottom
and then return a value.
It's going to do one
iteration and yield a result.
And the Python for you is going to
suspend the function, if you will,
but remember on what iteration it was.
So the next time you
iterate over it, as is
going to happen again and
again in this for loop in main,
you get back another
value again and again.
So yield returns, indeed,
this thing called an iterator.
And that iterator can be stepped over
as in a loop one element at a time.
But the language, Python
handles all of that for you
so that you don't need to do all of
the underlying plumbing yourself.
How about time for one other question
on these generators and integrators
as our sheep continue to fly by?
STUDENT: So if every
iteration, the program
will return the memory to the system
so the program will not crash?
DAVID J. MALAN: Correct.
On each iteration, it's only returning
the one string of sheep that's
appropriate for the current value of i.
It is not trying to return
all million rows of the same.
And therefore, it uses really one
millionth the amount of memory,
although that's a bit of
an oversimplification.
All right.
As these sheep continue
to fly across the,
screen let me now go
ahead and interrupt this,
as you might have had to in the past
with infinite loops in your own code.
Even though this isn't infinite,
it's just really long-- control
C will interrupt with your
keyboard that program, giving me
back control of my computer.
Well, here we are at the
end of CS50's Introduction
to Programming with Python.
And if today in particular of all
days felt like a real escalation
real quickly, realize
that these are really--
these are just additional perhaps
optional tools in your toolkit
that you can add to all of
the past lessons learned.
So that as you exit from this course
and tackle other courses or projects
of your own, you have all
the more of a mental model
and all the more of a toolbox with
which to solve those same problems.
If we think back now
just a few weeks ago,
it was probably in our focus
on functions and variables
that you first started struggling.
But now in retrospect, if you
look back at those problems
and those same problems sets,
odds are those same problems
would come all too easily to you now.
Conditionals was the next
step in the class, wherein
we gave you the ability to
ask questions and get answers
and therefore do things
conditionally in your code.
We came full circle today.
And you can see that you can now
use those same kinds of conditionals
now to do fancier things with
list comprehension and dictionary
comprehensions and the like.
Loops, of course, have been omnipresent
now for weeks, including today
as we built up those same structures.
And of course, something can go wrong.
And exceptions and exception
handling was our mechanism
for not only catching errors in code
but also raising your own exception.
So that if you're laying the foundation
to write code for other people,
as in the form of libraries,
you can do that too.
Libraries, of course, are things you can
not only use but now write on your own,
be it a small module or
whole package of code
that you want to share with
others around the world.
And even better, can you write tests
for your own code, for your libraries,
for other's code as well.
So that ultimately, you can
be all the more confident
that not only your
code is correct today.
But if you make a change
to your code tomorrow,
you haven't broken anything, at
least according to your tests
if they continue to pass.
File I/O though, meanwhile,
was a way of now storing
data not just in the computer's
memory like all of these sheep,
but actually storing things
persistently, longer term to disk,
being in a CSV or something more
like a binary file like an image.
With regular expressions,
you then had the ability
to express patterns and actually
validate data or extract data
from information.
All the more of a useful technique
nowadays when so much of the world
is trying to analyze and process
data at scale, some of which
might in fact be quite
messy from the get-go.
And then, of course, most recently,
object-oriented programming,
an opportunity to solve
the same kinds of problems
but with a slightly
different perspective, a way
to encapsulate and to represent real
world entities, this time in code.
And today, of course, et
cetera with so many other tools
that you can add that didn't necessarily
fall under any of those earlier
umbrellas but are useful
functions, and data types,
and techniques just to have,
again, in your back pocket
as yet other mechanisms for
solving problems as well.
Not just putting everyone to sleep,
but I thought another way to end
might be a little more vocally to try
writing one final program together,
this one using a library we've seen
in the past, as well as one other.
I've taken the liberty of installing a
text to speech library on my computer
here.
And I'm going to go ahead, perhaps,
and open a new file here called say.py
in VS Code.
And I'm going to go ahead here and first
import our own friend, import cowsay.
And I'm going to import this new
library here, import pyttsx3,
the Python text to speech library.
And now, per its documentation,
which I read in advance,
I'm going to go ahead and create
a variable for myself here,
engine equals pyttsx3 init to initialize
that library for text to speech.
I'm going to then ask the user,
well, what do I want to hear spoken?
And I might do something like this.
A variable called this equals
the return value of input.
What's this shall be my simple question.
And I'm going to keep it
this time as a string.
We've seen how to use cowsay.
We can do cowsay.cow of this.
Turns out this new library can
allow me to use its own engine
to say this as well.
But then, ultimately, I'm going to
have to run the engine.runAndWait,
just in case it's a long
phrase or sentence to be said.
But that's it.
In just eight lines of code, not only
am I apparently going to have a cow
appear on the screen to close us out
now but also some synthesized text.
Ultimately then we hope with this course
that you've not only learned Python,
that you've not only
learned programming,
but you've really learned
how to solve problems,
and ultimately how to teach
yourself new languages.
Funny enough, I myself only learned
Python just a few years ago.
And even though I certainly went through
some formal documentation and resources
online, I mostly learned
what I know now and even what
I had to learn again for today
by just asking lots of questions,
be it of Google, or friends, who are
more versed in this language than I.
And so, having that instinct,
having that vocabulary [INAUDIBLE]
which to ask questions of others
to search for answers to questions,
you absolutely now have enough
of a foundation in Python
and programming to go off
and stand on your own.
So you can certainly-- and you're
welcome and encouraged to go
on and take other courses in Python
and programming specifically.
But better still, as
quickly as you can, is
to find some project that's
personally of interest that
uses Python or some other language.
Because at least from my own
experience, I tend to learn best
and I hope you might too by
actually applying these skills.
Not to problems in the
classroom, but really truly
to problems in the real world.
Allow me with all that said to look at
my full screen terminal window here.
Run Python of say.py, crossing
my fingers one final time in
hopes that I've not made
any mistakes or bugs.
And here we go.
Python of say.py
prompting me, what's this?
How about we end on this note here.
COMPUTER: This was CS50.