[ORCHESTRA TUNING]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50's Introduction
to Programming with Python.
My name is David Malan, and this
is our week on regular expressions.
So a regular expression, otherwise known
as a regex, is really just a pattern.
And indeed, it's quite
common in programming
to want to use patterns to match on
some kind of data, often user input.
For instance, if the user types in an
email address, whether to your program,
or a website, or an
app on your phone, you
might ideally want to
be able to validate
that they did indeed
type in an email address
and not something completely different.
So using regular expressions, we're
going to have the newfound capability
to define patterns in our code to
compare them against data that we're
receiving from someone else,
whether it's just to validate it,
or, heck, even if we want to
clean up a whole lot of data
that itself might be messy because
it, too, came from us humans.
Before, though, we use
these regular expressions,
let me propose that we solve a few
problems using just some simpler syntax
and see what kind of
limitations we run up against.
Let me propose that I
open up VS Code here,
and let me create a file called
validate.py, the goal at hand
being to validate, how about just
that, a user's email address.
They've come to your app,
they've come to your website,
they type in their email
address, and we want
to say yes or no, this
email address looks valid.
All right.
Let me go ahead and type code of
validate.py to create a new tab here.
And then within this tab, let me go
ahead and start writing some code,
how about, that keeps
things simple initially.
First, let me go ahead and prompt
the user for their email address.
And I'll store the return value of
input in a variable called email,
asking them "what's your email?"
question mark.
I'm going to go ahead
and preemptively at least
clean up the user's input a little
bit by minimally just calling strip
at the end of my call
to input, because recall
that input returns a string or a str.
strs come with some built-in
methods or functions, one of which
is strip, which has the
effect of stripping off
any leading whitespace to the left or
any trailing whitespace to the right.
So that's just going to
go ahead and at least
avoid the human having accidentally
typed in a space character.
We're going to throw
it away just in case.
Now I'm going to do something simple.
For a user's input to
be an email address,
I think we can all agree
that it's got a minimal we
have an @ sign somewhere in it.
So let's start simple.
If the user has typed in
something with an @ sign, let's
very generously just say, OK,
valid, looks like an email address.
And if we're missing that @ sign,
let's say invalid, because clearly it's
not an email address.
It's not going to be the best version
of my code yet, but we'll start simple.
So I'm going to ask the question, if
there is an @ symbol in the user's
email address, go ahead and print out,
for instance, quote, unquote, "valid."
Else, if there's not, now I'm
pretty confident that the email
address is, in fact, invalid.
Now, what is this code doing?
Well, if @ sign in email is a Pythonic
way of asking is this string quote,
unquote "@" in this other string
email, no matter where it is--
at the beginning, the
middle, or the end.
It's going to automatically search
through the entire string for you
automatically.
I could do this more verbosely.
And I could use a for
loop or a while loop
and look at every character
in the user's email address,
looking to see if it's an @ sign.
But this is one of the things
that's nice about Python.
You can do more with less.
So just by saying if "@"
quote, unquote in email,
we're achieving that same result.
We're going to get back true
if it's somewhere in there, thus
valid, or false if it is not.
Well, let me go ahead now and run
this program in my terminal window
with python of validate.py.
And I'm going to go ahead and give it
my email address-- malan@harvard.edu,
Enter.
And indeed, it's valid.
Looks valid, is valid.
But of course, this program
is technically broken.
It's buggy.
What would be an example
input, if someone
might like to volunteer an answer
here, that would be considered valid
but you and I know it
really isn't valid?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, thank you.
Well, for instance, you can type
just two signs and that's it,
and it'll still be valid--
still be valid according to your
program, but missing something.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
We've set a very low bar here.
In fact, if I go ahead and
rerun python of validate.py,
and I'll just type in one @ sign,
that's it-- no username, no domain name,
this doesn't really look
like an email address.
But unfortunately, my code thinks it,
in fact, is, because it's obviously
just looking for an @ sign alone.
Well, how could we improve this?
Well, minimally an email
address, I think, tends to have,
though this is not
actually a requirement,
tends to have an @ sign and a single dot
at least, maybe somewhere in the domain
name-- so malan@harvard.edu.
So let's check for that dot as well.
But again, strictly speaking it
doesn't even have to be that case.
But I'm going for my own email address,
at least for now, as our test case.
So let me go ahead and change my code
now and say, not only if @ is in email,
but also dot is in email as well.
So I'm asking now two questions.
I have two Boolean
expressions-- if @ in email,
and I'm anding them together logically--
this is a logical and, so to speak.
So if it's the case that @ is in
email and dot is in email, OK,
now I'm going to go ahead and say valid.
All right.
This would still seem to
work for my email address.
Let me go ahead and run python
validate.py, malan@harvard.edu, Enter,
and that, of course,
is valid is expected.
But here, too, we can be a little
adversarial and type in something
nonsensical like "@."
and unfortunately, that, too, is
going to be mistaken as valid,
even though there's still no username,
domain name, or anything like that.
So I think we need to be a
little more methodical here.
In fact, notice that if I do this
like this, the @ sign can be anywhere,
and the dot can be anywhere.
But if I'm assuming the user is
going to have a traditional domain
name like harvard.edu
or gmail.com, I really
want to look for the dot in the
domain name only, not necessarily
just the username.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and introduce a bit
more logic here, and instead do this.
Let me go ahead and do email.split
of quote, unquote @ sign.
So email, again, is a string or a str.
strs come with methods,
not just strip but also
another one called split
that, as the name implies,
will split one str into multiple ones
if you give it a character or more
to split on.
So this is hopefully going to return to
me two parts from a traditional email
address, the username
and the domain name.
And it turns out I can unpack
that sequence of responses
by doing this-- username
comma domain equals this.
I could store it in a list
or some other structure,
but if I already know in advance
what kinds of values I'm expecting,
a username and hopefully
a domain, I'm going
to go ahead and do it like this instead
and just define two variables at once
on one line of code.
And now I'm going to be
a little more precise.
If username-- if username,
then I'm going to go ahead
and say, print "valid."
Else, I'm going to go ahead
and say print "invalid."
Now, this isn't good enough.
But I'm at least checking for
the presence of a username now.
And you might not have seen
this before, but if you simply
ask a question like "if username,"
and username is a string,
well, username-- "if
username" is going to give me
a true answer if username is
anything except none or quote,
unquote "nothing."
So there's a truthy value here, whereby
if username has at least one character,
that's going to be considered true.
But if username has no
characters, it's going
to be considered a
false value effectively.
But this isn't good enough.
I don't want to just check for username.
I want to also check that it's the case
that dot is in the domain name as well.
So notice here there's a
bit of potential confusion
with the English language.
Here, I seem to be saying
"if username and dot
in domain," as though I'm asking the
question, "if the username and the dot
are in the domain," but
that's not what this means.
These are two separate Boolean
expressions-- "if username,"
and separately, "if dot in domain."
And if I parenthesis this, we could
make that even more clear by putting
parentheses there, parentheses here.
So just to be clear, it's
really two Boolean expressions
that we're anding together, not
one longer English-like sentence.
Now, if I go ahead and run
this, python validate.py Enter,
I'll do my own email address again,
malan@harvard.edu, and that's valid.
And it looks like I could
tolerate something like this.
If I do malan@, just say,
harvard, I think at the moment
this is going to be invalid.
Now, maybe the top-level
domain harvard exists.
But at the moment, it looks like
we're looking for something more.
We're looking for a top-level
domain too, like .edu.
For now, we'll just
consider this to be invalid.
But it's not just that we want to do--
it's not just that we want to check
for the presence of a username
and the presence of a dot.
Let's be more specific.
Let's start to now narrow
the scope of this program,
not just to be about generic emails
more generally, but about edu addresses,
so specifically for someone in
a US university, for instance,
whose email address
tends to end with .edu.
I can be a little more precise.
And you might recall
this function already.
Instead of just saying, is
there a dot somewhere in domain,
let me instead say, and the domain
ends with quote, unquote ".edu."
Now we're being even more precise.
We want there to be minimally a username
that's not empty-- it's not just quote,
unquote "nothing"-- and we want the
domain name to actually end with .edu.
Let me go ahead and run
python of validate.py.
And just to make sure I
haven't made things even worse,
let me at least test my own email
address, which does seem to be valid.
Now, it seems that I minimally
need to provide a username,
because we definitely do
have that check in place.
So I'm going to go ahead and say malan.
And now I'm going to go ahead and say @.
And it looks like I could
be a little malicious here,
just say malan@.edu, as
though minimally meeting
the requirements of this pattern.
And that, of course,
is considered valid,
but I'm pretty sure there's
no one at malan@.edu.
We need to have some
domain name in there.
So we're still not
being quite as generous.
Now, we could absolutely continue
to iterate on this program,
and we could add some
more Boolean expressions.
We could maybe use some
other Python methods
for checking more precisely is there
something to the left of the dot,
to the right of the dot.
We could use split multiple times.
But honestly, this
just escalates quickly.
Like, you end up having to
write a lot of code just
to express something that's
relatively simple in spirit--
just format this like an email address.
So how can we go about improving this?
Well, it turns out in Python there's
a library for regular expressions.
It's called succinctly
R-E. And in the re library,
you have a lot of capabilities to
define and check for and even replace
patterns.
Again, a regular
expression is a pattern.
And this library, the
re library in Python,
is going to let us define
some of these patterns,
like a pattern for an
email address, and then
use some built-in functions
to actually validate
a user's input against
that pattern or even
use these patterns to
change the user's input
or extract partial
information therefrom.
We'll see examples of all this and more.
So what can and should
I do with this library?
Well, first and foremost, it
comes with a lot of functionality.
Here is the URL, for instance,
to the official documentation.
And let me propose
that we focus on using
one of the most versatile functions
in the library, namely this-- search.
re.search is the name of the
function and the re module
that allows you to pass
in a few arguments.
The first is going to be a pattern
that you want to search for in,
for instance, a string
that came from a user.
The string argument here is going
to be the actual string that you
want to search for that pattern.
And then there's a third
argument optionally
that's a whole bunch of flags.
A flag in general is like
a parameter you can pass in
to modify the behavior of the function.
But initially, we're not
even going to use this.
We're just going to pass in a
couple of arguments instead.
So let me go ahead and employ this
re library, this regular expression
library, and just improve on
this design incrementally.
So we're not going to solve
this problem all at once,
but we'll take some incremental steps.
I'm going to go back to VS Code here.
And I'm going to go ahead now
and get rid of most of this code.
But I'm going to go into the top
of my file and first of fall,
import this re library.
So import re gives me access
to that function and more.
Now, after I've gotten the user's
input in the same way as before,
stripping off any leading
or trailing whitespace,
I'm just going to use this
function super trivially for now,
even though this isn't
really a big step forward.
I'm going to say, if re.search
contains quote, unquote "@"
in the email address, then let's
go ahead and print "valid."
Else, let's go ahead
and print "invalid."
At the moment, this is really no
better than my very first version
where I was just asking Python,
if @ sign in the email address.
But now I'm at least beginning to use
this library by using its own re.search
function, which for now you can assume
returns a true value effectively
if, indeed, the @ sign is an email.
Just to make sure that this version
does work as I expect, let me go ahead
and run python of validate.py and Enter.
I'll type in my actual email
address, and we're back in business.
But of course, this is not
great, because if I similarly
run this version of the program
and just type in an @ sign,
not an email address, and yet my
code, of course, thinks it is valid.
So how can I do better than this?
Well, we need a bit more vocabulary
in the realm of regular expressions,
in order to be able to express
ourselves a little more precisely.
Really, the pattern I
want to ultimately define
is going to be something like, I want
there to be something to the left,
then an @ sign, then
something to the right.
And that something to the right should
end with .edu but should also have
something before the .edu,
like Harvard, or Yale,
or any other school in the US as well.
Well, how can I go about doing this?
Well, it turns out that in the world of
regular expressions, whether in Python
or a lot of other languages as
well, there are certain symbols
that you can use to define patterns.
At the moment, I've just
used literal raw text.
If I go back to my code
here, this technically
qualifies as a regular expression.
I've passed in a quoted string
inside of which is an @ sign.
Now, that's not a very
interesting pattern.
It's just an @ sign.
But it turns out that once you
have access to regular expressions
or a library that offers
that feature, you can more
powerfully express yourself as follows.
Let me reveal that the pattern
that you pass to re.search
can take a whole bunch
of special symbols.
And here's just some of them.
In the examples we're about to see,
in the patterns we're about to define,
here are the special symbols.
You can use a single period,
a dot, to just represent
any character except a
newline, a blank line.
So that is to say, if I don't really
care what letters of the alphabet
are in the user's
username, I just want there
to be one or more characters
in the user's name,
dot allows me to express A through
z, uppercase and lowercase,
and a bunch of other letters as well.
* is going to mean-- a single
asterisk-- zero or more repetitions.
So if I say something
*, that means that I'm
willing to accept either
zero repetitions, that is,
nothing at all, or more repetitions--
1, or 2, or 3, or 300.
If you see a plus in
my pattern, so that's
going to mean one or more repetitions.
That is to say, there's got to be at
least one character there, one symbol,
and then there's
optionally more after that.
And then you can say
zero or one repetition.
You can use a single question mark
after a symbol, and that will say,
I want zero of this character or
one, but that's all I'll expect.
And then lastly, there's
going to be a way
to specify a specific number of symbols.
If you use these curly
braces and a number,
represented here
symbolically as m, you can
specify that you want m repetitions,
be it 1, or 2, or 3, or 300.
You can specify the number
of repetitions yourself.
And if you want a range
of repetitions, like you
want this few characters
or this many characters,
you can use curly braces
and two numbers inside,
called here m and n, which would be
a range of m through n repetitions.
Now, what does all of this mean?
Well, let me go back to
VS Code here, and let
me propose that we iterate
on this solution further.
It's not sufficient to
just check for the @ sign.
We know that already.
We minimally want something
to the left and to the right.
So how can I represent that?
I don't really care what
the user's username is,
or what letters of the alphabet are
in it, be it malan or anyone else's.
So what I'm going to do to
the left of this equal sign
is I'm going to use a single period--
the dot that, again, indicates any
character except for a newline.
But I don't just want
a single character.
Otherwise, the person's username
could only a at such and such,
or b at such and such.
I want it to be multiple
such characters.
So I'm going to initially use a *.
So dot * means give me something to the
left, and I'm going to do another one,
dot * something to the right.
Now, this isn't perfect, but
it's at least a step forward.
Because now what I'm going
to go ahead and do is this.
I'm going to rerun
python of validate.py.
And I'm going to keep testing my
own email address just to make
sure I haven't made things worse.
And that's now OK.
I'm now going to go ahead
and type in some other input,
like how about just malan@
with no domain name whatsoever.
And you would think this
is going to be invalid.
But, but, but it's
still considered valid.
But why is that?
If I go back to this chart, why is
malan@ with no domain now considered
valid?
What's my mistake here by having
used .*@.* as my regular expression
or regex?
AUDIENCE: Because you're using
the * instead of the plus sign.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
The *, again, means zero
or more repetitions.
So re.search is perfectly happy to
accept nothing after the @ sign,
because that would be zero repetitions.
So I think I minimally need to evolve
this and go back to my code here.
And let me go ahead and change
this from dot * to dot +.
And let me change the
ending from dot * to dot +
so that now when I run my code here--
let me go ahead and run
python of validate.py.
I'm going to test my
email address as always.
Still working.
Now let me go ahead and type in
that same thing from before that
was accidentally considered valid.
Now I hit Enter, finally it's invalid.
So now we're making some
progress on being a little more
precise as to what it is we're doing.
Now, I'll note here, like with
almost everything in programming,
Python included, there's often multiple
ways to solve the same problem.
And does anyone see
a way in my code here
that I can make a slight tweak if I
forgot that the plus operator exists
and go back to using a *?
If I allowed you only to
use dots and only stars,
could you recreate the notion of plus?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
Use another dot, dot dot *.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Because if a dot means any
character, we'll just use a dot.
And then when you want to say "or
more," use another dot and then the *.
So equivalent to dot +
would have been dot dot *,
because the first dot means any
character, and the second pair
of characters, dot *, means
zero or more other characters.
And to be clear, it doesn't
have to be the same character.
Just by doing dot or dot * does not
mean your whole username needs to be
a, or aa, or aaa, or aaaa.
It can vary with each symbol.
It just means zero or more of
any character back to back.
So I could do this on both
the left and the right.
Which one is better?
You know, it depends.
I think an argument could be made that
this is even more clear, because it's
obvious now that there's a
dot, which means any character,
and then there's the dot *.
But if you're in the habit
of doing this frequently,
one of the reasons things
like the plus exist
is just to consolidate your code into
something a little more succinct.
And if you're familiar
with seeing the plus now,
maybe this is more readable to you.
So again, just like with
Python more generally,
you're going to often see different
ways to express the same patterns,
and reasonable people
might agree or disagree
as to which way is better than another.
Well, let me propose to
you that we can think
about both of these models
a little more graphically.
If this looks a little cryptic
to you, let me go ahead
and rewind to the previous incarnation
of this regular expression, which
was just a single dot *.
This regular expression,
.*@.* means what again?
It means zero or more characters
followed by a literal @ sign followed
by zero or more other characters.
Now when you pass this pattern
in as an argument to re.search,
it's going to read it from
left to right and then use
it to try to match against the
input, email, in this case,
that the user typed in.
Now, how is the computer,
how is re.search
going to keep track of whether or not
the user's email matches this pattern?
Well, it turns out that it's going to
be using a machine of sorts implemented
in software known as a
finite state machine, or more
formally, a nondeterministic
finite automaton.
And the way it works, if we depict
this graphically, is as follows.
The re.search function starts over
here in a so-called start state.
That's the sort of condition
in which it begins.
And then it's going to read the user's
email address from left to right.
And it's going to decide whether
or not to stay in this first state
or transition to the next state.
So for instance, in this first state,
as the user is reading my email address,
malan@harvard.edu, it's going to
follow this curved edge up and around
to itself, a reflexive edge.
And it's labeled dot, because dot,
again, just means any character.
So as the function is reading my
email address, malan@harvard.edu,
from left to right, it's going to
follow these transitions as follows,
M-A-L-A-N.
And then it's hopefully going
to follow this transition
to the second state, because there's
a literal @ sign both in this machine
as well as in my email address.
Then it's going to try to read the rest
of my address, H-A-R-V-A-R-D dot E-D-U,
and that's it.
And then the computer is going to check.
Did it end up in an accept
state, a final state,
that's actually depicted
here pictorially
a little differently with double
circles, one inside of the other?
And that just means that if the
computer finds itself in that second
accept state after having
read all of the user's input,
it is, indeed, a valid email address.
If by some chance, the
machine somehow ended up
stuck in that first state, which
does not have double circles
and is therefore not an
accept state, the computer
would conclude this is an
invalid email address instead.
By contrast, if we go back
to my other your version
of the code where I instead had dot
plus on both the left and the right,
recall that re.search is going to
use one of these state machines
in order to decide from left to right
whether or not to accept the user's
input, like malan@harvard.edu.
Can we get from the start state,
so to speak, to an accept state
to decide, yep, this was, in
fact, meeting the pattern?
Well, let's propose that this
nondeterministic finite automaton
looked like this instead.
We're going to start as before
in the leftmost start state,
and we're going to necessarily consume
one character per this first edge,
which is labeled with a dot to indicate
that we can consume any one character,
like the m in malan@harvard.edu.
Then we can spend some time consuming
more characters before the @ sign,
so the A-L-A-N.
Then we can consume the @ sign.
Then we can consume at least one
more character, because recall
that the regex has dot plus this time.
And then we can consume even
more characters if we want.
So if we first consume
the H in harvard.edu,
then leaves the A-R-V-A-R-D,
and then dot E-D-U.
And now here, too, we're
at the end of the story,
but we're in an accept state,
because that circle at the end
has two circles total, which means
that if the computer, if this function,
finds itself in that accept state after
reading the entirety of the user's
input, it is, too, in fact,
a valid email address.
If by contrast, we had gotten
stuck in one of those other states,
unable to follow a transition,
one of those edges,
and therefore unable to make progress
in the user's input from left to right,
then we would have to conclude that
email address is, in fact, invalid.
Well, how can we go upon
approving this code further?
Let me propose now that we check not
only for a username and also something
after the username, like a domain name,
but minimally require that the string
ends with .edu as well.
Well, I think I could do
this fairly straightforward.
Not only do I want there to
be something after the @ sign,
like the domain like Harvard, I want
the whole thing to end with .edu.
But there's a little bit of danger here.
What have I done wrong by implementing
my regular expression now in this way,
by using .+@.+.edu?
What could go wrong with this version?
AUDIENCE: The dot is--
the dot means something
else in this context, where it
means three or more repetitions
of a character, which is why it
will interpret it [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Even though I mean for it to
mean literally .edu, a period,
and then .edu, unfortunately in
the world of regular expressions,
dot means any character, which means
that this string could technically end
in aedu, or bedu, or cedu, and so forth,
but that's not, in fact, that I want.
So any instincts now as to
how I could fix this problem?
And let me demonstrate
the problem more clearly.
Let me go ahead and run this code here.
Let me go ahead and type
in malan@harvard.edu.
And as always, this does, in fact, work.
But watch what happens here.
Let me go ahead and do
malan@harvard and then--
malan@harvard?edu, Enter,
that, too, is valid.
So I could put any character there
and it's still going to be accepted.
But I don't want ?edu.
I want .edu literally.
Any instincts, then, for how
we can solve this problem here?
How can I get this new function,
re.search, and a regular expression
more generally, to literally
mean a dot, might you think?
AUDIENCE: You can use the
escape character, the backslash?
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
The so-called escape character,
which we've seen before outside
of the context of regular expressions
when we talked about newlines.
Backslash n was a way of telling
the computer I want a newline,
but without actually literally hitting
Enter and moving the cursor yourself.
And you don't want a
literal n on the screen.
So backslash n was a way to escape n
and convey that you want a newline.
It turns out regular expressions
use a similar technique
to solve this problem here.
In fact, let me go into
my regular expression.
And before that final dot,
let me put a single backslash.
In the world of regular expressions,
this is a so-called special sequence.
And it indicates, per this
backslash and a single dot,
that I literally want to match on a dot.
It's not that I want to match
on any character and then edu.
I want to match on a
dot, or a period, edu.
But we don't want Python to
misinterpret this backslash
as beginning an escape sequence,
something special like backslash
n, which even though we as the
programmer might type two characters
backslash n, it really is interpreted
by Python as a single newline.
We don't want any kind of
misinterpretation like that here.
So it turns out there's one other thing
we should do for regular expressions
like this that have a
backslash used in this way.
I want to specify to Python that I want
this string, this regular expression
in double quotes, to be
treated as a raw string,
literally putting an r at
the beginning of the string
to indicate to Python that you
should not try to interpret
any backslashes in the usual way.
I want to literally pass the
backslash and the dot and the edu
into this particular function,
search, in this case.
So it's similar in spirit to using
that f at the beginning of a format
string, which, of course, tells Python
to format the string in a certain way,
plugging in variables that
might be between curly braces.
But in this case, r
indicates a raw string
that I want passed in exactly as is.
Now, it's only strictly necessary if
you are, in fact, using backslashes
to indicate that you want some
special sequence, like backslash dot.
But in general, it's
probably a good habit
to get into to just use raw strings
for all of your regular expressions
so that if you eventually go back
in, make a change, make an addition,
you don't accidentally
introduce a backslash
and then forget that that might have
some special or misinterpreted meaning.
Well, let me go ahead and try
this new regular expression.
I'll clear my terminal window,
run python of validate--
run python of validate.py.
And then I'll type in my email
address correctly, malan@harvard.edu.
And that's, fortunately, still valid.
Let me clear my screen and run it
one more time, python of validate.py.
And this time, let's mistype
it as malan@harvard?edu,
whereby there's obviously
not a dot there,
but there is some other single character
that last time was misinterpreted
as valid.
But this time, now that I've
improved my regular expression,
it's discovered as, indeed, invalid.
Any questions now on this technique for
matching something to the left of the @
sign, something to the right, and
now ending with .edu explicitly?
AUDIENCE: What happens when
user inserts multiple @ signs?
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
And you kind of called me out here.
Well, when in doubt, let's try.
Let me go ahead and do python of
validate.py, malan@@@harvard.edu,
which also is incorrect, unfortunately,
my code thinks it's valid.
So another problem to solve,
but a shortcoming for now.
Other questions on these
regular expressions thus far?
AUDIENCE: Can you use curly
brackets m instead of backslash?
DAVID MALAN: Can you use curly
brackets instead of backslash?
Not in this case.
If you want a literal dot, backslash
dot is the way to do it literally.
How about one other question
on regular expressions?
AUDIENCE: Is this the same thing
that Google Forms uses in order
to categorize data in, let's say, some--
if you've got multiple people sending
in requests about some feedback?
Do they categorize
the data that they get
using this particular
regular expression thing?
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
If you've ever used Google
Forms to not just submit it
but to create a Google Form,
one of the menu options
is for response validation,
in English at least.
And what that allows
you to do is specify
that the user has to input
an email address, or a URL,
or a string of some length.
But there's an even more
powerful feature that some of you
may not have ever noticed.
And indeed, if you'd like
to open up Google Forms,
create a new form temporarily, and
poke around, you will actually see,
in English at least, quote,
unquote "regular expression"
mentioned as one of
the mechanisms you can
use to validate your users'
input into your Google Form.
So in fact, after today you can
start avoiding the specific dropdowns
of like email address,
or URL, or the like,
and you can express your own
patterns precisely as well.
Regular expressions can even
be used in VS Code itself.
If you go and find, or do a
find and replace in VS Code,
you can, of course, just
type in words, like you could
into Microsoft Word or Google Docs.
You can also type, if you check
the right box, regular expressions
and start searching for patterns,
not literally specific values.
Well, let me propose that we now
enhance this implementation further
by introducing a few other symbols,
because right now with my code,
I keep saying that I want my email
address to end with .edu and start with
a username, but I'm being
a little too generous.
This does, in fact, work as
expected for my own email address,
malan@harvard.edu.
But what if I type in a
sentence like, "my email address
is malan@harvard.edu," and suppose
I've typed that into the program
or I've typed that into a Google Form?
Is this going to be
considered valid or invalid?
Well, let's consider.
It's got @ sign, so we're good there.
It's got one or more characters
to the left of the @ sign.
to the right of the @ sign.
It's got a literal .edu somewhere
in there to the right of the @ sign.
And granted, there's
more stuff to the right.
There's literally this period at
the end of my English sentence.
But that's OK, because at the moment,
my regular expression is not so precise
as to say, the pattern must start with
the username and end with the .edu.
Technically, it's left unsaid
what more can be to the left
and what more can be to the right.
So when I hit Enter now, you'll see
that that whole sentence in English
is valid, and that's
obviously not what you want.
In fact, consider the case of
using Google Forms or Office
365 to collect data from users.
If you don't validate
your input, your users
might very well type in a full
sentence or something else
with a typographical
error, not an actual email.
So if you're just trying to
copy all of the results that
have been typed into your
form so you can paste them
into Gmail or some email
program, it's going to break,
because you're going to accidentally pay
something like a whole English sentence
into the program instead of
just an email address, which
is what your mailer expects.
So how can I be more precise?
Well, let me propose we introduce
a few more symbols as well.
It turns out in the context of a regular
expression, one of these patterns,
you can use the caret symbol,
the little triangular mark,
to represent that you
want this pattern to match
the start of the string
specifically-- not anywhere
but the start of the user's string.
By contrast, you can use a $ sign in
your regular expression to say that you
want to match the end of the string,
or technically just before the newline
at the end of the string.
But for all intents and purposes,
think of caret as meaning "start
of the string" and $ sign as
meaning "end of the string."
It is a weird thing that one
is a caret and one is $ sign.
These are not really things
that I think of as opposites,
like a parentheses or
something like that.
But those are the symbols the
world chose many years ago.
So let me go back to VS Code now.
And let me add this
feature to my code here.
Let me specify that yes, I do
want to search for this pattern,
but I want the user's input
to start with this pattern
and end with this pattern.
So even though it's going to
start looking even more cryptic,
I put a caret symbol
here at the beginning,
and I put a $ sign here at the end.
That does not mean I want the user
to type a caret symbol or a $ sign.
This is special symbology
that indicates to re.search
that it should only look for now an
exact match against this pattern.
So if I now go back to
my terminal window--
and I'll leave the previous
result on the screen--
let me type the exact same thing.
"My email address
malan@harvard.edu," Enter--
sorry, period.
And now I'm going to
go ahead and hit Enter.
Now that's considered invalid.
But let me clear the screen.
And just to make sure
I didn't break things,
let me type in just my email
address, and that, too, is valid.
Any questions now on this version of
my regular expression, which, note,
goes further to specify
even more precisely
that I want it to match
at the start and the end?
Any questions on this one here?
AUDIENCE: OK.
You have slash, and
.edu, then the $ sign.
But the dot is one of the
regular expression, right?
DAVID MALAN: It normally is.
But this backslash that I deliberately
put before this period here
is an escape character.
It is a way of telling re.search that
I don't want any character there,
I literally want a period there.
And it's the only way you can
distinguish one from the other.
If I got rid of that slash, this
would mean that the email address just
has to end with any character,
then an E, then a D,
than a U. I don't want that.
I want literally a period, then
the E, then the D, then the U.
This is actually common convention in
programming and technology in general.
If you and I decide on
a convention, whereby
we're using some character on the
keyboard to mean something special,
invariably we create a
future problem for ourself
when we want to literally
use that same character.
And so the solution in
general to that problem
is to somehow escape the character
so that it's clear to the computer
that it's not that special symbol,
it's literally the symbol it sees.
AUDIENCE: So we don't even know the--
we don't need another slash before the $
sign?
DAVID MALAN: No.
Because in this case, $ sign
means something special.
Per this chart here, $ sign by itself
does not mean US dollars or currency.
It literally means "match
the end of the string."
If, however, I wanted the user to
literally type in $ sign at the end
of their input, the
solution would be the same.
I would put a backslash
before the $ sign,
which means my email address would have
to be something like malan@harvard.edu
$ sign, which is
obviously not correct too.
So backslash is just allow you
to tell the computer to not treat
those symbols specially, likes
meaning something special,
but to treat them literally instead.
How about one other question
here on regular expressions?
AUDIENCE: You said one
represents to make it one plus,
then you said one was to
make it one with nothing.
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
AUDIENCE: So why would you add the plus?
DAVID MALAN: Let me rewind in time.
I think what you're referring to
was one of our earlier versions
that initially looked like this,
which just meant zero or more
characters, than an @ sign, then
zero or more other characters.
We then evolved to that to be
this, dot plus on both sides, which
means one or more
characters on the left, then
an @ sign, then one or more
characters on the right.
And if I'm interpreting
your question correctly,
one of the points I made earlier was
that if you didn't use plus or forgot
that it exists, you could equivalently
achieve the exact same result with two
dots and a *, because the
first dot means any character--
it's got to be there--
the second dot * means zero
or more other characters,
and same on the right.
So it's just another way of
expressing the same idea.
"One or more" can be represented
like this with dot dot *,
or you can just use the handier syntax
of dot +, which means the same thing.
All right.
So I daresay there's still some problems
with the regular expression in this
current form, because even though now
we're starting to look for the user
name at the beginning of
the string from the user,
and we're looking for the .edu literally
at the end of the string from the user,
those dots are a little
too encompassing right now.
I'm allowed to type in more
than the single @ sign.
Why?
Because @ is a character,
and dot means any character.
So honestly, I can have as many @ signs
in this thing at the moment as I want.
For instance, if I run
python of validate.py,
malan@harvard.edu,
still works as expected.
But if I also run python of
validate.py and incorrectly do
malan@@@harvard.edu, should be invalid,
but it's considered valid instead.
So I think we need to be a little more
restrictive when it comes to that dot.
And we can't just say, oh, any
old character there is fine.
We need to be more specific.
Well, it turns out that regular
expressions also support this syntax.
You can use square brackets
inside of your pattern,
and inside of those square brackets
include one or more characters
that you want to look for specifically.
Alternatively, you can inside
of those square brackets
put a caret symbol, which
unfortunately in this context,
means something completely different
from "match the start of the string."
But this would be the complement
operator inside of the square brackets,
which means "you cannot match
any of these characters."
So things are about to
look even more cryptic now.
But that's why we're focusing on
regular expressions on their own here.
If I don't want to allow any character,
which is what a dot is, let me go ahead
and I could just say, well, I only
want to support A, or Bs, or Cs, or Ds,
or Es, or Fs, or Gs.
I could type in the whole
alphabet here plus some numbers
to actually include all of the
letters that I do want to allow.
But honestly, a little
simpler would be this.
I could use a ^ symbol and then an @
sign, which has the effect of saying,
this is the set of characters that
has everything except an @ sign.
And I can do the same thing over here.
Instead of a dot to the right of the @
sign, I can do open bracket ^, @ sign.
And I admit, things are starting
to escalate quickly here,
but let's start from the
left and go to the right.
This ^ outside of the square brackets
at the very start of my string,
as before, means "match from
the start of the string."
And let's jump ahead.
The $ sign all the way at the end of
the regular expression means "match
at the end of the string."
So if we can mentally tick those
off as straightforward, let's
now focus on everything
else in the middle.
Well, to the left here
we have new syntax--
a square bracket, another ^, an @ sign,
and a closed square bracket, and then
a +.
The + means the same thing as always.
It means "one or more of
the things to the left."
What is the thing to the left?
Well, this is the new syntax.
Inside of square brackets here, I
have a ^ symbol and then an @ sign.
That just means any
character except an @ sign.
It's a weird syntax, but this is how
we can express that simple idea--
any character on the keyboard
except for an @ sign.
And heck, even other characters that
aren't physically on your keyboard
but that nonetheless exist.
Then we have a literal @ sign, then we
have another one of these same things--
square bracket, ^@ closed bracket, which
means any character except an @ sign,
then one or more of those things,
followed by literally a period edu.
So now let me go ahead
and do this again.
Let me rerun python of validate.py
and test my own email address
to make sure I've not made things worse.
And we're good.
Now let me go ahead and clear my
screen and run python of validate.py
again and do malan@@@harvard.edu,
crossing my fingers this time.
And finally, this now is invalid.
Why?
I'm allowing myself to have one @ sign
in the middle of the user's input,
but everything to the left per this
new syntax cannot be an @ sign.
It can be anything
but one or more times.
And everything to the right of the @
sign can be anything but an @ sign one
or more times followed by,
lastly, a literal .edu.
So again, the new syntax
is quite simply this--
square brackets allow you to specify
a set of characters that you literally
type out at your keyboard--
A, B, C, D, E, F, or the
complement, the opposite,
the ^ symbol, which means "not,"
and then the one or more symbols you
want to exclude.
Questions now on this syntax here?
AUDIENCE: So right after @ sign,
can we use the curly brackets m one
so that we can only have one
repetition of the @ symbol?
DAVID MALAN: Absolutely.
So we could do this.
Let me go ahead and pull up VS Code.
And let me delete the current
form of a regular expression
and go back to where we began,
which was just dot * @ and dot *.
I could absolutely do
something like this
and require that I want at
least one of any character here.
And then I could do something
more to have any more as well.
So the curly brace syntax, which
we saw on the slide earlier
but didn't yet use,
absolutely can be used
to specify a specific
number of characters.
But honestly, this is more
verbose than is necessary.
The best solution, arguably,
or the simplest, at least,
ultimately, is just to say dot +.
But there, too, another example of
how you can solve the same problem
multiple ways.
Let me go back to where the
regular expression just was
and take other questions as well.
Questions on the sets of characters
or complementing that set?
AUDIENCE: So can you
use that same syntax
to say that you don't want a certain
character throughout the whole string?
DAVID MALAN: You could.
It's going to be--
you could absolutely use the
same character to exclude--
you could absolutely use this syntax
to exclude a certain character
from the entire string.
But it would be a
little harder right now,
because we're still
requiring .edu the end.
But yes, absolutely.
Other questions?
AUDIENCE: What happens if the
user inputs .edu in the beginning
of the string?
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
What happens if the user types in
.edu at the beginning of the string?
Well, let me go back to VS Code here.
And let's try to solve
this in two different ways.
First, let's look at
the regular expression
and see if we can infer if
that's going to be tolerated.
Well, according to the current
cryptic regular expression,
I'm saying that you can have
any character except the @ sign.
So that would work I. Could
have the dot for the .edu.
But then I have to have an @ sign.
So that wouldn't really work,
because if I'm just typing in .edu,
we're not going to pass that constraint.
So now let me try this
by running the program.
Let me type in just literally .edu.
That doesn't work.
But, but, but I could
do this, .edu@.edu.
That, too, is invalid.
But let me do this, .edu@something.edu.
That passes.
So it's starting to
get a little weird now.
Maybe it's valid, maybe it's not.
But I think we'll eventually
be more precise, too.
How about one more question
on this regular expression
and these complementing of sets?
AUDIENCE: Can we use another
domain name, the string input?
DAVID MALAN: Can you
use another domain name?
Absolutely.
I'm using my own just for
the sake of demonstration.
But you could absolutely use
any domain or top-level domain.
And I'm using .edu,
which is very US centric.
But this would absolutely work exactly
the same for any top-level domain.
All right.
Let me go ahead now and propose that
we improve this regular expression
further, because if I pull
it up again in VS Code here,
you'll see that I'm being a
little too tolerant still.
It turns out that there are certain
requirements for someone's username
and domain name in an email address.
There is an official standard in the
world for what an email address can be
and what characters can be in it.
And this is way too accommodating
of all the characters
in the world except for the @ symbol.
So let's actually narrow
the definition of what
we're going to tolerate in usernames.
And companies like Gmail could
certainly do this as well.
Suppose that it's not just
that I want to exclude @ sign.
Suppose that I only
want to allow for, say,
characters that normally
appear in words,
like letters of the alphabet, A through
z, be it uppercase or lowercase,
maybe some numbers, and heck, maybe even
an underscore could be allowed, too.
Well, we can use this
same square bracket syntax
to specify a set of
characters as follows.
I could do abcdefghij--
oh, my god.
This is going to take forever.
I'm going to have to type out
all 26 letters of the alphabet,
both lowercase and uppercase.
So let me stop doing that.
There's a better way already.
If you want to specify within these
square brackets a range of letters,
you can actually just do a hyphen.
If you literally do a-z
in these square brackets,
the computer is going to
know you mean a through z.
You do not need to type 26
letters of the alphabet.
If you want to include uppercase
letters as well, you just do the same.
No spaces, no commas, you literally
just keep typing a through capital Z.
So I have little a hyphen
little z, big A hyphen
big Z. No spaces, no
commas, no separators.
You just keep specifying those ranges.
If I additionally want
numbers, I could do 01234--
nope.
You don't need to type
in all 10 decimal digits.
You can just say 0 through
9 using a hyphen as well.
And if you now want
to support underscores
as well, which is pretty common
in usernames for email addresses,
you can literally just type
an underscore at the end.
Notice that all of these
characters are inside
of square brackets, which just again,
means here is a set of characters
that I want to allow.
I have not used a ^ symbol at the
beginning of this whole thing,
because I don't want to complement
it-- complement it with an E,
not compliment it with an I--
I don't want to complement
it by making it the opposite.
I literally want to accept
only these characters.
I'm going to go ahead and do
the same thing on the right.
If I want to require that
the domain name similarly
come from this set of characters, which
admittedly is a little too narrow,
but it's familiar for now
so we'll keep it simple,
I'm going to go ahead and paste that
exact same set of characters over there
to the right.
And so now, it's much more restrictive.
Now I'm going to go ahead and
run python of validate.py.
I'm going to test my own email
address, and we're still good.
I'm going to clear my
screen and run it once more,
this time trying to break it.
Let me go ahead and do something like,
how about, david_malan@harvard.edu,
Enter, but that, too,
is going to be valid.
But if I do something
completely wrong again,
like malan@@@harvard.edu, that's
still going to be invalid.
Why?
Because my regular expression
currently only allows
for a single @ in the middle,
because everything to the left
must be alphanumeric--
alphabetical or numeric--
or an underscore,
the same thing to the
right, followed by the .edu.
Now honestly, this is
a regular expression
that you might be in the habit
of typing in the real world.
As cryptic as this might look, this
is the world of regular expressions.
So you'll get more comfortable
with this syntax over time.
But thankfully, some
of these patterns are
so common that there are built-in
shortcuts for representing
some of the same information.
That is to say, you don't have to
constantly type out all of the symbols
that you want to include, because
odds are some other programmer
has had the same problem.
So built into regular
expressions themselves
are some additional
patterns you can use.
And in fact, I can go ahead and get
rid of this entire set, a through z
lowercase, A through Z uppercase,
0 through 9 and an underscore,
and just replace it with
a single backslash w.
Backslash w in this case
represents a "word character,"
which is commonly known as a
alphanumeric symbol or the underscore
as well.
I'm going to do the
same thing over here.
I'm going to highlight the
entire set of square brackets,
delete it, and replace it
with a single backslash w.
And now I feel like
we're making progress,
because even though it's
cryptic, and would have
looked way cryptic a little bit ago--
and even though it would have looked
even more cryptic a little bit ago, now
it's at least starting to
read a little more friendly.
This ^ on the left means "start matching
at the beginning of the string."
Backslash w means "any word character."
The + means "one or more."
@ symbol literally.
Then another word character, one
or more. then a literal dot, then
literally edu, and then match at the
very end of the string, and that's it.
So there's more of these, too.
And we won't use them
all here, but here is
a partial list of the patterns you
can use within a regular expression.
One, you have backslash d for any
decimal digit, "decimal digit" meaning
0 through 9.
Commonly done here, too, is if you
want to do the opposite of that,
the complement, so to speak, you
can do backslash capital D, which
is anything that's not a decimal digit.
So it might be letters, and
punctuation, and other symbols as well.
Meanwhile, backslash s
means whitespace characters,
like a single hit of the space, or
maybe hitting Tab on the keyboard.
That's whitespace.
Backslash capital S is
the opposite or complement
of that-- anything that's
not a whitespace character.
Backslash w, we've seen, a
word character, as well as
numbers and the underscore.
And if you want the complement
or opposite of that,
you can use backslash capital W to give
you everything but a word character.
Again, these are just common patterns
that so many people were presumably
using in yesteryear that it's now baked
into the regular expression syntax
so that you can more succinctly
express your same ideas.
Any questions, then,
on this approach here,
where we're now using backslash
w to represent my word character?
AUDIENCE: So what I
want to ask about was
the-- actually the previous approach,
like the square bracket approach.
Could we accept lists in there?
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
We'll see this before long.
But suppose you wanted to tolerate not
just .edu, but maybe .edu, or .com,
you could do this.
You could introduce parentheses,
and then you can or those together.
I could say com or edu.
Could also add in something
like in the US, or gov, or net,
or anything else, or org, or the like.
And each of the vertical bars
here means something special.
It means "or."
And the parentheses simply
group things together.
Formally, you have this syntax here--
A or B, A or vertical bar B, means
"A has to match or B has to match,"
where A and B can be any
other patterns you want.
In parentheses, you can
group those things together.
So just like math, you can
combine ideas into one phrase
and do this thing or the other.
And there's other syntax as
well that we'll soon see.
Other questions on these regular
expressions and this syntax here?
AUDIENCE: What if we put
spaces in the expression?
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
So if you want spaces in there,
you can't use backslash w alone,
because that is only a word character
which is alphabetical, numerical,
or the underscore.
But you could do this.
You could go back to this approach
whereby you use square brackets.
And you could say a through z,
or A through Z, or 0 through 9,
or underscore, or I'm going to
hit the space bar, a single space.
You can put a literal space inside
of the square brackets, which
will allow you then to detect a space.
Alternatively, I could
still use backslash w,
But I could combine it as follows.
I could say, give me a
backslash w or a backslash s,
because recall that
backslash s is whitespace.
So it's even more than a single space.
It could be a tab.
But by putting those
things in parentheses, now
you can match either
the thing on the left
or the thing on the
right one or more times.
How about one other question
on these regular expressions?
AUDIENCE: Perfect.
So I was going to ask, does
the backslash w include a dot?
Because-- no, OK.
DAVID MALAN: No, it only Includes
letters, numbers, and underscore.
That is it.
AUDIENCE: And I was
wondering, you gave an example
at the beginning that had spaces,
like this is my email, so-and-so.
I don't think our current version--
or even quite a long while
ago stopped accepting it.
Was that because of the ^ or
because of something else?
DAVID MALAN: No, the reason I was
handling spaces in other English words
when I typed out my email
address as malan@harvard.edu
was because we were using initially dot
*, or dot +, which is any character.
And even after that, we said
anything except the @ sign,
which includes spaces.
Only once I started using square
brackets and a through z and 0
through 9 and underscore did
we finally get to the point
where we would reject white space.
And in fact, I can run this here.
Let me go into the current version of my
code in VS Code, which is using, again,
the backslash w's for
word characters, let
me run python of validate.py and
incorrectly type in something
like "my email address is
malan@harvard.edu," period, which
has spaces to the left of my
username, and that is now invalid,
because space is not a word character.
You're going to notice, too, that
technically I'm not allowing dots.
And some of you might be
thinking, wait a minute.
My Gmail address has a dot in it.
That's something we're
going to still have to fix.
A backslash w is not the end all here.
It's just allowing us to
express our previous solution
a little more succinctly.
Now, one thing we're still
not handling quite properly
is uppercase versus lowercase.
The backslash w technically does
handle lowercase letters and uppercase,
because it's the exact same
thing as that set from before,
which had little a through little z and
big A through big Z. But watch this.
Let me go ahead in my current
form run python of validate.py,
and just because my Caps lock
key is down, MALAN@HARVARD.EDU,
shouting my email address.
It's going to be OK
in terms of the MALAN.
It's going to be OK in
terms of the HARVARD,
because those are matching
the backslash w, which
does include lowercase and uppercase.
But I'm about to see invalid.
Why?
Why is MALAN@HARVARD.EDU invalid
when it's in all caps here,
even though I'm using backslash w?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So you are asking for the
domain.edu in lowercase,
and you're typing it in uppercase.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
I'm typing in my email
address in all uppercase,
but I'm looking for literally ".edu."
And as I see you with AirPods and
so many of you with headphones,
I apologize for yelling into my
microphone just now to make this point.
But let's see if we can't fix that.
Well, if my pattern on line 5
is expecting it to be lowercase,
there's actually a few
ways I can solve this.
One would be something
we've seen before.
I could just force the user's
input to all lowercase.
And I could put onto the end of my first
line .lower and actually force it all
to lowercase.
Alternatively, I could
do that a little later.
Instead of passing an email, I could
pass in the lowercase version of email,
because email addresses should,
in fact, be case insensitive.
So that would work, too.
But there's another mechanism
here, which is worth seeing.
It turns out that that function before
called re.search supports, recall,
a third argument as well,
these so-called flags.
And flags are configuration
options, typically
to a function, that allow you to
configure it a little differently.
And how might I go about
configuring this call
to re.search a little bit differently
insofar as I'm currently only passing
in two arguments?
Well, it turns out that some of the
flags you can pass into this function
are these.
It turns out that the regular
expression library in Python, a.k.a.
re, comes with a few built-in
variables, so to speak,
things that you can
think of as constants,
that have meaning to re.search.
And they do so as follows.
If you pass in as a flag re.IGNORECASE,
what re.search is going to do
is ignore the case of the user's input.
It can be uppercase, lowercase,
a combination thereof,
the case is going to be ignored.
It will be treated case insensitively.
And you can do other things,
too, that we won't do here.
But if you want to handle the user's
input that maybe spans multiple lines--
maybe they didn't just type in an
email address but an entire paragraph
of text, and you want
to match different lines
of that text that is multiple lines.
Another flag is for re.MULTILINE
for just that, or re.DOTALL,
whereby you can configure
the dot to recognize not just
any character except newlines but
any character plus newlines as well.
But for now, let me go ahead and
just make use of this first one.
Let me pass in a third argument to
re.search, which is re.IGNORECASE.
Let me now rerun the
program without clearing
my screen, python of validate.py.
Let me type in again in all
caps, effectively shouting,
MALAN@HARVARD.EDU, Enter, and
now it's considered valid,
because I'm telling
re.search specifically
to ignore the case of the input.
And that, too, here is fine.
And why might I do this approach rather
than call .lower in one of those other
locations?
Eh, if I don't actually want to change
the user's input for whatever reason,
I can still treat it case
insensitively without actually changing
the value of that variable itself.
All right, any final questions now on
this validation of email addresses?
AUDIENCE: So the pattern
is a string, right?
DAVID MALAN: Mm-hmm.
AUDIENCE: Can we use an fstring?
DAVID MALAN: You can.
Yes, you can use an fstring so that
you could plug in, for instance,
the value of a variable and
pass it into the function.
Other questions on this?
AUDIENCE: Backslash w character, could
we take it as an input from the user?
DAVID MALAN: Technically yes.
That's not a problem we're
trying to solve right now.
We want the user to provide literal
input, like their email address,
not necessarily a regular expression.
But you could imagine building
software that asks the user, especially
if they're more advanced users, to type
in a regular expression for some reason
to validate something else against that.
And in fact, that's
what Google is doing.
If you play around with Google Forms and
create a form with response validation
and select Regular Expression,
Google lets you and I type
in our own regular expressions, which
would be a perfect example of that.
All right.
Well, let me propose that we try
to solve one other problem here,
whereby if I go into the same version
as before, which is now ignoring case,
but I type in one of my
other email addresses.
Let me go ahead and run
python of validate.py.
And this time, let me type in
not malan@harvard.edu, which
I use primarily, but
another email address
of mine, malan@cs50.harvard.edu,
which forwards to the same.
Let me go ahead and hit Enter now.
And huh, invalid, even
though I'm pretty sure that
is, in fact, my email address.
Well, let's put our
finger on the reason why.
Why at the moment is
malan@cs50.harvard.edu
being considered invalid, even though
I'm pretty sure I send and receive
email from that address, too?
Why might that be?
AUDIENCE: Because there is a dot
that has come after the @ symbol.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
There's a dot after my cs50.
And I'm not expecting any dots
there, I'm expecting only,
again, word characters, which is A
through z, 0 through 9, and underscore.
So I'm going to have to retool here.
But how could I go about doing this?
Well, it turns out theoretically,
there could be other email addresses,
even though they'd be getting a
little excessively long, for instance,
malan@something.cs50.harvard.edu,
which does not technically exist,
but it could.
You can have, of course, multiple dots
in a domain name like we see here.
Wouldn't it be nice if we
could handle that as well?
Well, let me propose that we modify
my regular expression as follows.
It turns out that you
can group ideas together.
And you can not only ask whether
or not this pattern matches
or this one using syntax like A vertical
bar B, which means "either A or B,"
you can also group things together and
then apply some other operator to them
as well.
In fact, let me go
back to the code here.
And let me propose that if I want
to tolerate a subdomain, like cs50,
that may or may not be there, let me
go ahead and change it as follows.
I could naively do this.
If I want to support
subdomains, I could say, well,
let's allow for other word characters
plus, and then a literal dot.
And notice, I'll highlight in
blue here what I've just added.
Everything else is the same, but I'm now
adding room for another sequence of one
or more word characters
and then a literal dot.
So this now, I think, if I
rerun python of validate.py,
will work for
malan@cs50.harvard.edu, Enter.
Unfortunately, does anyone
see where this is going?
Let me rerun python of
validate.py and type
in as I keep doing,
malan@harvard.edu, which up until now
has kept working despite
all of my changes.
But now, ugh, finally I've
broken my own email address.
So logically what's the solution here?
Well, there's a bunch of
ways we could solve this.
I could maybe start using
two regular expressions
and support email addresses of
the form username@domain.tld,
or username@subdomain.domain.tld,
where TLD just
means Top Level Domain, like edu.
Or I could maybe just
modify this one, because I'd
prefer not to have two regular
expressions or one that's twice as big.
Why don't I just specify to re.search
that part of this pattern is optional?
What was the symbol we
saw earlier that allows
you to specify that the thing
before it is technically optional?
AUDIENCE: The straight bar?
We were using the straight bar as an--
optional, make the argument optional.
DAVID MALAN: So we could.
We could use a vertical
bar and some parentheses
and say, "either there's something
here or there's nothing."
We could do that in parentheses.
But I think there's
actually an even easier way.
AUDIENCE: Actually,
it's a question mark.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed, question mark.
Think back to this summary here
of our first set of symbols,
whereby we had not just dot and * and
+, but also a question mark, which
means literally "zero or
one repetitions," which
effectively means optional.
It's either there,
one, or it's not, zero.
Now, how can I translate
that to this code here?
Well, let me go ahead and surround this
part of my pattern with parentheses,
which doesn't mean I want literally
a parentheses in the user's input,
I just want to group
these characters together.
And in fact, this now will still work.
I've only added parentheses around
the new part for the subdomain.
Let me run python of validate.py.
Let me run
malan@cs50.harvard.edu, Enter.
That's still valid.
But to be clear, if I rerun it again
for malan@harvard.edu, that is still
invalid, but not if I go in here and
say, after the parentheses, which
now is one logical unit, it's
one big group of ideas together,
I add a single question mark there.
This will now tell re.search that
that whole thing in parentheses
can either be there once or be
there not at all, zero times.
So what does this translate
into when I run it?
Well, let me go ahead and rerun
it with malan@cs50.harvard.edu
so that the subdomain is there.
That works as before.
Let me clear my screen
and run it again, python
of validate.py with malan@harvard.edu,
which used to work then broke.
Are we back in business now?
We are.
That's now valid again.
Questions now on this
approach, where we've used
not just the question mark
but the parentheses as well?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
You said it works for
zero or one repetitions.
What if you have more?
DAVID MALAN: What if you have more?
That's OK.
That's where you could do *.
* is zero or more, which gives you
all the flexibility in the world.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So I was just asking that--
with question marks, there's
only one repetition allowed.
DAVID MALAN: It means
zero or one repetition.
So it's either not there or it is there.
And so that's why this pattern now, if
I go back to my code, even though again,
it admittedly looks cryptic, let me
highlight everything after the @ sign
and before the $ sign.
This now represents a domain
name, like harvard.edu,
or a subdomain within the domain name.
Why?
Well, this part to the
right is the same as always.
Backslash w + means something
like Harvard or Yale.
Backslash .edu means literally ".edu."
So the new part is this.
In parentheses, I have another set
of backslash w + backslash dot now.
But it's all in parentheses.
I'm now having a question
mark right after that,
which means that whole thing in
parentheses either can be there,
or it can't be there.
It's either of those
that are acceptable.
So a question mark effectively
make something optional.
It would not be correct
to remove the parentheses,
because what would this mean?
If I removed the
parentheses, that would mean
that only this dot is optional, which
isn't really what we want to express.
I want the subdomain, like
cs50 and the additional dot
to be what's there or not there.
How about one other
question on regexes here?
AUDIENCE: Can we use
this for the usernames?
DAVID MALAN: Absolutely.
We still have other problems.
We're not solving all of
the problems today just yet.
But absolutely.
Right now, we are not letting you
have a period in your username.
And again, some of you with Gmail
accounts or other accounts, you
probably have not just
underscores, numbers, and letters.
You might have periods, too.
Well, we could fix that, not
using question mark here per se.
But now that we have these parentheses
at our disposal, what I could do
is this.
I could use parentheses to
surround the backslash w
to say "any word character," which is
the same thing, again, as a letter,
or a number, or an underscore.
But I could also or in, using
a vertical bar, something else,
like a literal dot.
Now, a literal dot needs
to be escaped, otherwise it
represents any character, which
would be a regression, a step back.
But now notice what I've done.
In parentheses, I'm telling re.search
that those first few characters
in your email address,
that is your username,
has to be a word character, like A
through z, uppercase or lowercase, or 0
through 9, or an underscore,
or a literal dot.
We could do this differently, too.
I could get rid of the
parentheses and the
or, and I could just
use a set of characters.
I could, again, manually say a
through z, A through Z, 0 through 9,
underscore, and then I could do a
literal dot with a backslash period.
And now I technically don't
even need the uppercase,
because I'm already telling
the computer to ignore case.
I can just pick one or the other.
Which one is better is really up to you.
Whichever one you think is more readable
would generally be the better design.
All right.
Let me propose that
I rewind this in time
to where we left off, which was here.
And let me propose
that there are, indeed,
still limitations of this solution,
not just with the username, not just
with the domain name.
We're still being a
little too restrictive.
So would you like to see the
official regular expression
that at least browsers use nowadays
whenever you type in an email address
to a web form, and the
web form, the browser,
tells you yes or no, your email
address is syntactically valid?
Ready?
Here is-- and this isn't even
officially the right regular expression.
It's a simplified version
that browsers use because it
catches most mistakes but not all.
Here we go.
This is the regular expression
for a valid email address,
at least as browsers
nowadays implement them.
Now it's crazy cryptic at first glance.
But note-- and it's wrapping on to
many lines, but it's just one pattern.
But just notice the
now-familiar symbols.
There is the ^ symbol at the very top.
There is the $ sign at the very end.
There is a square bracket
over here and then some
of these ranges plus other characters.
Turns out you don't normally see
these characters in email addresses.
It looks like you're swearing
at someone in their username.
But they're valid characters.
They're valid officially.
That doesn't mean that Gmail is going
to allow you to put $ signs and other
punctuation in your username.
But officially, some
servers might allow that.
So if you really want to
validate a user's email address,
you would actually come up with
or copy-paste something like this.
But honestly, this looks so cryptic.
And if you were to type it out manually,
you are so likely to make a mistake.
What's the better solution here instead?
This is where, per past weeks,
libraries are your friend.
Surely someone else on the
internet, a programmer more
experienced than you,
even, has come up with code
that validates email addresses properly,
using this regular expression or even
something more sophisticated than that.
So generally, if the problem
at hand is to validate
input that is pretty
conventional-- an email address,
a URL, something where there's
an official definition that's
independent of you yourself--
find a popular library that you're
comfortable using and use it in your
code to validate email addresses.
This is not a wheel, necessarily,
that you yourself should invent.
We've used email addresses,
though, to iteratively start
from something simple, too
simple, and build on top of that.
So you could certainly imagine
using regular expressions still
to validate things that
aren't email addresses but are
data that are important to you.
So we at least now have
these building blocks.
Now, besides the regular
expressions themselves,
it turns out there's other
functions in Python's re
library for regular expressions.
Among them is this
function here, re.match,
which is actually very
similar to re.search,
except you don't have
to specify the ^ symbol
at the very beginning of
your regex if you want
to match from the start of a string.
re.match by design will
automatically start matching
from the start of the string for you.
Similar in spirit is re.fullmatch,
which does the same thing but not only
matches at the start of the string but
the end of the string, so that you,
too, don't need to type in the
^ symbol or the $ sign as well.
But let's go ahead and transition
back now to some actual code,
whereby we solve a
different problem in spirit.
Rather than just
validate the user's input
and make sure it looks the
way we want, let's just
assume that the users are not going
to type in data exactly as we want,
and so we're going to have
to clean up their input.
This happens so often when you're using
like a Google Form, or Office 365 form,
or anything else to collect user input.
No matter what your form
question says, your users
are not necessarily going
to follow those directions.
They might go ahead and type
in something that's a little
differently formatted
than you might like.
Now, you could certainly go through
the results and download a CSV,
or open the Google spreadsheet,
or equivalent in Excel,
and just clean up all
of the data manually.
But if you've got lots
of submissions-- dozens,
hundreds, thousands of
rows in your data set--
doing things manually
might not be very fun.
It might be much more effective
to write code, as in Python,
that can allow you to clean up that
data and any future data as well.
So let me propose that we go
ahead here and close validate.py.
And let's go ahead and create a new
program altogether called format.py,
the goal of which is to reformat the
user's input in the format we expect.
I'm going to go ahead and
run code of format.py.
And let's suppose that the
data we're going to reformat
is the user's name-- so not
email address but name this time.
And we're going to hope
that they type in their name
properly, like David Malan.
But some users might be
in the habit, for whatever
reason, of typing their
name backwards, if you will,
with a comma, such as
Malan comma David instead.
Now, it's fine because both are
clearly as readable to the human.
But if you want to standardize
how those names are stored
in your system, perhaps a database,
or CSV file, or something else,
it would be nice to at least standardize
or canonicalize the format in which
you're storing your data, so that
if you print out the user's name
it's always the same
format, David Malan,
and there's no commas
or backwardness to it.
So let's go ahead and
do something familiar.
Let's go ahead and give
myself a variable called name
and set it equal to the
return value of input,
asking the user, as we've done
many times, "what's your name,"
question mark.
I'm going to go ahead and proactively
at least clean up some messiness,
as we keep doing here, by just stripping
off any leading or trailing whitespace.
Just in case the user
accidentally hits the spacebar,
we don't want that
ultimately in our data set.
And now let me go ahead and
do this as we've done before.
Let me just go ahead quickly
and print out, just to make sure
I'm off to the right start, "hello,"
and then in curly braces name,
so making an fstring to
format "hello," comma, "name."
Now let me go ahead and clear my
screen and run python of format.py.
Let me behave and type in my name as
I normally would, David, space, Malan,
Enter.
And I think the output
looks pretty good.
It looks as expected grammatically.
Let me now go ahead, though,
and play this game again.
But this time, maybe
because I'm not thinking,
or I'm just in the habit of
doing last name comma first,
I do Malan, comma, David, and hit Enter.
All right.
Well, this now is weird.
Even though the program is just
spitting out exactly what I typed in,
arguably this is not close to
correct, at least grammatically.
It should really say
"hello, David Malan."
Now, maybe I could
have some if conditions
and I could just reject the
user's input if they type a comma
or get their names backwards somehow.
But that's going to be too little
too late if the user has already
submitted a form online,
and I already have the data,
and now I need to go in and clean it up.
And it's not going to be
fun to go through manually
in Google Spreadsheets, or Apple
Numbers, or Microsoft Excel
and manually fix a lot of people's
names to get rid of the commas
and move the first name before the
last, as is conventional in the US.
So let's do this.
It could be a little
fragile, but let's start
to express ourselves a little
programmatically here and ask this.
If there is a comma in the
person's name, which is Pythonic--
I'm just asking the question, is this
shorter string in this longer string?--
then let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and grab
that name in the variable,
split on not just the
comma but the space after,
assuming the human typed in
a space after their name.
And let me go ahead and store the result
of that splitting of Malan, comma,
David into two variables.
Let's do last, comma,
first, again unpacking
the sequence of values that comes back.
Now let me go ahead
and reformat the name.
So I'm going to forcibly change
the user's name to be as I expect.
So name is actually going
to be this format string--
first name then last name, both in
curly braces but formatted together
with a single space, so that
I'm overwriting the user's input
and updating my name
variable accordingly.
For the moment, to be clear,
this program is interactive.
Like, the users, like me, are
typing their name into the program.
But imagine the data
already is in a CSV file.
It came in from some process like a
Google Form or something else online.
You could imagine writing
code similar to this,
but that maybe goes and reads
that file into memory first.
Maybe it's a CSV via CSV
Reader or DictReader,
and then iterating over
each of those names.
But we'll keep it simple and
just do one name at a time.
But now what's kind of interesting here
is if I go back to my terminal window
and clear it, and run
python of format.py,
and hit Enter, I'm going to type
in David, space, Malan as before.
And I think we're still good.
But I'm also going to
go ahead and do this--
python of format.py Malan, comma,
David, with a space in between,
crossing my fingers and
hit Enter, and voila.
That now has been fixed.
Such a simple thing to be sure.
But it is so commonly necessary
to clean up users input.
Here we see at least one
way to do so pretty easily.
Now, to be fair, there's
some problems here.
And in fact, can someone imagine a
scenario in which this code really
doesn't fix the user's input?
What could still go wrong
even with this fix in my code?
Any thoughts?
AUDIENCE: If they typed in their
name comma and then [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Oh, and
then something else.
Yeah.
So let me try this, for instance.
Let me go ahead and run a program.
And I am the only David
Malan that I know.
But suppose I were, let's
say, junior like this.
And it's common, in English at least,
to sometimes put a comma there.
You don't necessarily
need the comma, but I'm
one of those people who uses a comma.
That's now really, really broken.
So I've broken some assumption there.
And so that could
certainly go wrong here.
What else?
Well, let me go ahead
and run this again.
And if I did Malan,
comma, David, no space,
because I'm being a
little sloppy, I'm not
paying attention, which is going to
happen when you have lots of users
ultimately, well, this really broke now.
Notice I have a ValueError,
an actual exception.
Why?
Well, because split is supposed to be
splitting the string into two strings
by looking for the comma and a space.
But if there is no comma and space,
it can't split it into two things.
And the fact that I have
two variables on the left,
but I'm only getting back
one thing on the right,
means that I can't do
this code quite as this.
So it's fragile to be sure.
But wouldn't it be nice if
we could at least improve it?
For instance, we now know some
regular expressions syntax.
What if I at least wanted
to make this space optional?
Well, I could use my newfound
regular expression syntax
and put a question mark, Question
mark means zero or one of the things
to the left.
What's the thing to the left?
It's literally a space.
I don't even need parentheses
if there's just one thing there.
So that would be the start of a
pattern that says, I must have a comma,
and then I may or may not have a
space, zero or one spaces thereafter.
Unfortunately, the version of split
that's built into the str variable,
as in this case, doesn't
support regular expressions.
If we want our regular expressions,
we need to go use that library here.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go in and leave this
code as is but go up to the top
now and import re to import the
library for regular expressions.
And now let me go ahead and
start changing my approach here.
I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to use the same
function called re.search,
and I'm going to search
for a pattern that I
think will be last, comma, first.
So let me use my newfound
regular expression syntax
and represent a pattern for something
like Malan, comma, space, David.
How can I do this?
Well, inside of my quotes for
re.search, I'm going to have something--
so dot +--
sorry.
I'm going to have something, so dot +.
Then I'm going to have a comma.
Then I'm going to have a space.
Then I'm going to have something dot +.
Now I'm going to preemptively
refine this a little bit.
I want this whole
pattern to start matching
at the beginning of the user's input.
So I'm going to add the ^ right away.
And I want the end of the user's input
to be matched as well, so that I'm
literally expecting any character one or
more times, then a comma then a space,
then any other character
one or more times.
And then that is it.
And I'm going to pass in
the name variable as before.
Now, when we've used
re.search in the past,
we really used it just
to answer a question.
Does the user's input match
the following pattern or not,
true or false, effectively.
But re.search is actually
more powerful than that.
You can actually get
back more information.
And you can do this.
You can specify a variable and
then an assignment operator,
and get back more precise answers to
what has been found when searched for.
But what is it you want to get back?
Well, it turns out there's this
other feature of regular expressions
which allow you to use parentheses,
not just to group things together,
but to capture them.
It turns out when you specify
parentheses in a regular expression
unbeknownst to us up until now,
everything in the parentheses
will be returned to you as a return
value from the re.search function.
It's going to allow you to extract
specific amounts of information
from the user's own input.
You can reverse this process, too,
by using the non-capturing version
as well.
You can use parentheses, and then
literally a question mark, and a colon,
and then some other stuff.
And that will say, don't
either capturing this.
I just want to group things.
But for now, we're going to use
just the parentheses themselves.
So how am I going to do this?
Well, if I want to get back the
user's last name and first name,
I think what I want to capture is
the dot + here and the dot + here.
So I've deliberately
surrounded in parentheses
the dot + both to the left
and the right of the comma,
not because I'm grouping
them together per se--
I'm not adding a question mark, I'm
not adding up another + or a *--
I'm using parentheses now
for capturing purposes.
Why?
Well, I'm going to do this next.
I'm going to still ask a Boolean
question like, "if there are matches,
then do this."
So if matches is not
effectively false, like none,
I do expect I've gotten
back some matches.
And watch what I can do now.
I can do last, comma, first
equals whatever matches in
and get back all of
the groups of matches.
Then go ahead and update name just
like before with a format string
and do first and then
last in curly braces
as well, and then at the very
bottom, just like before, print out,
for instance, "hello," comma, "name."
So the new code now is
everything highlighted here.
I'm using re.search to search for
whether the user typed their name
in last, comma, first format.
But I am more powerfully using re.search
to capture some of the user's input.
What's going to get captured?
Anything I surrounded
in parentheses will
be returned to me as return values.
How do you get at those return values?
You ask the variable to which you
assign them for all of the groups,
all of the groups of
parentheses that were captured.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead now and run
python of format.py, Enter.
And I'm going to type my name as usual.
In this case, nothing happens
with this if condition.
Why?
Because I did not type a comma, and
so this search does not find a comma,
so there are no matches.
So we immediately just
print out "hello, name."
Nothing interesting or new there.
But if I now go ahead, and clear my
screen, and run python of format.py,
and do Malan, comma, space, David,
Enter, we've reformatted my name.
Well, how did this work?
Let me be a little more explicit now.
It turns out I don't have
to just say matches.groups.
I can get specific
groups back that I want.
So let me change my
code a little bit more.
Let me go ahead now and just say this.
Let's update name to--
actually, let's do this.
Let's say that the last name
is going to be in the matches
but specifically group 1.
The first name is going to be in the
matches but specifically group 2.
Why 1 and 2?
Because this is the first set of
parentheses to the left of the comma.
This is the second set of parentheses
to the right of the comma.
And based on the input, this
would be the user's last name
in this scenario, Malan.
This would be the user's first
name, David, in this scenario.
That's why I'm using
group 1 for the last name
and group 2 for the first name.
And now I'm going to go ahead and
say name equals fstring, again, first
and then last, done.
And let me refine this one last
step before we take questions.
I don't really need these variables
if I'm immediately using them.
Let's just go ahead and tighten
this up further as we've
done in the past for design's sake.
If I want to make the
name the concatenation
of the person's first
name and last name,
let's just do this.
matches.group 2 first,
plus a space, plus matches.group 1.
So it's just up to me from
left to right, this is group 1,
this is group 2.
So group 1 is last, group 2 is first.
So if I want to flip them around
and update the value of name,
I can explicitly get group 2 first,
concatenate using +, a single space,
and then concatenate on group 1.
All right.
That was a lot.
Let me pause to see if
there are questions.
The key difference here is we're still
using re.search the exact same way,
but now I'm using its return
value, not just to answer
a question true or
false, but to actually
get back specific matches
anything I captured, so to speak,
with parentheses.
AUDIENCE: Why is it here we're
using 1 and 2 instead of 0 and 1
for capturing the first?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
A good observation.
In almost every other
context, we've started
counting at 0 and 1 instead of 1 and 2.
It turns out there's
something else in location 0
when it comes back from re.search
related to the string itself.
So according to the documentation
of this function only,
1 is the first set of parentheses,
and 2 is the second set,
and onward from there.
Just a different convention here.
Other questions?
AUDIENCE: What if we write nothing,
like whitespace, comma, whitespace?
How do we check truth of condition?
DAVID MALAN: Before I
answer directly, let me just
run this and make sure I've
not broken anything further.
Let me run python of format.py.
Let me type in David,
space, Malan, the right way.
Let me run it once more.
Let me type in Malan, comma, David,
the wrong way that we're fixing.
And we're still good.
But I think it will still break.
Let me run it a third time with
Malan, comma, David with no space.
And now it's still broken.
Why?
Because I'm still
looking for comma space.
Now, how can I fix that?
One way I could do that is to add
a question mark here, which again,
is zero or more of the thing before.
So if I have a space and then a
question mark literally, no need for any
parentheses, then I can literally
tolerate both Malan, comma, space,
David or Malan, comma, David.
So let's try again.
Before, this did not work.
Let's do Malan, comma,
David with no space.
Now it does actually work.
So we can tolerate different
amounts of whitespace
if I am a little more
precise with my formula.
Let me go ahead and try once more.
Let me very weirdly but possibly hit
the space bar a few too many times
so now they're really separated.
This, again, is not going to work
quite right, because it's going
to consume all of that whitespace.
So now I might want to
strip, left and right, any
of the leading white space on the
result. Or what I could do here
is say this.
Instead of zero or one, I
could use a * here, so space *.
And now if I run this once more with
Malan, comma, space, space, space,
David, Enter, now we've
cleaned up things further.
So you can imagine, depending on
how messy the data is that you're
cleaning up, your regular
expressions might need
to get more and more sophisticated.
It really depends on just how many
problems we want to solve at once.
Well, allow me to propose that we forge
ahead further just to clean this up
even more so, using a
feature that's actually
relatively new to Python itself.
It is very common when
using regular expressions
to do exactly what I've done here--
to call a function like re.search
with capturing parentheses inside,
such that you get back a return
value that I'm calling matches--
you could call it something else,
but I'm calling it by default matches.
And then notice on the next
line, I'm saying "if matches."
Wouldn't it be nice if I could just
tighten things up further and do these
all on the same line?
Well, you can sort of.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me get rid of this if.
And let me just try to
say something like this.
If matches equals
re.search and then colon--
so combining my if condition into
just one line instead of those two.
In C, or C++, or Java, you would
actually do something like this,
surrounding the whole
thing with parentheses,
sometimes double sets to
suppress any warnings,
if you want to do two things at once.
If you want to not only assign
the return value of re.search
to a variable called
matches, but you want
to subsequently ask a Boolean question,
is this effectively true or false.
That's what I was doing a moment ago.
Let me undo this.
A moment ago, I was getting
back the return value
and assigning it to matches, and
then I was asking the question.
Well, it turns out this need to have
two lines of code presumably rubbed
people wrong for too long in Python.
And so you can now combine these
two kinds of lines into one.
But you need a new operator.
You cannot just say, "if
matches equals re.search"
and then in a colon at the end.
You instead need to do this.
You need to do colon equals if and
only if you want to assign something
from right to left and you
want to ask an if or an elif
question on the same line.
This is affectionately known, as can
see here, as the walrus operator.
And it's new to Python in recent years.
And it both allows you to assign a
value as I'm doing from right to left,
and ask a Boolean question
about it, like I'm
doing with the if or equivalently elif.
Does anyone know why this is
called the walrus operator?
If you kind of look at
it like this, perhaps,
if you're familiar with walruses, it
kind of sort of looks like a walrus.
So a minor detail but a relatively new
feature of Python that honestly, you'll
probably continue to see online, and
in source code, and in textbooks,
and so forth, increasingly
so now that it does exist.
It does not change the logic at all.
If I run python of format.py and
type Malan, comma, space, David,
it still fixes things, but it's
tightened up my code just a bit more.
All right.
Let's go ahead and look
at one final problem
to solve, that of extracting
information now as well.
So at this point, we've now
validated the user's input
by checking whether or not
it meets a certain pattern.
We've cleaned up the
user's input by checking
against a pattern, whether
it matches or not, and if it
does match, we kind of reorganize
some of the user's information
so we can clean up their input and
standardize the format in which we're
storing or printing it, in this case.
Let's do one final example where
we're very specifically extracting
information in order to
answer some question.
So let me propose this.
Let me go ahead and close format.py and
create a new file called twitter.py,
the goal of which is to prompt users
for the URL of their Twitter profile
and extract from it, infer from that
URL, what is the user's username.
Now, why might you want to do this?
Well, one, you might want users to be
able to just very easily copy and paste
the URL from their own Twitter
profile into your form, into your app,
so that you can figure out
what their username is.
Or you might have a form that asks
the user for their Twitter username,
and because people aren't necessarily
paying very close attention,
some people type their username.
Some people type their whole URL
or something else altogether.
It would be nice now
that you're a programmer
to just be more tolerant
of different types of input
and just take on the burden of
canonicalizing, standardizing the data,
but being flexible with the users.
It's arguably a better user experience
if you just let me copy-paste
or type in what I want, you clean it up.
You're the programmer not me.
Lends for a better experience, perhaps.
Well, let me go ahead and
do this with twitter.py.
Let me first go ahead and prompt the
user here for a value for a variable
that I'll call url, and just ask them to
input the URL of their Twitter profile.
I'm going to go ahead
and strip off any leading
or trailing whitespace, just in case
users accidentally hit the spacebar.
That's literally the least
I can do quite easily.
But now let's go ahead and do this.
Suppose that the user's
address is the following.
Let me print out what did they type in.
And let me clear my screen
and run python of twitter.py.
I'm going to go ahead and
type in, for instance,
https://twitter.com/davidjmalan, which
happens to be my own Twitter username.
For now, we're just going to
print it back onto the screen just
to make sure I've not messed up yet.
OK.
So I've printed back
out the exact same URL.
But the goal at hand is to
extract the username only.
Now, let me just ask, perhaps,
a straightforward question.
Logically, what do I need to do
to get at the user's username?
AUDIENCE: Well, we just ignore
what's before the username
and then just extract the username?
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
Yeah, I mean, it is as simple as that.
If you know the username is
at the end, well, let's just
somehow ignore everything
to the beginning.
Well, what's at the beginning?
Well, it's a URL.
So we're probably going to need to
ignore an HTTPS, a ://, a twitter.com,
and a /.
So we just want to
throw all of that away.
Why?
Because if it's an URL, we
know by how Twitter works
that the username comes at the end.
So let's use that very simple idea
to get at the information we want.
I'm going to try this
a few different ways.
Let me go back into my program here.
And instead of just printing it out,
which was just to see what's going on,
let me do this.
Let me create a new
variable called username.
And let me call url.replace.
It turns out that if URL is
a string or a str in Python,
it, again, comes with multiple
methods, like strip, and split,
and others as well, one of
which is called replace.
And replace will do just that.
You pass it two arguments, the first of
which is, what do you want to replace?
The second argument is, what
do you want to replace it with?
So if I want to get rid
of, as I've proposed,
really just everything
before the username,
that is, the Twitter URL or the
beginning thereof, let's just say this.
Go ahead and replace
"https://twitter.com/",
close quote, that's
what I want to replace.
And comma, second argument, what
do you want to replace it with?
Nothing.
So I'm literally going
to pass in quote unquote
to effectively do a find and replace.
That's what the replace method
does, just like you can do it
in Microsoft Word or Google Docs.
This is the programmer's way
of doing find and replace.
Now let me go ahead and
print out just the username.
So I'll use an fstring like this.
I'll say username, colon,
and then in curly braces,
username, just to format it nicely.
All right.
Let me go ahead and clear my screen and
run python of twitter.py, Enter, URL.
Here we go.
https://twitter.com/davidjmalan, Enter.
OK.
Now we've made some progress.
Done for the day, right?
Well, what is suboptimal about this?
Can anyone critique or
find fault with my program?
It is working now, but
it's a little fragile.
I bet we could contrive some scenarios
where I think it works but it doesn't.
AUDIENCE: Well, I have
a few ideas, actually.
Well, first of all, if we don't
specify HTTPS, it will be broken.
Secondly, if we have a slash at
the end, it also will be broken.
If we have a question mark or
something after question mark,
it also won't work.
So a lot of scenarios, actually.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, my god.
I mean, here we are.
I was pretending to think I was done.
But my god, like, Alex gave us a
whole laundry list of problems.
And just to recap, then, what
if it's not HTTPS, it's HTTP?
Slightly less secure,
but I should still be
able to tolerate that programmatically.
What if the protocol is not there?
What if the user just typed
twitter.com/davidjmalan?
It would be nice to tolerate
that rather than show an error
and make me type in the protocol.
Why?
It's not good user experience.
What if it had a slash at the end
of the username, or a question mark?
If you think about URLs
you've seen on the web,
there's very commonly more
information, especially
if it's been shared on social media.
There might be a HTTP
parameters, so to speak,
just stuff there that we don't want.
There could be a www.twitter.com,
which I'm also not expecting but does
work if you go to that URL, too.
So there's just so many
things that can go wrong.
And even if I come back to my
contrived example as earlier,
what if I run this
program and say this--
"my username is
https://twitter.com/davidjmalan,"
Enter.
Well, that too just didn't really
work-- it got rid of the-- actually--
[LAUGHS] OK, actually
that kind of worked.
But the goal here is to actually
get the user's username,
not an English sentence
describing the user's username.
So I would argue that even though
I just accidentally created
perfectly correct English
grammar, I did not
extract the Twitter username correctly.
I don't want words like "my
username is" as part of my input.
So how can we go about improving
this, and maybe chipping away
at some of those problems one by one?
Well, let me clear my screen here.
Let me come back up to my code.
And let me not just replace it, but
let me do something else instead.
I'm going to go ahead, and
instead of using replace,
I'm going to use another
function called removeprefix.
A prefix is a string or a substring
that comes at the start of another.
So if I remove prefix, I don't need
a second argument for this function.
I just need one.
What prefix do you want to remove?
So this will at least now
fix the problem I just
described of typing in like a whole
sentence, where the URL is there,
but it's not at the beginning,
it's only at the end.
So here, this still is not correct.
But we don't create this weird-looking
output that just removes the URL part
of the input--
"my username is
https://twitter.com/davidjmalan."
A moment ago, it did remove the
URL and left only the davidjmalan.
This is not perfect still.
But at least now, it does
not weirdly remove the URL
and then leave the English.
It's just leaving it alone.
So maybe I could handle
this better, but at least
it's removing it from the part
of the string I might anticipate.
Well, what else could we do here?
Well, it turns out that
regular expressions just
let us express patterns
much more precisely.
We could spend all day using a whole
bunch of different Python functions
like removeprefix, or remove, and
strip, and others, and kind of
make our way to the right solution.
But a regular expression just
allows you to more succinctly,
if admittedly more cryptically, express
these kinds of patterns and goals.
And we've seen from
parentheses, which can
be used not just to group
symbols together as sets
but to capture information as well,
we have a very powerful tool now
in our toolkit.
So let me do this.
Let me go ahead and start fresh
here and import the re library
as before at the very top of my program.
I'm still going to get the user's
URL via the same line of code.
But I'm now going to use
another function as well.
It turns out that there's not
just re.search, or re.match,
or re.fullmatch.
There's also re.sub in the regular
expression library, where "sub" here
means "substitute."
And it takes more arguments, but
they're fairly straightforward.
The first argument to re.sub is
the pattern, the regular expression
that you want to look for.
Then you have a replacement
string-- what do
you want to replace that pattern with?
And where do you want to do all that?
Well, you pass in the string that
you want to do the substitution on.
Then there's some other arguments
that I'll wave my hands at for now.
Among them are those same
flags and also a count,
like how many times do you
want to do find and replace?
Do you want it to do all,
do you want to do just one,
or so forth you can have
further control there, too,
just like you would in Google
Docs or Microsoft Word.
Well, let me go back to my
code here, and let me do this.
I'm going to go ahead and call re
not search but re.sub for substitute.
I'm going to pass in the
following regular expression,
"https://twitter.com/" and then
I'm going to close my quote.
And now what do I want
to replace that with?
Well, like before with the
simple str replace function,
I want to replace it with nothing,
just get rid of it altogether.
But what string do I want
to pass in to do this to?
The URL from the user.
And now let me go ahead and
assign the return value of re.sub
to a variable called username.
So re.sub's purpose in life
is, again, to substitute
some value for some regular
expression some number of times.
It essentially is find and
replace using regular expressions.
And it returns to you
the resulting string
once you've done all
those substitutions.
So now the very last line of my code
can be the same as before, print--
and I'll use an fstring, username,
colon, and then in curly braces,
username.
So I can print out literally just that.
All right.
Let's try this and see what happens.
I'll clear my terminal window,
run python of twitter.py.
And here we go,
https://twitter.com/davidjmalan.
Cross my fingers and hit Enter.
OK, now we're in business.
But it is still a little fragile.
And so let me ask the group,
what problem should I now
further chip away at?
They've been said before,
but let's be clear.
What's one or more
problems that still remain?
AUDIENCE: The protocols and
the domain prefix [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Good.
The protocols, so HTTP versus HTTPS.
Maybe the subdomain, www,
should it be there or not?
And there's a few other
mistakes here, too.
Let me actually stay with the group.
What are some other shortcomings
of this current solution?
AUDIENCE: If we use a
phrase like you do before,
we are going to have the same problem,
because it's not taking account
in the first part of the text example.
DAVID MALAN: Good.
I might still allow for some words,
some English to the left of the URL
because I didn't use my ^ symbol.
So I'll fix that.
And any final observations
on shortcomings here?
AUDIENCE: Well, it could be an HTTP, or
there could be less than two slashes.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So it could be HTTP.
And I think that was mentioned,
too, in terms of protocol.
There could be fewer than two slashes.
That I'm not going to worry about.
If the user gives me instead of
two, that's really user error.
And I could be tolerant of it,
but you know what, at that point
I'm OK yelling at them with an error
message saying, please fix your input.
Otherwise, we could be here all day long
trying to handle all possible typos.
For now, I think in the
interests of usability,
or user experience,
UX, let's at least be
tolerant of all possible valid inputs
or reasonable INPUTS if you will.
So let me go here, and let me
start chipping away at these here.
What are some problems we can solve?
Well, let me propose that we first
address the issue of matching
from the beginning of the string.
So let me add the ^ to the beginning.
And let me add not a $ sign
at the end, though, right?
Because I don't want to
match all the way to the end,
because I want to
tolerate a username there.
So I think we just want
the ^ symbol there.
There's a subtle bug that
no one yet mentioned.
And let me just kind of highlight it
and see if it jumps out at you now.
It's a little subtle here on my screen.
I've highlighted in
blue a final bug here--
maybe some smiles on the screen, yeah?
Can we take one hand here?
Why am I highlighting the dot in
twitter.com, even though it definitely
should be there?
AUDIENCE: So the dot without a backslash
means any character except a newline.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
It means any character.
So I could type in something like
twitter?com, or twitter anything com,
and that would actually be tolerated.
It's not really that bad, because
why would the user do that?
But if I want to be
correct, and I want to be
able to test my own code properly, I
should really get this detail right.
So that's an easy fix, too,
but it's a common mistake.
Anytime you're writing regular
expressions that happen to involve
special symbols, like dots
in a URL or domain name,
a $ sign in something involving
currency, remember you might, indeed,
need to escape it with a
backslash like this here.
All right.
Let me ask the group about
the protocol specifically.
So HTTPS is a good thing in the world.
It means secure.
There is encryption being used.
So generally, you like to see HTTPS.
But you still see people
typing or copy-pasting HTTP.
What would be the simplest fix here
to tolerate, as has been proposed,
both HTTP and HTTPS?
I'm going to propose
that I could do this.
I could do HTTP vertical bar or
HTTPS, which, again, means A or B.
But I think I can be smarter than that.
I can keep my code a
little more succinct.
Any recommendations here for
tolerating HTTP or HTTPS?
AUDIENCE: We could try to put
in question mark behind the S.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
Just use a question mark.
Both of those would be viable solutions.
If you want to be super
explicit in your code, fine.
Use parentheses and say HTTP or HTTPS,
so that you, the reader, your boss,
your teacher just know
exactly what you're doing.
But if you keep taking the more
verbose approach all the time,
it might actually become
less readable, certainly
once your regular expressions
get this big instead of this big.
So let's save space where we can.
And I would argue that this
is pretty reasonable, so
long as you're in the habit
of reading regular expressions
and know that question mark does
not mean a literal question mark,
but it means zero or
one of the thing before.
I think we've effectively
made the S optional here.
Now, what else can I do?
Well, suppose we want to tolerate the
www dot, which may or may not be there,
but it will work if you go to a browser.
I could do this--
www dot-- wait, I want a
backslash there so I don't
repeat the same mistake as before.
But this is no good either, because
I want to tolerate being there or not
being there.
And now I've just
required that it be there.
But I think I can take
the same approach.
Any recommendations?
How do I make the www.
optional, just to hammer this home?
AUDIENCE: We can group--
make a square and a question mark.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So question mark is
the short answer again.
But we have to be a
little smarter this time.
As Maria has noted, we
need parentheses now.
Because if I just put a
question mark after the dot,
that just means the dot is optional.
And that's wrong, because we
don't want the user to type
in W-W-W-T-W-I-T-T-E-R. We want the dot
to be there or just not at all with no
www.
So we need to group this
whole thing together,
put a parenthesis there, and then a
parenthesis, not after the third W,
after the dot, so that that whole thing
is either there or it's not there.
And what else could we still do here?
There's going to be one other
thing we should tolerate.
And it's been said before,
and I'll pluck this one off.
What about the protocol?
Like, what if the user just doesn't
type or doesn't copy-paste the http://
or an https://?
Honestly, you and I
are not in the habit,
generally, of even typing the
protocol anymore nowadays.
You just let the browser
figure it out for you,
and automatically add it instead.
So this one's going to look
like more of a mouthful.
But if I want this whole thing
here in blue to be optional,
it's actually the same solution
as Maria offered a moment ago.
I'm going to go ahead and
put a parenthesis over here,
and a parenthesis after the two
slashes, and then a question
mark so as to make that
whole thing optional as well.
And this is OK.
It's totally fine to
make this whole thing
optional, or inside of it, this little
thing, just the S optional as well.
So long as I'm applying the
same principles again and again,
either on a small scale
or a bigger scale,
it's totally fine to nest one
of these inside of the other.
Questions now on any
of these refinements
to this parsing, this
analyzing of Twitter?
AUDIENCE: What if we put a
vertical bar besides this www dot?
DAVID MALAN: What if we
use a vertical bar there?
So we could do something like that, too.
We could do something like this.
Instead of the question mark,
I could do www dot or nothing
and just leave that and the parentheses.
That, too, would be fine.
I personally tend not to like
that, because it's a little less
obvious to me-- wait, a minute.
Is that deliberate, or did I forget to
finish my thought by putting something
after the vertical bar?
But that, too, would be allowed there
as well, if that's what you mean.
Other questions on where
we left things here,
where we made the
protocol optional, too?
AUDIENCE: What happens
if we have parenthesis,
and inside we have another
parenthesis, and another parenthesis?
Will it interfere with each other?
DAVID MALAN: If you have parentheses
inside of parentheses, that,
too, is totally fine.
And indeed, that should be one
of the reassuring lessons today.
As complicated as each of these regular
expressions has admittedly gotten,
I'm just applying the exact same
principles and the exact same syntax
again and again.
So it's totally fine to have
parentheses inside of parentheses
if they're each solving
different problems.
And in fact, the lesson I would
really emphasize the most today
is that you will not be
happy if you try to write out
a whole complicated regular
expression all at once.
Like, if you're anything
like me, you will fail,
and you will have trouble
finding the mistake.
Because my god, look at these things.
They are, even to me all
these years later, cryptic.
The better way, I would argue,
whether you're new to programming
or is old to it as I am,
is to just take these baby
steps, these incremental steps
where you do something simple,
you make sure it works.
You add one more feature,
make sure it works.
Add one more feature,
And hopefully, by the end, because
you've done each of those steps one
at a time, the whole thing
will make sense to you.
But you'll also have gotten each of
those steps correct at each turn.
So please, do avoid
the inclination to try
to come up with long,
sophisticated regular expressions
all at once, because it's
just not a good use of a time
if you then stare at it trying
to find a mistake that you
could have caught if you did
things more incrementally instead.
All right.
There still remains,
arguably, at least one problem
with this solution in
that even though I'm
calling re.sub to substitute
the URL with nothing,
quote, unquote, I then in my
final line of code, line 6,
am just blindly assuming
that it all worked,
and I'm going to go ahead
and print out the username.
But what if the user--
if I clear my screen here and
run python of twitter.py--
doesn't even type a Twitter URL?
What if they do something
like https://google.com/,
like completely unrelated,
for whatever reason,
Enter, that is not
their Twitter username.
So we need to have some
conditional logic, I would argue,
so that for this program's
sake, we're only printing out
or, in a back end system, we're only
saving into our database or a CSV
file the username if we actually
matched the proper pattern.
So rather than use re.sub, which
is useful for cleaning up data,
as we've done here to get rid of
something we don't want there,
why don't we go back to
re.search, where we began today,
and use it to solve this same problem
but in a way that's conditional,
whereby I can confidently say, yes
or no, at the end of my program,
here's the username, or here it is not?
So let me go ahead now.
And I'll clear my terminal window here.
I'm going to keep most of--
I'm going to keep the first two
lines the, same where I import re,
and I get the URL from the user.
But this time, let's do this.
Let's this time search for, using
re.search instead of re.sub,
the following.
I'm going to start matching at the
beginning of the string, https,
question mark to make the S
optional, colon, slash, slash,
I'm going to make my www optional by
putting that in question marks there,
then a twitter.com with a literal dot
there so I stay ahead of that issue,
too, then a slash.
And then well, this is where
davidjmalan is supposed to go.
How do I detect this?
Well, I think I'll just tolerate
anything at the end of the URL here.
All right, $ sign at the
very end, close quote.
For the moment, I'm going
to stipulate that we're not
going to worry about question
marks at the end or hashes,
like for fragment IDs in URLs.
We're going to assume for
simplicity now that the URL just
ends with the username alone.
Now what am I going to do?
Well, I want to search
for this URL specifically,
and I'm going to ignore
case, so re.IGNORECASE,
applying that same lesson
learned from before.
re.search, recall, will return to
you the matches you've captured.
Well, what do I want to capture?
Well, I want to capture everything to
the right of the twitter.com URL here.
So let me surround what should be
the user's username with parentheses,
not for making them optional but to
say, "capture this set of characters."
Now, re.search, recall,
returns an answer.
matches will be my variable name again,
but I could call it anything I want.
And then I can do this.
If matches, now I know I can do this.
Let's print out the format
string, username colon.
And then what do I want to print out?
Well, I think I want to print out
matches.group 1 for my matched
username.
All right.
So what am I doing just to recap?
Line 1, I'm importing the library.
Line 2, I'm getting
the URL from the user.
So nothing new there.
Line 5, I'm searching the user's URL, as
indicated here as the second argument,
for this regular
expression, this pattern.
I have surrounded the
dot + with parentheses
so that they are captured
ultimately, so I can extract,
in this final scenario,
the user's username.
If I indeed got a match,
and matches is non-none,
it is actually containing some match,
then and only then, print out username.
In this way, let me try this now.
If I run python of twitter.py and
type in https://www.google.com/,
now nothing gets printed.
So I've at least solved
the mistake we just saw,
where I was just assuming
that my code worked.
Now I'm making sure that I have searched
for and found the Twitter URL prefix.
All right.
Well, let's run this for real now.
Python of twitter.py
https://twitter.com/davidjmalan.
But note, I could use
HTTP, I could use www.
I'm just going to go
ahead here and hit Enter.
Huh, none.
What has gone wrong?
This one's a bit more subtle.
But why does matches.group
1 contain nothing?
Wait a minute.
Let me-- maybe I did this wrong.
Maybe-- maybe do we need the www?
Let me run it again.
So here we go. https://, let's
add a www.twitter.com/davidjmalan.
All right.
Enter.
Ho, ho, ho.
What is going on?
AUDIENCE: You have to say group 2.
DAVID MALAN: I have to say group 2?
Well, wait-- oh, right, because
we had the subdomain was optional.
And to make it optional, I
needed to use parentheses here.
And so I then said zero or on.
OK.
So that means that actually, I'm
unintentionally but by design
capturing the www dot, or none
of it if it wasn't there before,
but I have a second
match over here because I
have a second set of parentheses.
So I think, yep, let me
change matches.group 1
to matches.group 2, and let's run this.
Python of twitter.py
https://www.twitter--
let's do this,
twitter.com/davidjmalan, Enter,
and now we've got
access to the username.
Let me go ahead and tighten
it up a little bit further.
If you like our new friend--
it's hard not to like.
If we like our old friend the
walrus operator, let's go ahead
and add this just to tighten things up.
Let me go back to VS Code here, and let
me get rid of the unnecessary condition
there and combine it up
here, if matches equals that.
But let's change the single assignment
operator to the walrus operator.
Now I've tightened things up further.
But I bet, I bet, I bet there
might be another solution here.
And indeed, it turns out that we can
come back to this final set of syntax.
Recall that when we
introduce these parentheses,
we did it so that we could do A or B,
for instance, with the vertical bar.
Then you can even combine
more than just one bar.
We use the group to combine
ideas like the, www dot.
And then there's this admittedly weird
syntax at the bottom here, up until now
not used.
There is a non-capturing
version of parentheses
if you want to use parentheses
logically because you need to,
but you don't want to
bother capturing the result.
And this would arguably
be a better solution
here, because, yes, if I
go back to VS Code, I do
need to surround the www dot
with parentheses, at least
as I've written my regex
here, because I wanted
to put the question mark after it.
But I don't need the
www dot coming back.
In fact, let's only extract
the data we care about,
just so there's no confusion
down the road, for me,
or my colleagues, or my teachers.
So what could I do?
Well, the syntax per this slide is
to use a question mark and a colon
immediately after the open parentheses.
It looks weird admittedly.
Those of you who have prior
programming experience
might recognize the syntax from ternary
operators, doing an if else all in one
line.
A question mark colon at the
beginning of that parenthetical
means, yes, I'm using parentheses
to group these things together,
but no, you do not need
to capture them instead.
So I can change my code
back now to matches.group 1.
I'll clear my screen here,
run python of twitter.py.
I'll again run here
https://twitter.com/davidjmalan
with or without the www.
And now, I indeed get
back that username.
Any questions, then, on
these final techniques?
AUDIENCE: So first of all,
could we move the ^ right
at the beginning of Twitter, and
then just start reading from there,
and then get rid of everything else
before that, the kind of www issues
that we had?
And then my second question is,
how would we use kind of, I guess,
either a list or a dictionary
to sort the .com kind of thing,
because we have .co.uk,
and that kind of stuff.
How would we bring that
into the re function?
DAVID MALAN: A good question but no.
If I move the ^ before twitter.com and
throw away the protocol and the www,
then the user is going to have to type
in literally twitter.com/username.
They can't even type
in that other stuff.
So that would be a
regression, a step back.
As for the .com, the .org,
and .edu, and so forth,
the short answer is there's
many different solutions here.
If I wanted to be stringent about .com--
and suppose that Twitter probably owns
multiple domain names, even though
they tend to use just this one.
Suppose they have something
like .org as well.
You could use more parentheses here and
do something like this-- com or org.
I'd probably want to go
in and add a question mark
colon to make it non-capturing,
because I don't care which
it is, I just want to tolerate both.
Alternatively, we could capture that.
We could do something like
this, where we do dot + so as
to actually capture that.
And then we could do
something like this.
If matches.group 1 now equals equals
com, then we could support this.
So you could imagine factoring out the
logic just by extracting the Top-Level
Domain, or TLD, and then just using
Python code, maybe a list, maybe
a dictionary, to validate
elsewhere, outside of the regex,
if it's, in fact, what you expect.
For now, though, we kept things simple.
We focused only on
the .com in this case.
Let's make one final
change to this program
so that we're being a little
more specific with the definition
of a Twitter username.
It turns out that we're being a little
too generous over here, whereby we're
accepting one or more of any character.
I checked the documentation for Twitter.
And Twitter only supports letters
of the alphabet, a through Z,
numbers 0 through 9, or
underscores, so not just dot,
which is literally anything.
So let me go ahead and
be more precise here.
At the end of my string,
let me go ahead and say,
this set of symbols in square brackets.
I'm going to go ahead and say a through
Z, 0 through 9, and an underscore.
Because, again, those are
the only valid symbols.
I don't need to bother with an
uppercase A or a lowercase z,
because we're using
re.IGNORECASE over here.
But I want to make sure now that
I tolerate not only one or more
of these symbols here but also maybe
some other stuff at the end of the URL.
I'm now going to be OK with there
being a slash, or a question mark,
or a hash at the end of the URL, all
of which are valid symbols in a URL,
but I know from the
Twitter's documentation,
are not part of the username.
All right.
Now I'm going to go ahead and
run python of twitter.py one
final time, typing in
https://twitter.com/davidjmalan, maybe
with, maybe without a trailing slash.
But hopefully, with my biggest fingers
crossed here, I'm going to go ahead now
and hit Enter, and thankfully my
username is, indeed, davidjmalan.
So what more is there in the
world of regular expressions
and this own library?
Not just re.search and also re.sub,
there's other functions, too.
There's re.split, via which
you can split a string, not
using a specific character or
characters like a comma and a space,
but multiple characters as well.
And there's even
functions like re.findall,
which can allow you to search for
multiple copies of the same pattern
in different places in a
string so that you can perhaps
manipulate more than just one.
So at the end of the day now, you've
really learned a whole other language,
like that of regular expressions,
and we've used them in Python.
But these regular expressions actually
exist in so many languages, too,
among them JavaScript, and
Java, and Ruby, and more.
So with this new language, even
though it's admittedly cryptic
when you use it for the first time,
you have this newfound ability
to express these patterns that,
again, you can use to validate data,
to clean up data, or even extract
data, and from any data set
you might have in mind.
That's it for this week.
We will see you next time.