[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right,
this is CS50's introduction
to programming with Python.
My name is David Malan.
And this is our week on exceptions.
Exceptions in Python as well as
in other programming languages
refer to problems in your code.
Indeed, when something is
exceptional in your program,
it actually doesn't
mean it's a good thing.
It means something has gone wrong
that, ideally, you will somehow solve.
So what are some of the
things that can go wrong?
So I'm going to go ahead and open
up VS Code on my computer here.
And in the terminal window, I'm going
to go ahead and run code of hello.py.
That's going to, of
course, open up a brand
new tab for me, hello.py, in
which I can write my code.
And let me go ahead and write
some very simple code just
to say hello to the world.
Let's go ahead and say
print "hello, world.
And then let me go ahead and--
I'm forgetting to close that quote.
So a mistake that you yourself
might have already made
or might surely in the future
make-- and it's a little subtle
because you might not necessarily
notice that you've just
missed that one character.
Well, let me go ahead and
somewhat optimistically
go down to my terminal window now and
run Python of hello.py and hit Enter.
And that's the first of my errors.
My gosh, I've only
written one line of code.
And I seem to have more lines
of errors on the screen.
But the salient point is
this bottom-most thing here.
Notice where it says syntax error.
A syntax error is a problem with the
code that you have typed, your syntax.
Just like English and
other human languages
have syntax associated
with them, so does my code.
And it's not quite correct.
Something is awry.
I didn't follow the
instructions properly.
And it does elaborate for me,
unterminated string literal.
Now, that's a bit arcane.
That is a bit of a
confusing error message.
But unterminated would
generally mean that I
started something but didn't stop it.
I didn't terminate it.
String, of course, is a sequence of
text, like we've discussed before--
or stir in Python.
And literal generally refers to
something that you literally typed.
It's not a variable.
It's something like quote unquote--
or just "hello world.
So the fix here, of
course, is going to be
to go ahead and terminate that
string and actually close the quote.
And if I now go back down
into my terminal window
and rerun Python of hello.py, now
I'm saying hello to the world.
So the catch with syntax errors here
is that syntax errors are entirely
on you to solve.
A syntax error is a problem that
you've got to go back into your code
and fix from the get-go.
You can't just kind of
hope that it's going
to resolve itself or expect
that other parts of your code
will catch it for you.
Syntax errors just must be fixed.
But there's a lot of other
types of errors in Python
that might be described
as runtime errors, that
happen while your code is running.
And it's really up to you to write
some additional code defensively
to detect when those errors happen
because you don't necessarily know,
for instance, what input humans are
going to type into your program.
And so you better be ready,
defensively, to accommodate things
that they type or even misstype.
So, for instance, let's go
back over here to VS Code.
And let me propose that we take a
look at a new file all together.
I'm going to close hello.py.
And I'm going to write
code of say number.py.
So let's play around with
some numbers in Python.
And the first thing I'm going to go
ahead here and do with number.py,
after opening this new tab, is I think
I'm going to go ahead and print--
type up a relatively simple program that
maybe prompts the user for an integer,
like x, and then just
prints out what x is.
So we're going to start simple,
but, again, in starting simple,
we'll be able to really see
where I've done something wrong.
Well, here we go.
I'm going to go ahead
and say a variable called
x is going to get assigned the
value of the return value of input,
quote unquote, "what's x?"
And I'm going to include a space to
move the cursor over a little bit.
And then, ultimately, I'm going to
go ahead and-- oh, wait a minute.
If I'm wanting to get
an int from the user,
recall that I need to do
something proactively.
I need to actually convert
that input to an integer using
the int function in Python.
So now I'm passing the return value
of input as the argument to int.
And that will store in x,
ultimately, an integer, not
a string that looks like an integer.
All right, let me go ahead now and just
quite simply print out what this is.
I'm going to go ahead and print
out, quote unquote, "x is x."
But I don't want to
literally say x is x.
I want to plug in the value of x.
So maybe the easiest way to do that
is to surround it with curly braces.
And then if I'm using
these curly braces and I
want Python to interpolate
the value of that variable,
that is substitute what x actually
is in between those curly braces,
recall that I need to use a
format string or an F-string
by fixing this whole thing with an F.
Now that I've done that, let's go ahead
and see what happens.
I'm going to go ahead in my terminal
window and run Python of number.py.
I hit Enter.
And so far, so good.
All is well and being prompted for x.
Let me go ahead and type
in a number like 50.
All right, that seems to work.
Program seems to be correct.
Or is it?
What could go wrong in this program,
even though nothing did just go wrong?
But if I run it and run
it and run it again,
during the running of my program,
what could still go wrong,
especially if I'm not the
human interacting with it
but some other human instead?
Any volunteers here for this one?
What could go wrong?
And in what way is this program
not really correct, even
though at first glance it seems so.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So I'm
not calling an integer.
I'm still having trouble hearing you.
But what I think I heard is that
if what the user types in is not,
in fact, an integer, I can't just
blindly convert it to an int.
If I'm not putting too
many words into your mouth,
I think what I should perhaps do
here is be a little defensive.
And let me see if I can't
simulate exactly the problem that
could go wrong here.
Let me go ahead and run,
again, Python of number.py.
Let me try another number.
In fact, when testing
your code, generally it's
a good idea to test corner cases, maybe
numbers that aren't quite as plain as
or 49 or 51.
Let's choose some numbers that might
be a little more interesting, if only
mathematically, like zero.
All right, zero seems to work.
My code still prints out that x is zero.
What might be another
corner case to consider?
Well, let me go ahead and
try a negative number.
That, too, is pretty different
in spirit from negative.
Negative 1?
OK, that works too.
Well, let me try it one more time.
I've tried positive numbers,
negative numbers, 0.
Let me try something like a cat.
So literally, C-A-T-- typing in a string
that doesn't even look like a number.
And yet, let's see now what
happens when I hit Enter.
All right, we'll see now we've
got another kind of error.
It's not a syntax error, because I
didn't make a typographical mistake.
I didn't forget some piece of syntax.
I actually now have an
error with one of my values.
And it's an a value I
didn't even anticipate.
The human, me, in this case typed
it in long after I wrote the code.
So what does this refer to?
A value error.
Well, let's see what the explanation is.
Invalid literal for int with
base 10, quote unquote, "cat."
Now, this, too, is a bit of a mouthful.
And, unfortunately, in Python and
a lot of programming languages,
the error messages are written for
pretty comfortable programmers.
And, of course, when you're learning
programming for the first time,
you might not be so comfortable
with the programming language
let alone the error messages.
But let's see if we
can't glean some insight.
So invalid literal.
Well, again, a literal is just something
that's been typed in, it would seem,
for int.
What is int exactly?
Well, int is the function I'm
using to convert the user's
input to a corresponding integer.
Base 10, that refers to the
decimal system, which is this
the default that Python is using.
And it looks like at the end
of the day, what Python really
doesn't like is that I passed cat,
quote unquote, "to the int function."
So how do I go about
actually fixing this problem?
Well, I could just add
instructions in my program.
Maybe I could add a
line of print telling
the user more explicitly,
be sure to type an integer,
or, please don't type cat.
Please don't type strings.
Of course, the user
might still not oblige.
They might not be
reading the instruction.
So that too is probably
not an effective strategy.
What we really want to do is write
our code with error handling in mind.
We want to write lines of
code that not only accomplish
the problems we care
about but that also handle
errors that might unexpectedly happen.
And, in general, when programming,
programming defensively.
Assume that the users aren't going
to be paying attention or, worse,
they're malicious.
They're trying to crash your program.
So we want to handle as
many errors as we can.
Now, how do we go about
doing that in Python?
Well, it turns out whether you want
to catch a value error or other types
of errors as well--
though not syntax error--
Python actually has
this keyword called try.
And it's sort of aptly named.
If you want to try to
do something in Python,
you can literally use this keyword.
And you can check whether or not
something exceptional, something
erroneous, has happened.
So using both try and this
other keyword, except,
can I go and try to do something
except if something goes wrong?
I can do something else instead.
So let's consider, how
can I go about trying
to convert the user's input to an
int except if something goes wrong?
Well, let me go back to my code here.
And let me propose that I now
modify this example as follows.
Let me go ahead and, above
my first line of code,
I literally write, try and
a colon, telling Python,
try to do the following.
I'm going to go ahead and indent
my existing lines of codes
here by the same number of
spaces, four in this case.
And then I'm going to add one more new
line down here that literally says,
except Value Error.
And notice it's important
that I've capitalized the V
and I've capitalized the E.
These symbols are case sensitive.
And this is now an
opportunity, after this colon,
to tell Python what I want to
do in exceptional cases, when
the number or the input from the
user is not, in fact, a number.
And I'm going to say something
plain like print, quote unquote,
"x is not an integer."
I'm at least going to tell the user
roughly what the problem actually is.
So notice another detail.
The indentation is important.
Because I have try on line one and I've
indented lines two and three, those
are the two lines of code that I'm
trying, except if I see a value error,
line five, because it's
indented is what is
going to get executed in
cases of those errors.
Let me go ahead now back to my terminal
window and run Python of number.py,
Enter.
And let's go ahead and type in again.
Still seems to work.
And, of course, I'm
trying and succeeding.
Let me go ahead and try once more,
this time, though, with the word cat
or, really, anything that's
not a decimal number.
And now you'll see much more
cleanly x is not an integer.
I'm not seeing some scary
error message that I, the user,
am going to have no idea how to handle.
Now you, the programmer,
have anticipated
that something exceptional can happen.
And you've gone about actually
handling the error for the user,
giving them an appropriate
error message instead.
Let me pause here and see,
are there any questions now
on what we've just
done by introducing try
and accept to handle this value error?
AUDIENCE: Is value ever the
only type of error you can get?
Or are there other types?
DAVID MALAN: Is value error
the only thing you can catch?
There are other errors as well.
And we'll see a few of them today.
And there's many, many more,
honestly, that if you continue
programming and programming
in Python, you're
going to see a lot of them over the
weeks the months the years to come.
But the technique for
handling them is going
to be largely the same other
questions on try, accept,
or these exceptions more generally?
AUDIENCE: Yes, sir.
Actually, to use the except block, you
need to know the type of error, right?
[INAUDIBLE] what if you can't anticipate
this particular type of error?
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
So I'm being very good
about catching, so to speak,
the very error that I might happen.
I don't know when it
might happen because it's
going to depend on the user.
But I know what kind of error
will happen from the int function.
There is a way in Python where you can
say, except if anything goes wrong.
And you can literally omit value
error and just catch everything.
The problem with that is that it
sometimes hides other bugs in your code
because you don't necessarily
know what's going wrong.
And if you don't necessarily
know what's going wrong,
how can you possibly
handle it correctly?
So bad practice.
And it put another way, it's lazy to
do that, to just say, catch everything
and I'll deal with it here.
So a much better practice would be
to figure out what kind of errors
could happen and include mention
of them explicitly, as I have done.
Now, with that said, if you read
Python's official documentation,
as you'll eventually
invariably do, it is not
great about telling you
proactively what kinds of errors
can be raised in this way.
So it's a bit of contradictory advice.
You should do it this way.
But it's not always obvious
what you should be checking for.
But you get better at it with practice.
And some of the times, the documentation
does spell out what could go wrong.
Let me turn our attention
now back to this
and point out that even
though this is better code,
it is more correct in the sense that
I'm not just leaving it to the user
to see some really ugly default Python
error message that most people are
going to have no idea
what to do with, I'm
at least handling it more elegantly.
And I'm printing out
x is not an integer.
So it's at least more instructive.
But this isn't necessarily the
best way to implement this code.
Why?
Well, here, too, I'm actually
still being a little lazy.
So notice that I'm trying to do not
one line of code but two lines of code.
And this isn't a huge deal because we're
only talking about two lines of code.
But in the interest of
preaching best practices,
you should really only be trying to do
the one or very few lines of code that
can actually raise an exception
that can actually fail in some way.
I am pretty sure that calling print here
is not going to raise a value error.
Whether x is an int or a string
or a float or anything else,
the format string feature of Python is
going to handle printing it just fine.
So, really, what I'm
going to do is this.
I'm going to move this line three
down to the bottom of my code.
I no longer need to indent it.
I'm just going to execute it
at the bottom of my file here.
Unfortunately, by doing this--
I've done a good thing by now only
trying to do the minimal amount of work
necessary that might raise
the exception of value error.
But I fear I've
introduced a new mistake.
Well, let's see.
What is now incorrect?
Let me go ahead and again run
Python of number.py, Enter.
Let me go ahead and do
it correctly with 50.
And all seems to be well.
But, again, let's try
those corner cases--
the zeros, the negative numbers,
or, in this case, the cat.
Let me go ahead and type in C-A-T again.
Enter.
Now I have a name error.
So now it's yet another type of error
in my code that I've introduced here.
And what does this name error mean?
Well, just as a value error refers
to that-- the value of some variable,
the value that someone has
typed in is incorrect--
name error tends to refer to your
code, like you're doing something with
the name of a variable
that you shouldn't.
And why might that be?
Well, let me turn our
attention back to the code
here and consider, what
is it complaining about?
Well, the name errors
what I see down here.
And it's telling me, name, quote
unquote, "x is not defined."
And notice if I look further
here, it is mentioning line six.
So I know the problem is
with my code on line six.
And that worked a moment ago.
And I'm defining x on line two.
But let me ask the group here, why
does x, in fact, exist online six?
Why is it not defined, even
though I'm pretty sure I
was intending to define it on line two?
AUDIENCE: Maybe the scope of the
variable is between the [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: So, good terminology.
Scope refers to the portion of
code in which a variable exists.
That, too, though isn't
quite right in Python.
That would be true in C, C++, and Java,
where indentation or curly braces tend
to define the scope of a variable.
But, again, here in general--
and this worked a moment ago.
X exists once it's defined on
line two because, remember,
I printed out x is 50 a little bit ago.
Let's try one more hypothesis here.
One more hand?
Why is x somehow still not defined?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so is it
because it's local variable,
meaning that it doesn't
define outside of the scope
because what people have mentioned.
It prompts the input in try, right?
The outside of it is undefined.
DAVID MALAN: So still good instincts.
And good terminology, too.
There's this notion of local
variables, which tend to exist inside
of functions, for
instance, global variables,
which tend to exist in entire files.
In this case, too, though,
that's not quite the case.
What's happening here boils
down to order of operations.
Let me come back to the code here
and recall that any time we've
discussed the assignment operator,
the single equal sign, that copies
a value from the right to the left.
But consider for a moment at what
point something is going wrong.
Well, the input function is
probably working just fine
because we've used that a
lot now to get users' input.
It always returns a string
or a stir in Python.
But what could be going wrong?
Well, if I'm passing that string to
the int function as its argument,
it's probably the int's
function that's erroring.
And, indeed, if you think back
earlier when we had the value error,
it was, in fact, the int
function that did not
like, quote unquote, "cat" as input.
So this is all to say that
this portion of my code
highlighted now to the right
of the equal sign, that's
the code that's creating a problem.
That's the code that was
creating a value error.
And in this case, we're
catching the value error.
But because the value error is happening
on the right of the equal sign,
there's no value being
copied to the left.
The error is interrupting
that whole process.
So even though we see x equals
dot dot dot on line two,
the portion of that line to
the left of the equal sign
isn't getting evaluated,
ultimately, because the value
error is happening too soon.
And so when we finally
get down to line six,
even though it looked like
I was defining on line two--
and I would have defined x on
line two if all had gone well--
we didn't get to the part where the
value is copied from right to left
because the value error happened first.
So this code is just incorrect now.
So how do I go about
solving something like this?
Well, it turns out that there's
another feature of the try
and accept syntax that
Python supports, which is
that it also supports the keyword else.
Now, we've seen else before.
If you think back to our discussion
of conditionals, we saw if.
We saw elif.
We saw else, which was
kind of this catchall, what
you should do in the event
that nothing else is relevant.
That's kind of the same intuition here
for the try-except feature of Python.
What you can do is this.
You can try to do the following, as
I've done, except if this goes wrong.
But if nothing goes wrong,
else go ahead and do this.
So this is one way I can
solve this same problem now.
No matter what now, Python is
going to try to execute line two.
If something goes wrong, it's
going to execute lines three
and four to handle that value error.
However, if you try
and this code succeeds,
then there is no exception to handle.
So you're then going to
execute this line here.
So it's a little
confusing, perhaps, in that
we're now using else both for
conditionals-- if, elif, elif, elif,
else.
And we're also using else
with these try-except blocks.
But that's OK.
That's part of the language.
That's one of the features.
So now if I rerun this code in my
terminal window, Python of number.py--
let's do something correct, like 50--
I see that x is 50.
So line one is executed.
We're trying to do the following.
Line two is executed because the
conversion happened successfully
and the number 50 gets
copied from right to left.
The exception does not happen.
So we ignore lines three and four.
We jump immediately to line five and
six, which prints out the result.
By contrast, though-- let's
do this one last time.
Python of number.py-- let's type in cat
or, again, any other word and hit Enter
now.
We don't see what x is.
Rather, we see, quote unquote,
"x is not an integer,"
which is what's being
handled in my except clause.
All right, let me pause here
because that's a lot of new syntax,
and see here if there's any
questions on try, on except,
on else, name error, or value error.
AUDIENCE: Can you please
repeat the try function?
DAVID MALAN: Repeat the name error?
What's the problem with the name error?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
Yes.
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
So let's just rewind
a couple of lines here
before I fix this problem by
now getting rid of the else.
A moment ago, we had code
that looked like this, whereby
I was getting a name error,
Python of number.py, Enter,
typing in cat, that looked like
this, where name x is not defined.
And the problem was on line six,
according to this output in Python.
Well, let's think about
this now deductively.
Let's try a different approach.
On line six, I'm seeing an error
that name x is not defined.
OK, Python's already telling me
x does not exist at that point.
So how could that possibly be?
Well, where should x be defined?
Well, presumably, x is
defined on line two, up here.
So what could go wrong?
Well, if the user has inputted something
that doesn't look like a number,
like the word cat, passing
cat, the return value of input,
as the argument to int to convert
the word to an int makes no sense.
You can't convert a cat,
C-A-T, to an integer at all.
So the int function is raising
a value error at that point.
And the error is being
handled with this code here.
But notice this line
six is not indented.
It's left aligned with the rest of
my code, which means no matter what,
line six is going to execute.
It's going to execute whether I
typed in 50 or I typed in cat.
But if I typed in cat,
again, x never gets a value.
So it's not defined here on line six.
So when I introduced, finally,
the else statement, that
makes sure that these things
are mutually exclusive.
I only execute the else if I
tried and succeeded up above.
Well, let me propose that we refine
this just a little bit further as well
and consider how we might improve
this example a little bit more.
It's a little unfriendly of me to be
rejecting the user's input after they
fail to provide an integer and just
quitting the program, really, right?
It'd be more user
friendly if I just prompt
or reprompt the user again and again.
And in the chat, if you could,
what's the feature of Python
that you can use if you want
to do something again and again
and again until such time as the
user cooperates and gives you
what you're looking for, like a number?
So yeah, loop, loop, loop.
So a loop is something that
happens again and again and again.
And maybe we can use that same
mechanism, a loop, in order
to prompt the user for x.
And if they don't give us a
number, prompt them again.
And if they don't, prompt them
again and again and again.
We don't need to just
quit out of the program.
So, quickly-- so let me propose this.
Let me propose here that I improve
this code by deliberately doing this.
Let me induce a infinite loop at the
very top of my code with while true.
Recall that the wild keyword induces a
loop, a cycle that behaves like this.
And it asks a question,
a Boolean expression
that needs to evaluate
either to true or false.
Well, if I want this
thing to loop forever,
at least initially, we'll just say
while true because true is true.
So this has the effect
of doing something
no matter what forever unless
we break out of it early.
Now I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and
move my try except code
indented underneath this loop
so that I'm trying to get an x.
If I have a value error instead,
I print out x is not an integer.
But this time, what do I
want to do if the user does
try and succeed in giving me a number?
Well, I can do this.
I can just break out of my code here.
And down here now, I can
use that same line of code
from before, an F-string that says x
is, and then in curly braces, x again.
So what's going on here?
I think this code now,
because I've added
the loop, is going to have the
effect of trying at least once, maybe
a second time, maybe a third time maybe
500 times until the user finally gives
me what I want, which is an integer.
And once they do, once there's
no value error happening,
then I break out of the loop.
And line nine executes as I would hope.
So let me go ahead and try
executing this version--
Python of number.py, Enter.
What's x?
Let me go ahead and type
in the easy thing first--
50.
X is 50.
What just happened in
terms of the control flow
of this program, the flow of my logic?
Well, I first found myself
on line one inside of a loop.
Hopefully, I'll get out of this loop.
What did I then do?
On lines two and three, I tried
to get input from the user
and convert it to an int.
Well, I was a nice guy this time.
And I typed in 50, which
looks like and is a number.
So the int function
converted it just fine
and stored it from right to left in x.
Except value error?
There is no value error
because if I typed in a number,
there's nothing exceptional happening.
This is a boring, good
execution of my program.
So what happens?
I break out of the loop.
So, again, the else clause is associated
with the try not with the except.
And once I'm out of the loop, of
course, I'm just printing out what x is.
Well, let's try the other
scenario that might happen.
Python of number.py, Enter.
What's x?
Let's try cat or any other word.
Enter.
Ah, this is now a new feature.
I'm being informed what I did wrong.
X is not an integer.
So I'm getting some
useful user feedback.
But notice, again, I'm
prompted, what's x?
Well, let me try typing in dog.
X is not an integer.
What's x?
Let me try bird.
Enter.
X is not an integer.
What's x?
And suffice it to say, this will happen
now forever if I'm in an infinite loop
until I try and succeed,
at which point I break out.
So let's try again.
50, Enter.
Now I'm out of the loop.
And I'm printing out what x actually is.
All right, let me pause here and
see if there are any questions.
The logic is almost the same.
But what is different
now is I'm in a loop.
And I'm using the
keyword break in Python
to deliberately break
out of the loop when I'm
ready to, once the user has cooperated.
AUDIENCE: Do we really need to break?
Can't we just print?
Or what keeps us from just printing?
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
So let me try that.
Couldn't I just print?
Well, let's see what
happens if I do that.
Let me move this print line
at the end into my loop
here, thereby shortening the program.
And, in general, that's
been a good thing.
Python of number.py, Enter.
Let me go ahead and type in 50.
OK, x is 50.
What's x?
OK, maybe it's 49.
X is 49.
OK, maybe 48.
Unfortunately, I
think-- you're laughing.
You see it.
I never break out of the loop,
which maybe that's a feature.
Maybe you want this to be your program.
But I didn't.
I'd eventually like this game to stop.
So I need to break out in that way.
But I can do it a little differently.
And let me propose that we
modify this a little bit.
But, first, any other
questions on this syntax here?
Let me rewind to the prior version.
AUDIENCE: Hi, can I use a break
[INAUDIBLE] except and else?
For example, in another print,
may you use printing the else,
you can use prints together with
break or something like this?
DAVID MALAN: So you can use break
inside of loops to break out of loops.
And you can use it
inside of a conditional,
like an if, an elif, or an else.
You can do it inside of a try,
except, else statement to.
Any time you're in a loop
that you want to break out
of, you can use this keyword, break.
I'm using it in the
context of exceptions.
But it's not restricted to that.
And let me show you, too.
It doesn't even have to be in the else.
If I wanted to, I
could actually do this.
I could get rid of my else.
And I could go back to line three,
add another line that's indented,
line four, and break out here.
Now, why is this logically OK?
Well, consider what
I'm now trying to do.
I'm trying to execute line three and
converting the user's input to an int.
And I'm trying to store the
result from right to left in x.
If something goes wrong,
the code we've already seen
is immediately going
to jump to line five
and then six to handle the exception.
But if nothing goes
wrong, my code presumably
should just keep on
executing line by line.
So I could technically
logically put the break here.
And watch what happens
when I run this version.
Python of number.py,
50, Enter, it worked.
I broke out of the loop.
Now, which way is better?
Honestly, I think it could
go either way at this point.
This program is so
relatively short that even
though I'm trying to do two things
now, one of which, the break,
is not going to fail.
You either break or you don't.
There's no piece of data from the
user that's going to influence that.
We don't strictly need to have
those two lines of code there.
But it's only two lines.
So I think it's OK.
And if you recall our discussion in
the past, not just of correctness--
does the code work as
it should?-- but design,
I think you could argue it either way.
If you prefer the readability
of this and the fact
that you don't have
an else, that's fine.
If, though, you prefer
to minimize just how
many lines of code you're trying to
execute in case something goes wrong,
the else is a reasonable approach too.
Well, allow me to propose, too,
now that we refine this further.
I think we're at the point
where it's pretty darn correct.
But suppose now that I find
myself today and tomorrow
trying to get numbers
from the user quite a bit.
It would be nice, as we've seen, to
maybe just invent my own function,
get int to get an integer from the user
both today and tomorrow and beyond.
And, heck, maybe I can even share
that function with other people.
If they want to write programs,
they get integers from users.
So how might I go about doing this?
Well, let me go ahead and
propose that we do this.
Let me get rid of the print line
but keep most of my loop here.
Let me define a function called get
int that takes no arguments for now.
And I'm going to go ahead and
indent all of the code I already
wrote underneath get int.
So now I have a function called get
int that tries to do the following.
Try to get in it from the user.
If something goes wrong
and there's a value error,
yell at them with x is not an integer.
Else, break.
But it's not just breaking
that I want to do here.
Now that I'm in a function, recall
our discussion of return values.
If you're inventing your own
function whose purpose in life
isn't just a print something on
the screen like a side effect
but is to hand back a value,
to hand you back a value,
like on that same post-it note
from our discussion of functions,
well, you need to return x explicitly.
How do I now use this function?
Well, as soon as we start
making our own functions,
it tends to be convenient to define
our own main function as well.
That's the main part of our program.
And I'm going to keep this simple.
I'm now going to say, x equals get int.
And then on the next line, I'm going
to do that print from before, quote
unquote, "x is"-- in curly braces--
"x."
And at the very bottom
of my program recall,
I'm going to call main,
so that no matter what,
I'm invoking my main function
after everything's been defined.
Well, let's see how this works.
Let me go ahead and run
Python of number.py.
Enter.
Let's type in 50.
And it seems to work as before.
Let's go ahead and run it again,
typing in cat, C-A-T, this time.
X is not an integer.
And I'm being prompted.
Dog, and I'm being prompted.
Bird, and I'm being prompted.
Fine, fine, fine.
50.
That's an int.
And so it is printed.
So what's worth noting here-- well, I'm
manifesting a couple of good properties
here.
One, I've kind of abstracted away
this notion of getting an integer.
And even though I just
artificially hit Enter
a whole bunch of times just to
hide that function for now--
it needs to be there, but we don't
need to see it at this point-- notice
that now this entire
program really boils down
to just these three lines of code now.
Why?
Because I've abstracted away that whole
process of getting an int from the user
into this new function
of my own called get int.
But can I improve upon this?
Well, let me go and undo
all of those blank lines
and pull this up just so we can
see more on the screen at once.
Can I tighten up my
implementation of get int?
It is correct.
I claim this is correct.
It's handling errors.
And it's returning x.
But I don't, strictly speaking,
need to write the code as long.
What else could I do?
Well, let me propose that if all you're
doing on this line 13 is breaking
and then immediately after
that, per the indentation,
you're executing return x on line 14,
why are you wasting everyone's time?
Once you know you're ready to return
the value, you could just return x.
And so in my else, I could
break out and return a value.
So here, too, return is used to
return values from functions.
Break is used to break out of loops.
But it turns out that return
is sort of stronger than break.
It will not only break
you out of a loop.
It will also return a value for you.
So it's doing two things
for once, if you will.
But can I make this even more compact?
If my goal is to just tighten the code
up, even though it's already correct,
can anyone think of
a further refinement,
whether you've programmed
in Python before or not?
Can I shorten this implementation
further just a little bit,
if only to decrease the
probability that I've
made a mistake by having
fewer lines and just
make it a little easier to
read because it's shorter?
Any suggestions for tightening
up my implementation of get int?
AUDIENCE: You can just
return the value on the try
function, when you're trying.
You take the input x and then return x.
DAVID MALAN: Good.
We can just return x a little higher up.
And let me correct folks as we go.
It's not a try function.
It would be a try
statement, technically.
A function typically has a
parentheses and another one.
In this case, it's just a statement.
But we can do exactly that.
I don't technically need the else.
If I really want, I could do this.
Right after line nine,
I could return x here.
Or recall our discussion of defining
variables unnecessarily sometimes.
Why define a variable here
if you're immediately going
to use it here and then never again?
So we could avoid a new line here.
And I could avoid even
defining x explicitly.
I could just say something like this.
I could return int, input,
quote unquote, "what's x?"
I can do it all at once.
Now, which is better?
I don't know.
I mean, again, this is where
reasonable people might disagree.
I'd argue that, on the one hand,
we're tightening up the code.
We're using fewer lines.
It's easier to read, lower
probability that I've made a mistake.
On the other hand, it's a little more
complicated to understand, perhaps.
It's a little less obvious
where I'm returning from.
So I think arguments
can be made either way.
At the end of the day, what's important
is that you've done this consciously.
You've made a decision to
do it this way or this way.
And you can justify it in your mind--
not that your answer is, eh, it worked,
so I left it alone.
Have a good reason.
Come up with a good reason.
And that will come with
experience and practice.
Well, let me propose to you that
we make one other refinement here.
Suppose that you're finding your
programs to be a little noisy.
And it's a little obnoxious
that you keep telling the user,
x is not an integer.
X is not an integer.
What if you want to make things
a little gentler and just prompt
the user again with the
same words, what's x?
What is x?
What's x?
Again and again.
Well, you can do that as well.
And it turns out that if you want
to handle an exception in Python
but you want to pass on doing anything
with it-- so you want to catch it,
but you essentially want to ignore it.
You don't want to print anything.
You don't want to quit the program.
You just want to
silently ignore it, like
if you're talking in a room full of
people and it's your turn to talk
and you're just like, pass.
They're still calling on you.
But you're not doing or
saying anything more.
Well, we can add this
keyword to our code here.
Let me go back to my program here.
And instead of printing out again
and again, x is not an integer,
I could just do this.
I could pass on handling
the error further.
I'm still catching it.
So the user is not going to see a scary
message even mentioning value error.
My code is catching it.
But I'm passing on
saying anything about it.
I'm going to stay in the loop.
I'm going to stay in the loop and keep
prompting and reprompting the user
so now the effect looks a
little something like this.
Python of number.py.
Let's type in cat.
What's x again?
Let's type in dog.
Type in bird.
So it's just a little, maybe, more
user friendly and that you're just
reminding the user what you want.
Maybe it's worse.
Maybe it would be helpful
to tell the user why
you're prompting them again and again.
It's not obvious.
So it could go both ways.
But, again, it's just another mechanism,
now, for handling these errors.
We use the except keyword
to catch a specific error.
But we don't have to
handle it more than that.
We can just pass on
doing something further.
Let me pause here and see if there's
any questions now on try, accept, else,
or pass?
AUDIENCE: OK, yeah.
No.
I was just kind of curious,
I guess, about the idea
of when you were inventing with
the get int function, for example.
Because I'm noticing,
obviously, going through it
with the whole logic and breakdown
of the entire function, while true,
do this.
But I'm just kind of curious in
elaborating with the indentations
for the code more.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So the invitation is
deliberate logically.
Some languages don't require
as rigorous indentation.
You can use curly braces
or other symbology
to make clear what is
associated with what.
In general, any time you indent
something in Python on this line--
rather, anytime you write a code a
line of code in Python that's here
and the lines below it
are somehow indented,
that means that those lines are somehow
associated with that first line.
And, presumably, those
indented lines should only
be executed if the first line
told the computer to do so.
So, concretely, what does this mean?
On line six here, we're
defining a function called
get in that takes no arguments, colon.
Everything that's indented
by at least four spaces
hereafter is part of that function.
Why?
That's just the design
of the Python language.
Frankly, I think the designers got tired
of seeing really ugly code in languages
like C and C++ and Java that don't
necessarily enforce indentation to this
extent.
So now it's baked into the language.
And my chronology might
be a little off there.
But there's been many languages
that are looser than Python when
it comes to indentation.
The indentation is
meaningful on line seven too.
Notice that because the while
true is indented by four spaces.
That just means it's part
of the get int function.
But notice below the while true
statement, there is eight, there's 12,
there's eight, there's 12 spaces here.
And I'm just quickly counting the dots.
That means that all of the
lines I've just highlighted
are inside of that while loop.
While true means to execute lines
eight through 11, potentially,
again and again and again.
And now, lastly, on line eight,
because we have try and indented below
it is line nine, that just
means that what you should try
is what's on line nine.
And similarly, on line 10, below
it, we have indented line 11.
You should only pass when there
is an exception of a value error.
So the indentation just means
what is associated with what.
And once you get comfortable
with that, you'll
see that the indentation alone helps
explain the logic of your program.
And it has a wonderful side effect
that for yourself the next morning,
for your colleagues, your family,
your friends, your teachers, your code
is much more readable as a result. It's
not one big mess of a blob of text.
Other questions now on
try, except, else, or pass?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, thanks.
Two question.
Question one-- once you
say pass, can the caller
still learn anything about this era
through a system variable or whatever?
And question two-- problem set zero
referenced some string methods,
including is numeric--
is it any different to [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
So on the first question, if I'm
handling the error in this way,
the caller is not going
to know anything about it.
That's the point of my handling it, so
that main or other callers don't know
that anything technically went wrong.
On the second question, is
numeric is another function
that you can call that can
look at a string and determine
is this, in fact, a number.
I could use a mechanism like that.
I could use a conditional.
If this looks like a number,
then pass it to the int function.
And go ahead and convert
it to an integer.
That's totally fine.
I would generally say that the
Pythonic way of doing things is often,
for better or for worse, to
try things, hope they work.
But if they don't, handle the exception.
So other languages are more in favor
of checking if, if, if, if, elif, else,
and all of these conditionals.
Python tends to be a little
more of the mindset, eh, try it.
But just make sure you're
handling the error.
So this would be the
Pythonic way of doing it.
Your way, though-- checking with the
conditional, is it a number first?--
is totally reasonable too,
if you want to go that way.
Well, let me propose
some final refinements
to this program that really
just kind of tighten things up,
one additional step to improve
the implementation of this
get int function.
Let me propose that we not hard code,
so to speak-- that is type manually x
all over the place.
Let's make this function, get
int, a little more reusable.
Right now, notice that I'm just kind of
using the honor system that, well, main
is defining a variable called x.
And get int is asking
for a variable called x.
But it would be nice
if the caller, main,
doesn't have to know what the call-ee
is naming its variables and vise versa.
So caller-- to call a
function means to use it.
The caller is the
function that's using it.
The call-ee is just the
function being called.
It would be nice if I'm not just hoping
that x is the same in both places.
So let me propose this.
Let me propose that we actually add
a parameter to get int, like this.
What's x?
That is to say, if main wants
to use the get int function,
well, then main should probably
tell the get int function what
prompt to show the user.
Just like the input function, recall,
that comes with Python, it's up to you
to pass in a prompt that the user then
sees when the human is asked for input.
So how do I make this work here?
I can go down to my
definition of get int.
And I can say, all right, get int
is going to take a parameter now,
called prompt.
I could call it anything I want.
But prompt in English is
pretty self-explanatory.
It means the message the user will see.
And now, down here, when
I actually use input,
I don't have to
presumptuously say, what's x?
Because what if the
program, the caller, wants
to ask for y or z or
some other variable?
I can just pass to input whatever
prompt the caller has provided.
So now I'm making more reusable code.
It still works just the same.
I haven't changed the
functionality, per se.
But now it's a little
more dynamic because now
get int doesn't have to know or care
what variable's being asked for,
what's being asked for.
It just needs to know what prompt
it should show to the user.
So if I now run this program down
here, again, prompt number.py, Enter,
what's x?
50 still seems to work.
Let's run it again.
Let's type in cat.
It still seems to work.
And if I type in cat, dog,
bird, or anything else,
it will keep prompting me with
that same prompt, making this code,
therefore, all the more usable.
Now it turns out, too, you can
even raise exceptions yourself
using Python's raise keyword.
But more on that another time.
So in the coming days, the
coming weeks, the coming months,
as you write more code in Python,
you'll see that errors are inevitable.
Sometimes they're syntax
errors, which you've
got to just fix if you even
want to run your program at all.
But they could be name
errors-- for instance,
variables that you meant to define
but somehow didn't-- value errors,
where maybe the user didn't cooperate
and provided you with something that
you weren't expecting, or a whole list
of other possible errors or exceptions.
But now, hopefully, you know
how you can handle these errors
and respond to them in any way you like.
This, then, was our look at exceptions.
And we'll see you next time.