[CLASSICAL MUSIC]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right,
this is CS50's Introduction
to Programming with Python.
My name is David Malan, and this is our
week on object-oriented programming,
or OOP.
It turns out that, in
the world of programming,
there's different paradigms
of programming languages.
There's different ways of
solving problems with code,
and it's a little hard
to see this at first
if you've only learned one language.
But over time, if and when you learn
other languages besides Python,
you'll start to notice certain
patterns and certain capabilities
of some languages but not another.
Thus far, within the
world of Python, you and I
have largely been writing code that's
procedural in nature, whereby we're
writing procedures;
we're writing functions;
and we're doing things top to bottom.
Everything is step by
step by step, as you would
expect in general from an algorithm.
But along the way,
we've actually dabbled
in another paradigm known as functional
programming with Python whereby we've
been able to pass functions around.
We even had an anonymous
function some weeks ago.
And that's evidence of features of
a functional programming language,
even though we've just
scratched the surface thereof.
Today we focus on another paradigm,
and this one in more detail--
namely object-oriented programming.
And now, while some of you might
have prior programming experience
and have learned languages like Java,
which are, by design, fundamentally
object-oriented, Python indeed
allows you a bit of flexibility
when it comes to how you
solve problems with code.
But it turns out
object-oriented programming
is a pretty compelling
solution to problems
that you invariably encounter as
your programs get longer, larger,
and more complicated.
So indeed, OOP, for
our purposes, is going
to be a solution to a problem that
builds on so many of the lessons past.
So let's go ahead and do this.
Let's start by writing a
program very procedurally
by opening up VS Code here.
I'm going to go ahead and create
a program called student.py.
And in this program, I want to
do something relatively simple
initially, as we might have done
some weeks ago now, where I just
ask a user for their name and, maybe
in the context of the Harry Potter
universe, their house, and just
print out where that student is from.
And let's gradually enhance this program
by adding more and more features to it
and see if we don't stumble upon
problems that, up until now,
we might not have had very elegant,
well-designed solutions to.
But if we introduce, explicitly,
object-oriented programming
as a programming technique, I
bet we can clean up our code
and set the stage for writing even more
sophisticated programs, longer programs
down the line.
So in student.py, let me go
ahead and do a name variable,
setting it equal to the
return value of input,
and just prompt the user
for their name like this.
And then let me go ahead and do
the same for a house variable
and prompt the user for their
house, using input like this.
And let's do something super simple now.
Let's just go ahead and
print out an f string
that says something
like name from house,
just so that I can confirm that
the contents of these variables
are indeed as I expect.
I'm not going to do any
error checking or trimming
or anything like that for now.
I'm really just going to spit back
out whatever the user just typed in.
All right, let me go ahead
and run Python of student.py.
Let's use our go-to, like Harry, as
in Harry Potter, from Gryffindor.
And when I hit Enter, now let's see
if I see that Harry from Gryffindor
is indeed the case.
All right, so I think we have a working
program at this point, but let's
now introduce some of those lessons
learned way back from week zero
where we started writing
our own functions,
not necessarily because it solves
the problem more correctly--
I daresay this is correct as is.
But it begins to give us building
blocks that we can extend so
as to solve more complicated programs.
So let me go back up to student.py,
and let's go ahead now and do this.
Let's put the entire logic I just
wrote inside of our typical method
called main, and let me indent those
three lines so that at least they're
now combined into one main method.
But instead of using input
on line 2 an input on line 3,
don't we go ahead and
assume, for the moment,
that we've got some function
called get_name in the world,
and let's go ahead and assume we've
got another function like get_house
in the world that don't take parameters.
But their purpose in
life is, by their name,
going to be to get the user's name and
to get their users house, respectively.
And then I'm going to print out
the exact same f string as before.
I, of course, need to
implement these functions now.
So let me go lower in my file and
define a function called get_name.
Nothing in these parentheses because
it's not going to take a parameter.
And I'm going to go ahead and do
something like name equals input
("Name"), just like before, and then
I'm going to go ahead and return name.
So it's a super simple function,
but it's an abstraction.
I now have a function called
get_name whose implementation details
I don't have to care about anymore.
I just know that the function exists.
And I can tighten this up, in fact, .
Don't really need a
name variable on line 8
if I'm immediately going to return
that same name variable on line 9.
So let me just tighten
this up a little bit
even though it doesn't
change the functionality
and just immediately return the return
value of the inputs function call here.
Let's do something very
similar now for get_house,
which will similarly take no arguments.
I'm going to go ahead
and return the return
value of input, this time
prompting the user for their house.
And I need one final detail.
At the very bottom, let's continue our
habit of doing if the name of this file
equals, equals, quote, unquote,
main, then let's go ahead
and actually call main and
recall that we have that in place
so that, if this eventually becomes
part of a module, a library of sorts,
I don't accidentally call main blindly.
I only do it if I mean to run main
from the command line on this file.
All right, so if I didn't make
any mistakes here, let me go ahead
and, in my terminal window, again,
run Python of student.py, Enter.
Let's type in Harry, Enter.
Let's type in Gryffindor, Enter.
And we're set.
Harry from Gryffindor
seems to still be working.
So we haven't really solved
the problem any more correctly,
but I've laid the
foundation to maybe now do
some more interesting
things because I've
had these building blocks in place.
But let me propose that we could be
doing this a little bit differently.
get_name, get_house is fine.
But at the end of the day, I'm really
trying to get a student from the user.
I want their name and their
house, not just one or the other.
So maybe it would be
a little cleaner still
to define a function
called get_student and let
get_student do all of this work for us.
Now, theoretically, get_student could
call get_name and could call get_house.
But because these
functions are so short,
I think I'm OK with just defining
one function, called get_student,
that similarly won't take any arguments.
But it's going to do two things.
It's going to get the students name,
by prompting them with input as before.
And it's going to get
the student's house,
by also prompting them as before.
Now, hmm.
I want to return the
student, but I think
I might have painted
myself into a corner
here because I now have two
variables-- name and house.
And yet, up until now, we've pretty
much returned one or the other.
We've returned one value.
So any suggestions
for how we can perhaps
solve this problem that I just created
for myself, whereby I want to return,
really, a student, but I currently have
a name variable and a house variable.
I'd minimally like to
return both of those.
AUDIENCE: I believe that,
we can return a dictionary,
includes the name and the house.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
so we absolutely could
return a dictionary-- a dict object in
Python, whereby maybe one key is name;
one key is house; and the
values thereof are exactly
the values of these variables.
So we could totally do that.
I worry that that might be
getting a little complicated.
I wonder if there's a
simpler way instead.
Any other instincts-- even if
you're not sure it would work?
AUDIENCE: Return both name and house?
DAVID J. MALAN: Return
both name and house.
I like the sound of that.
It sounds simple.
I don't have to figure out what a
dictionary is going to look like.
And in fact, this, too,
would be a valid approach,
even if you've not seen this before.
It turns out, in Python, that
you can return multiple values,
but that's a bit of a white lie.
Or we could take Muhammad's approach
of actually returning a dictionary
and putting multiple keys therein.
So here, again, we have
yet another example
of how you can solve the same
problem in at least two ways,
and I daresay we're
about to see even more.
So one way you could solve
this problem, whereby
you want to return multiple values,
would be to do something like this.
I could go ahead and literally return
not just name, but I could put a comma
and also return house.
This is not necessarily something
you can do in other languages
if you have programmed in
other languages before.
It depends on the language.
But it looks like, thanks to
this comma, maybe I can, in fact,
return two values as
[INAUDIBLE] proposed.
Well, if I'm returning to
values in this way on line 10,
how do I get both
values at the same time?
Well, there's a couple of ways.
Let me go up to my main function.
I know, minimally, I'm going
to have to change the get_name
and get_house to get_student.
But what am I going to
store the return value in?
I think I could actually do this.
And we have seen this technique
before, where you can unpack,
so to speak, sequences of
values that are coming back.
And indeed, consider this
to be exactly that. name,
house is some kind of sequence that
I'm returning of values-- name, house.
So if I want to unpack
those and store the return
values in two separate
variables, I can, in fact,
use the commas on the left-hand side of
my assignment operator, the equal sign,
to do just that.
Now, to be clear, I don't need to call
these variables name and house here.
I could simplify this and
use just n here and h here,
and then I could return just n and h.
But I would argue that's not very clear
to the reader as to what's going on.
So I think, in this
case, even though it's
a coincidence that I've used the
same variable names in get_student
and get_name, and in main, it's a
little more readable to someone like me.
So I'm going to leave it as is.
Well, let's go ahead and
see, now, if this works.
Let me clear my screen down here
and run Python of student.py, Enter.
Let's again type in Harry.
Let's again type in Gryffindor, Enter.
And voila, we still see that
Harry is from Gryffindor.
But what are we actually doing here?
What are we actually doing
by returning this value?
Well, it turns out that what
we've just done is use a tuple.
A tuple is another type of data in
Python that's a collection of values--
x, y or x, y, z.
It's similar in spirit to a list,
in that sense, but it's immutable.
It's not mutable.
Now, what does that mean?
A list, as we've seen it before,
is a data structure in Python
that you can change the values of.
You can go into bracket 0 for the first
location and change the value there.
You can go to bracket 1, bracket
2, bracket 3 and actually change
the values in lists.
But if you have no intention of
changing the values of variables
and you want to return,
effectively, multiple values,
you don't have to even
return it as a list.
You can return it as a tuple
instead, just by using a comma.
And it turns out we can make
explicit that-- here's the white lie.
I'm not actually returning
to values per se.
Whenever you use a comma
in this way on line 9,
you're actually returning
one value, which is a tuple.
Inside of that tuple now are two values.
So it's similar in spirit to
returning one list with two thing Here
I'm returning one tuple with two things.
And the mere fact that I've
used a comma and nothing else
tells Python that I indeed
want to return a tuple.
But there's more explicit
syntax that we can use instead.
I can actually-- more verbosely-- put
explicit parentheses around the values
of this tuple just to make
more clear to me, to the reader
that this isn't two values per se.
This is one value with
two things inside of it.
And what I can actually
do then, too, is--
I don't have to unpack
this up here, so to speak.
I can actually go up here and maybe
give a more apt name, like student,
and I can name the value,
or rather name the variable
in which I'm storing the
return value of get_student as,
quote, unquote, "student."
So maybe this is a
little better design now
because I'm sort of abstracting
away what a student is.
It's implemented at the moment
as a tuple with two values.
But at least, now I have a variable
called what I mean, a student.
But there's going to be a catch.
On line 3, I still want to print out
that student's name and their house.
But I don't have a name variable
anymore, and I don't have a house.
And I also don't have a dictionary, as
was proposed earlier, so I can't even
go at those keys by name.
But what a tuple is-- it's very
similar in spirit to a list,
but it is indeed just immutable.
And what I mean by that is
I can still index into it
numerically by saying
student [0] for the item
in the first location in that tuple.
And then over here, instead of
house, I can say student [1].
student [1] is going to give me
the second location in that tuple.
Let me go ahead and
clear my terminal window.
Again, run Python of student.py.
Let's type in Harry.
Let's type in Gryffindor, Enter,
and we still have some working code.
Let me pause here now
and see if there are
any questions on this
technique of returning a tuple
and indexing into it in this way.
AUDIENCE: I guess, what's
an actual use case where
you would use a tuple versus a list
or something else that's similar?
DAVID J. MALAN: It's a
really good question.
When would you use a
tuple versus a list?
When you want to program
defensively, or, in general,
when you know that the values in
this variable shouldn't change,
so why would you use a data type
that allows them to be changed?
It just invites mistakes,
bugs down the line, either
by you or colleagues who are
interacting with your code.
So tuple is just another
way where you can increase
the probability of correctness by just
not letting anyone, yourself included,
change the contents therein.
So it's just another
tool in your toolkit.
But let's make clear, then,
what I mean by "immutable."
Again, I claim that "immutable" means
that you cannot change the value.
Well, let's go ahead and try to do this.
Let me go ahead and run this
program once more as is--
Python of student.py.
Let me go ahead and
type in, for instance--
how about Padma's name?
And I'm going to go
ahead and say that Padma
is in Gryffindor as in the movies.
And we see-- Padma from Gryffindor.
But technically, I went down this
rabbit hole in looking at Harry Potter
more closely.
Technically, in the books, Padma,
I believe, was from Ravenclaw.
So this is actually a
mistake or an inconsistency
between the movies and the books.
Let's see if we can't fix this
inconsistency in our code.
So how about we do this?
If the student's name that's
inputted equals Padma,
why don't we override
whatever the house is
and change it to be properly Gryffindor.
Let me go ahead and do if student--
now, if I want to get at Padma's name,
I'm going to have to do student [0].
I have to know what location
the name is in in this tuple.
But if that value equals equals Padma,
let's go ahead with this if statement
and make a change.
Let's change the student's [1] value.
So the second value, if
we're zero indexing--
let's change it to be another
house in the world of Harry Potter
called Ravenclaw.
So I'm just fixing
maybe the user's input.
They watched the movie so
they type in Padma Gryffindor,
but, mm-mm, in the books,
it was Padma from Ravenclaw.
All right, let me go ahead and
go down to my terminal window,
clear my terminal, and do
Python of student.py, Enter.
I'm going to do Harry as well as
Gryffindor, just to demonstrate
that that is still working as intended.
Let me clear my screen again, though,
and run Python of student.py on Padma,
and I'll put her, too, in Gryffindor,
as in the movies, and hit Enter.
And now I just see a big
mess of errors on the screen.
Some kind of exception has been thrown.
And indeed, a type error has happened.
I'm using a data type wherein there's
an error, and what is that error?
Well, 'tuple' object does
not support item assignment.
It's a little arcanely expressed-- that
is, it's not really very user friendly.
But if you think about
what those words mean,
'tuple" object does not
support item assignment.
So assignment is copying
from right to left.
So somehow, that's invalid.
And here is a manifestation
of the immutability of tuples.
You cannot change location
0 or 1 or anything inside.
That is a feature.
That is the design of a tuple.
So if I want to override
that, I think I'm
going to have to use a different
type of data that we've used before--
namely a list, and that's fine.
If you want to enable yourself
and colleagues using your code
to change the contents
of that container,
well, we can go ahead and
return not a tuple using
explicit parentheses or no
parentheses, just the comma,
but I can use square brackets.
And if I'm using square brackets
on the left and the right,
this is indeed explicitly a list.
Same idea, but it's mutable.
That is to say you can change
the contents of a list.
So making no other changes,
just returning a list
with square brackets instead of a tuple
with parentheses or just the comma.
Let me go ahead now and run
Python of student.py, Enter.
Let me type in Harry
and Gryffindor again.
That's still working.
Good to see.
Let me run this once more and type in
Padma and Gryffindor, as in the movies,
but no, now we've corrected
it to be Padma from Ravenclaw,
as in the books instead.
Any questions now on tuples
versus lists or this idea
of immutability versus mutability.
AUDIENCE: Can we use a nested
tuple in Python, like a nest list?
DAVID J. MALAN: Absolutely.
You can have not only
nested lists in Python,
where one of the elements in a
list could be another list-- so you
have some square brackets out here; you
might have some other square brackets
inside.
You can absolutely do the
same with a tuple as well.
There is no constraint on the types
of values you can put in there.
We've not had occasion
to do that in this case.
I'm just returning a simple
tuple with two elements.
But yes, you could
absolutely do that, too.
Other questions on tuples versus lists?
AUDIENCE: OK, for example,
when I see the square brackets,
is it mainly used for the list?
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, a
really good question.
Sort of.
So when you create a value like
a list, you use square brackets,
and that would indeed
be a visual indicator
that this is definitely a list.
If you instead see parentheses,
that's a visual indicator,
when creating a value, that
it's definitely a tuple.
However, somewhat confusingly,
both lists and tuples
use square brackets when you
access the contents of them.
When you index into them
at location 0 or location 1
you always use square brackets.
So that's the distinction there.
Good question.
Allow me to propose now, if I may, that
we solve this problem yet another way,
and let's see if we're either making
things better or for worse than us.
Recall that dictionaries, or dict
objects, also exist in Python.
And a dictionary is this
collection of keys and values.
And the upside, in
particular, of a dictionary
is that they have better semantics.
You don't just have to
assume that a name is always
going to be at location 0; house is
always going to be at location 1.
That's the kind of thing, especially if
you had three, four, or more values--
eventually you or someone is
going to get confused and forget
what the order is and you're
going to write buggy code.
So a dictionary is a
little more powerful
in that you can semantically
associate keys, little descriptions,
with the values--
those keys and those
values, respectively.
So let me go ahead and do this, and we
can do this in a few different ways.
But let me propose that we
focus on get_student here .
And let's go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and delete the
implementation of get_student as is.
Let me create a student variable and
initialize it to an empty dictionary.
And I can do that with
just two curly braces here.
And then let me go ahead and set
two keys inside of that dictionary.
Inside of the student, there
will be, quote unquote, a "name"
key, and the value of that is going to
be whatever the return value of input
is when I prompt the
user for their name.
And then the "house" key, inside
of that same student dictionary,
is going to be the return value
of whatever the user types
in for their house. , And lastly I'm
going to go ahead and return student.
So now I am literally
returning one thing, still,
but this time, it's a dict rather
than a tuple, rather than a list.
But there are still two things
in it, technically four things
if you count the keys and the values.
But there's two key value pairs.
Now, my code up here is going
to have to change a little bit.
And let's simplify this and
remove, for instance, now
the Padma if statement just to
focus on what's changing at hand.
And let me go ahead now
and leave line 2 alone.
I'm still going to have a student
variable that gets assigned the return
value of get_student.
But what I want to do here now is
actually access the keys inside of that
dictionary-- not by numeric index,
which was for tuples and lists--
0 and 1, but by way of the keys.
Now, normally, I might be in
the habit, as I personally
am, of using double quotes-- quote,
unquote, "name" inside of there
and quote, unquote,
"house" inside of there.
But before I even run this
code and show you a mistake--
see an error on the screen,
does anyone want to call out
what I have done wrong here?
This is just an f string.
I just want to print out the value of
the name key, the value of the house
key in this dictionary.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Your audio
was a little garbled for us.
But I think I heard double
quotes and single quotes.
So I'm going to assume that, indeed,
you've identified precisely the issue.
I'm just going to
confuse Python right now.
Even though this is an f string inside
of double quotes, prefixed with an f,
I can't actually use my double
quotes inside my double quotes
because that's going to
potentially confuse Python.
If I run this program now,
Python of student.py and hit
Enter, I get a syntax error.
So the program didn't even run fully.
It just couldn't be understood because
it got confused by those double quotes.
So the simplest fix
here would indeed just
be to use not double quotes but
single quotes around the keys,
or conversely, flip the double quotes
on the outside to single quotes,
then use double quotes in the inside.
You just want to be consistent.
So a subtle detail, but again, this
is now specific to dictionary syntax.
This isn't fundamental to how we're
solving this current problem at hand.
Well, let's go ahead and try this.
Let me go ahead now and
run Python of student.py.
Let's go ahead and type in Harry.
Let's type in Gryffindor.
And hopefully, Harry is
back from Gryffindor.
No syntax errors.
No other errors.
I think I'm back in business here.
And what I do like to be
clear about using a dictionary
is that it's allowing me
just better semantics.
And again, I don't have to remember,
memorize, document that 0 is name;
1 is house.
Instead, "name" is name
and "house" is house.
It's just a little clearer,
a little more expressive.
So that's generally a good thing,
especially if we stored more data about
students than just their name and their
house-- if you had three fields, four,
five, 10 different fields--
no one's going to want to remember or be
able to remember forever which is zero
which is 1, which is 2, and so forth.
Better to introduce names, like
"name" and "house" in this case.
But let me tighten this up further.
I'm typically in the habit of not
introducing variables unnecessarily,
unless they make the code more readable.
And an alternative way to format
the same code would be this.
Strictly speaking, I don't need
to create an empty dictionary,
then add one key to it,
then add a second key to it,
and then return that dictionary.
I can actually consolidate this all
into one statement, if you will.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and say name
equals inputs return value,
house equals inputs
return value, and then,
instead of returning any variable name
student, which I'm going to propose
doesn't need to exist
anymore, let me just create
and return the dictionary all at once.
Let me do, quote, unquote, "name" in
lowercase here, and then the variable.
It's storing the user's name.
Then, quote, unquote, "house," as
my second key, the value of which
is going to be house, the variable.
Now, is this better?
Maybe, maybe not.
Maybe the first way was
a little more readable,
and that's totally fine
to create variables
if they improve the
readability of your code.
But just know that you can also create
and return a dictionary on the fly
like this, so to speak,
all in one line, and I
think it's arguably pretty
reasonable in this case.
Why?
It's just pretty short.
I probably wouldn't do this if it
got longer and longer and longer.
I might minimally then start moving
my key value pairs to separate lines.
But this would just be a slightly more
compact way of doing this as well.
But let me propose we
do one more change.
Let's go ahead and introduce
that same special casing of Padma
to fix her house from Gryffindor,
for instance, to Ravenclaw.
How do we do this with dictionaries?
Well, dictionaries,
like lists, are mutable.
You can change what is in
them, just like you can lists.
How do you do that?
It's just a little
different syntactically.
So let's go back into
main and do this fix.
If the student variable has a name
key that equals equals Padma, then,
indented, go ahead and change the value
of the house key inside of that student
dictionary to be, quote,
unquote, "Ravenclaw" instead.
So very similar in spirit
to what we did with a list.
But instead of using location 0 and 1,
we're much more clearly, explicitly,
semantically using, quote, unquote,
"name" and, quote, unquote,
"house," because you index into lists
and tuples using numbers, but you index
into dictionaries using
strings, as I've done here.
All right, let me go ahead
and run Python of student.py.
We'll again do Harry from Gryffindor.
And I think all is well.
Let me run it one more time this
time with Padma, who, in the movies,
is from Gryffindor, but should
really be from Ravenclaw.
Any questions then on this progression
from tuples to lists to dictionaries?
We haven't necessarily introduced
anything new, other than those tuples,
which have been available
to us all this time.
But the goal at the moment is just
to demonstrate this distinction
among these different
data types and how they
each work a little bit differently.
AUDIENCE: What if a combination
of lists is there in our tuple?
We can change the list because are
immutable but lists are mutable?
DAVID J. MALAN: Correct.
You can change the
contents of lists, and you
can put most anything you want in them--
other lists or strings, as I've done,
integers, or anything else.
Tuples you can do the exact same
thing, but you cannot change them once
you've created them.
A dictionary is more like a
list in that it is mutable.
You can change it.
But the way you index
into a dictionary is
by way of these keys, these
strings, as we keep saying,
rather than by numbers--
those numeric indices.
All right, well, let me
propose that there is yet
another way of solving this problem.
And I would argue that there's
now an opportunity at hand.
Even though this program isn't
particularly complicated--
all I'm doing is collecting a
name from the user and a house
from the user-- you
could imagine wanting,
longer term, to collect
even more information,
like the student's
patronus or magical spell
or a whole bunch of other information
that might belong in a student.
And right now, we're just using
these very general purpose data
types in Python--
a tuple to combine some values
together; a list to do the same,
but let us change it later; a
dictionary, which is more powerful
because it's a little more structured.
It does have keys, and it
has values, not just values.
But you know what?
We wouldn't have to be having this
conversation if the authors of Python
had just given us a data
type called student.
Wouldn't it have been
nice if there were just
a type of variable I could
create in my code called student?
Then we wouldn't have
to figure out, well,
do we use a tuple or a
list or a dictionary?
But that's pretty reasonable.
You can imagine just how slippery
of a slope that is, so to speak,
if the creators of a
language had to anticipate
all the possible types of
data that programmers like you
and me want to store in your programs.
So they just gave us these
general purpose tools.
But they gave us another
general purpose tool
that's going to allow us to
create our own data types as well
and actually give them names,
and that terminology is a class.
A class is like a blueprint
for pieces of data objects.
A class is a mold that you
can define and give a name.
And when you use that mold
or you use that blueprint,
you get types of data that are
designed exactly as you want.
So in short, classes allow you to
invent your own data types in Python
and give them a name.
And this is a primary feature
of object oriented programming,
to be able to create your
own objects in this way
and, in the case of Python in classes,
even give them some custom names.
So what does this mean in real terms?
Well, let me go ahead
and come back to VS Code
here, and let me propose that we
introduce a little bit of new syntax.
I'm going to go ahead and
clear my terminal window first.
I'm going to go to the top of my file,
and I'm just going to start a thought
but not finish it yet.
I'm going to use this new keyword for
classes, called, literally, class,
so the new keyword we're
going to have here.
And if I go back to
our slides here, this
would be the official URL
where you can read up more
on this particular feature of Python.
In the official tutorial, class
is a new keyword we can use.
Now, this is coincidentally related to
students because students take classes,
but it has nothing to do with the
fact that we're dealing with students.
Class is a general purpose
term in a lot of languages--
Python among them-- that allow you
to define these custom containers
with custom names for pieces of data.
So let's go back to VS Code.
Let's use this new keyword.
And let me propose that we
create a class called Student.
And by convention, I'm going
to use a capital S here,
and I'm going to go
ahead, and with a colon,
get to, later, the
implementation of this class.
So I'm just going to use dot dot dot,
which is a valid placeholder for now,
that just indicates to me
that I'm going to come back
to implementing this later.
But as of now, it does, in fact, exist.
I now have a student class defined for
me that I can now use in my code here.
How am I going to use it?
Well, first of all, let
me go down to get_student,
and let me change this code to no longer
use a dictionary but to use this class.
I'm going to do this.
I'm going to give myself a variable
called student, as I've done before,
but I'm going to set it
equal to capital Student ().
So I'm going to do what appears
to be calling a function
and that function, Student
with a capital S, notice,
matches the name that I gave
this class at the top of my file.
All right, what do I next want to do?
I'm going to go ahead and
give this student a name.
Now, if I were still
using a dictionary, I
would say student, quote, unquote,
"name," using square brackets.
But this is not a dictionary.
It turns out classes
have what, for now, we'll
call attributes, properties of sorts
that allow you to specify values inside
of them.
And the syntax for that
happens to be a dot.
We've seen dots before.
We've used it in the context of
modules and libraries, more generally.
This is another similar
in spirit use of a dot
that allows you to get at
something inside of something else.
So student.name is
going to be the syntax
I use for giving this student a name.
And that name is going to be whatever
the return value of "Name" is.
And then I'm going to go ahead
and say student.house to give
another attribute called "House" and
give that the return value of input
here, prompting the user for house.
And then, as before, I'm
just going to return student.
But now what's really
powerful about class,
and object-oriented
programming more generally,
is that I've created this custom
data type called, literally,
Student, capital S. I've stored
one such student in a variable
like I can always do in a variable
called student, lowercase s.
But I could call it anything I want.
It just makes sense to call it student
as well, but lowercase for clarity.
And then I'm returning that variable.
And because of my syntax
in lines 14 and 15,
that has the result of
putting inside of that class
a name attribute and a house attribute.
I just need to make one
more change up here.
I'm going to go ahead
and remove our Padma
code, just so we can
focus only on what's new,
rather than fixing her house.
And I'm going to go in here
and change the syntax that
previously was for dictionaries.
Again, dictionaries use square
brackets and then strings in quotes--
either single quotes or double
quotes, depending on the context.
Here, though, I'm going to
change this to be student.name,
and over here, I'm going to
change it to be student.house.
And that's just going to be my new
syntax for getting the contents of what
appears to be a class called student.
Let me go ahead and rerun
Python of student.py, Enter.
Let's type in Harry's name as before.
Let's put him in Gryffindor,
crossing our fingers as we often do,
and Harry is indeed from Gryffindor.
What, though, have I done?
Let's introduce one other
bit of terminology here
it turns out that I can create a
class, using that class keyword.
But any time you use a class, you're
creating what are called objects.
And here is the word objects, as an
object-oriented programming, or OOP.
Let me go back to my code here.
And even though I haven't really
implemented much of it at all--
I literally just left it
with a dot, dot, dot--
that's enough code, lines 1 and 2,
to just invent a new data type called
Student, capital S, that may or may not
have some future functionality as well.
That's enough to create a class.
What, though, am I doing on line 11?
On line 11, what I'm technically doing
is creating an object of that class.
So this, too, is another term of art.
You create objects from classes.
So if we go back to that
metaphor, that a class is
like a blueprint for a house
or a class is like a mold,
an object is when you use that
blueprint to build a specific house
or something that comes out of-- in
plaster, the mold, when you actually
use that mold to create such an object.
So a class is, again, the
definition of a new data type.
The object is the incarnation of,
or technically instantiation of.
And another term for objects
would actually be an instance.
You have instances of classes as well.
So that's a lot of vocabulary.
But at the end of the day,
it just boils down to this.
You can define your own class,
which is really your own data type.
You can then store attributes inside
of it, using this dot notation here.
And then you can access those same
attributes using code like this here.
And now, I have a proper
"student" data type,
and I don't have to
hack something together
using a tuple or a list
or even a dictionary.
I now have a proper data type called
"student" that the authors of Python
didn't give me; I gave myself.
Any questions now on classes, this
new keyword, class, or this idea
of these objects or instances thereof?
AUDIENCE: Is the class
object mutable or immutable?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
And we've clearly laid the stage
for having that conversation
about every data type now.
We will see that they are mutable,
but you can make them immutable.
So you can get the best of both worlds.
Now, by writing some actual code-- and
we'll write more code than the dot,
dot, dot in just a bit, other questions
on classes or these objects thereof?
AUDIENCE: Then what would be
the properties of those classes?
DAVID J. MALAN: So at the moment, the
properties of-- or the attributes of,
as I've been calling them thus far--
would just be "Name" and "House."
It turns out that there may very well
be other attributes built into classes
that we may see before long.
But for now, the only two
attributes that I care about
are the ones that I myself created--
namely "Name" and "House" or,
again, what I would call attributes.
And in a little bit,
we're going to start
calling those same attributes, more
technically, instance variables.
"Name" and "House," as I
presented them here in VS Code
are really just variables called
"name" and called "house" inside
of an object whose type is student.
All right, so what more can
we do with these classes?
Well, again, on line 11 is
where we're instantiating
an object of the student class and
assigning it to a student variable.
We're then adding attributes--
"Name" and "House," respectively--
on lines 12 and 13 currently.
Both of those have values
that are technically
strings or strs, because that's what
the return value of the input is.
But those attributes values
could actually be any data type.
We're just keeping things simple
and focusing on defining students
in terms of two strings--
"Name" and "House."
And then, on line 14, we're
returning that variable.
We're returning that object to
main so that we can actually
print out who is from what house.
Well, let's go ahead and add a bit more
functionality here because, right now,
on lines 12 and 13,
this is a little manual.
And it's a little reckless of
me to just be putting anything
I want inside of this student object.
It turns out with classes,
unlike with dictionaries,
we can actually standardize, all the
more, what those attributes can be
and what kinds of values
you can set them to.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me propose that it
would actually be really
nice if, instead of doing
this here, let me go ahead
and simplify my code as follows.
Let me go ahead and give myself
a local variable called name
and set it equal to the return value of
input, like we've done many times now
already.
Let me give myself one other
variable for now, called house,
and set it equal to the
return value of input
as well, prompting the
user for their house.
And now, instead of creating a
student object from my student class
and then manually putting the
name attribute inside of it
and the house attribute
inside of it, let
me actually do something more powerful.
Let me do this.
Let me call that Student function,
which is identical to the class name--
just by defining a
class, you get a function
whose name is identical to the class
name, with the capital letter included.
But instead of just
doing open parenthesis,
closed parenthesis, let
me pass in the name that I
want to fill this object with and the
house that I want to put in that object
as well.
And now let me set the return value as
before to be student equals like this.
So what have I done that's different?
Fundamentally, I'm still getting
user input in the same way.
I'm using input on line
11 and input on line 12.
And I just so happen to be storing
those return values in local variables.
And now we're setting the stage for
the more powerful features of classes
and object-oriented
programming more generally.
Notice that I'm deliberately
passing to this capital S Student
function, name, house--
I'm passing in arguments
to the function.
Now, the student class is not going
to know what to do with those yet,
but now I'm standardizing how I'm
passing data into this student class.
And ultimately, it's going to
give me an opportunity to error
check those inputs, to make sure that
the name is valid, that it has a value
and it's not just the
user hitting Enter.
It's going to allow me to ensure
that it's a valid house, that it's
Gryffindor or Hufflepuff
or Ravenclaw or Slytherin
or not just hitting Enter or some
random value that the user types in.
Because I'm passing "Name"
and "House" to the student
class, this particular
function, I'm going
to have more control over
the correctness of my data.
So let's now go up to the student
class, which, up until now,
I left as just dot, dot, dot.
It turns out that, in
the context of classes,
there are a number of not
just attributes or instance
variables that you can put
inside, but also methods.
Classes come with certain methods,
or functions inside of them,
that you can define, and they
just behave in a special way,
by nature of how Python works.
These functions allow you to
determine behavior in a standard way.
They are special methods in that sense.
Now, what do I mean by this.
Well, let me go back to VS Code here.
And let me propose that I start
to define a standard function
called underscore underscore,
or Dunder, as it's
abbreviated, init,
underscore underscore,
and then I'm going to go
ahead and do open parentheses,
and then I'm going to put in
here, literally, the word self.
More on that in just a moment.
But now, inside of this function,
I'm going to have an opportunity
to customize this class's objects.
That is to say this underscore,
underscore init method,
or Dunder init method is specifically
known as an instance method,
and it's called exactly this.
This is designed by
the authors of Python.
And if you want to initialize the
contents of an object from a class,
you define this method, and we'll
see what it's about to do here.
Let me go back to VS Code, and
let me do something like this.
self.name = name, and
self.house = house.
But I don't want to just init
this object very generically.
I want this method, called init,
to take in not just self but name,
house as well.
Now, what in the world is going on?
Because there's a lot
of weird syntax here.
There's this Dunder init method--
double underscore,
init, double underscore.
There's, all of a sudden,
this parameter called self.
And then there's this new
syntax-- self.name and self.house.
Now you're seeing really a manifestation
of object-oriented programming.
It's not all that
different fundamentally
from what we've been doing
for weeks with dictionaries,
by adding keys to dictionaries.
But in this case, we're adding
variables to objects, a.k.a.
instance variables to objects.
Now, what's going on?
Let's do this in reverse.
Let's go back to the line
of code we wrote earlier.
On line 15, I am treating
the name of this class--
Student with a capital
S-- as a function.
And I am passing in two values--
"Name" and "House."
What I've highlighted here
on the screen, on line 15,
is generally known as
a constructor call.
This is a line of code that is going
to construct a student object for me.
Using synonyms, it is going to
instantiate a student object for me.
And again, how is it going
to create that object?
It's going to use the student class
as a template, as a mold of sorts
so that every student
is structured the same.
Every student is going to have a name.
Every student's going to have a house.
But because I can pass in arguments
to this Student function, capital S,
I'm going to be able to customize
the contents of that object.
So if you think about the real world--
if you've ever been on a street
or a neighborhood where all of the
houses look the same but they might be
painted differently; they might be
decorated a little bit differently
on the outside, all of those houses
might have been built using the exact
same blueprint--
a mold, if you will.
But then you can specialize exactly
the finer points of those houses.
By painting the outside a different
color or planting different trees,
you can style them differently.
Similar in spirit here, we
have a Student blueprint
that's always going to have now a name
and a house, but it's up to you and me
to pass in any name and
any house that we want.
Now, where is this function?
The fact that I'm calling Student,
capital, S and then a parenthesis
and a closed parenthesis
with arguments inside
suggest that there's
a function somewhere
in the world that has been defined,
with def, that's going to be called.
Well, as you might have
guessed by now, the function
that will always be called, by
definition of how Python classes work,
is a function called double
underscore, init, double underscore.
Why?
It's a crazy name, but it's
what the authors of Python
chose to just implement the
initialization of an object in Python.
Now, the only weird thing--
especially weird thing,
I will admit, is this.
It would be way clearer, to me, too, if
the only two parameters for init we're
just name, house.
That's how we've defined every
function thus far in the class.
You just specify the parameters that
you want the function to accept.
And that lines up with
what I'm doing on line 15.
I am only passing in two
things to the student function.
But it turns out that
the authors of Python
need to give us a
little bit of help here
because suppose that you pass in
"Name" and "House" to this init method.
And a method is just a
function inside of a class.
What are you going to do
with the name and the house?
Literally, where are
you going to put them?
If you want to remember the name
and the house for this student,
you've got to be able to
store those values somewhere.
And how do you store them
in the current object
that has just been "instantiated?"
Well, the authors of Python
decided that the convention
is going to be that this init
method also, semi secretly, takes
a third argument, that
has to come first.
By convention, it's
called self, but you could
call it technically anything you want.
But the convention is
to always call it self.
And self, as its name
implies, gives you access
to the current object
that was just created.
What does that mean?
Again, now, on line 14, now that
it's moved down a little bit,
this line here is a constructor.
It constructs a student object.
But there's nothing in
that object initially.
There's no name; there's no house.
But the object exists in
the computer's memory.
It's up to, now, you to store the name
and the house inside of that object.
How do you do that?
Well, Python will just automatically
call this init method for you,
and it's going to automatically pass
in a reference to an argument that
represents the current object that it
just constructed in memory for you,
and it's up to you to
populate it with values.
And what this means is that,
inside of your init method,
you can literally do self.name
to create a new attribute, a.k.a.
an instance variable, inside
of that otherwise empty
object and put this name inside of it.
It allows you to do self.house
and store that value of house.
Now, you could call these
things anything you want.
They could be n.
They could be h, as before.
But that's really not
very self-explanatory.
Much better to do this kind of
convention. self.name equals name.
self.house equals house.
And this is like installing into the
otherwise empty object the value name
and house and storing them in,
really, identically named instance
variables in the object.
And again, an object is
just an instance of a class.
Now, I know that was
a lot of vocabulary.
That's a lot of weird syntax.
So any questions on this init
method, whose purpose in life,
again, is to initialize an otherwise
empty object when you first create it?
AUDIENCE: So what is the difference
between the init method and default
constructor?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
So in other languages--
if you programmed before.
For instance, Java-- there are
functions that are explicitly called
constructors that construct an object.
They initialize it with values.
Python technically calls this init
method the initialization method.
It initializes the value.
It's on line 15 now of my code, if I
scroll back down, that I'm technically
constructing the object.
It turns out there's another
special method in Python,
that we won't talk
about in detail today,
called underscore underscore,
new, underscore underscore
that actually handles
the process of creating
an empty object in memory for us.
But, generally speaking,
you, the programmer,
don't need to manipulate
the new function.
It just works for you.
Instead, you define your
own init method here
and init function inside of
your class, and that method
initializes the contents of the object.
So there's technically a distinction
between constructing the object
with new and initializing it with init.
But in the world of Python, you pretty
much only worry about the init method.
Python generally does
the other part for you.
A good question.
Others?
AUDIENCE: What about if you want
to store more than one name or more
than one house?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
If you want to store more than
one name or more than one house,
you can do this in different ways.
You could create other attributes--
technically called instance variables--
like self.name1, self.name2.
But we've seen, in the
past, that that is not
a very good design, just to
have multiple variables to store
multiple things.
Maybe, instead, you have an instance
variable called self.names, plural,
and you set it equal to a list
of names or a list of houses.
Now, in this case, I don't think that
really solves a problem because I'm
trying to implement a student, singular,
so it doesn't really make sense
to have multiple first names.
Maybe a nickname, maybe a last
name, so we could add those, too.
But I don't think we need
multiple names per se
and, in this case, multiple houses.
But absolutely, you could do that using
some of our familiar building blocks
like lists.
Other questions?
AUDIENCE: How are classes or
objects represented in memory?
DAVID J. MALAN: How are classes
and objects represented in memory?
So the class is technically just code.
It is the code on the top of my
file-- lines 1 through fou4--
that defines that blueprint,
that template, if you will.
Objects are stored in
the computer's memory
by taking up some number of bytes.
So you're probably familiar with
bytes or kilobytes or megabytes.
There's some chunk of
bytes, probably all
in the same location in
the computer's memory
or RAM, where those objects are stored.
But that's what Python, the
program, handles for you.
Python the interpreter figures out where
in the computer's memory to put it.
You and I, the programmers, get to
think and solve problems at this level.
Python, the interpreter, handles
those lower level details for you.
How about one final question
on classes and objects?
AUDIENCE: So my question
is if we can the same do
the same thing with the
dictionaries, so why to use classes?
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
If you can do the same things
as you can with dictionaries,
why should you use classes?
Because we are just scratching
the surface now of what
you can do with classes.
Allow me to go back, now,
to my keyboard and show you
more of what you can do with classes.
But in short, you can do
much more with classes.
You can ensure the correctness of
your data much more with classes.
You can error-check things.
And generally, you can design more
complicated software more effectively.
And we'll continue to
see, today, features
of Python and object-oriented
programming more generally
that allows us to do just that.
So let me propose, in fact, that first,
let's just tighten up this current
implementation, which again has us with
an init method that just declares two
instance variables-- self.name and
self.house, house, which, again,
just creates those variables inside of
the otherwise empty object and assigns
them values--
name and house, respectively.
Let me go ahead and just
do one little thing here.
I don't really need
this student variable.
Let me just tighten this up so that
each time we improve or change the code,
we're focusing, really, on
just the minimal changes alone.
So I've not fundamentally
done anything different.
I just got rid of the
variable name, and I'm just
returning the return value
of this student function
that's constructing
my new object for me.
So I'm just tightening things up as
we've done many times in the past.
Well, what if something goes
wrong in creating this student?
For instance, what if the user does
not give us a name, and they just hit
Enter when prompted for name.
I don't want to put in
my computer's memory
a bogus student object that has no name.
I'd ideally like to check for
errors before I even create it
so I don't create a nameless student.
It would just be weird and probably a
bug to have an object that has no name.
Similarly, I don't want
the user to be able to type
in something random as their house.
At least in the world of
Harry Potter, there's really
only four houses, at Hogwarts at least.
There's, again,
Gryffindor and Hufflepuff
and Ravenclaw and Slytherin--
a list of four valid houses.
It would be nice if I somehow validated
that the user's input is indeed
in that list.
Now, I could do all of that
validation in my get_student function.
I could check, is the name empty?
If so, don't create the student object.
Is the house one of those four houses?
If not, don't create the student object.
But that would be rather
decoupled from the student itself.
get_student currently exists as just
my own function in my student.py file.
But classes-- and really,
object-oriented programming-- more
generally encourages you
to encapsulate, inside
of a class, all functionality
related to that class.
So if you want to validate
that a name exists--
if you want to validate
that a house is correct,
that belongs just fundamentally in
the class called student itself,
not in some random function
that you wrote elsewhere.
Again, this is just
methodology because, again,
if we think about writing code that
gets longer and longer, more and more
complicated, it should make
just intuitive sense that,
if you keep all the house--
all of the name and all of the
house-related code in the student,
it's just better organization.
Keep all of the related code
together, and that's probably
going to set you up for more success.
And indeed, that's part
of this methodology
of object-oriented programming.
Let me go ahead now and
change my students classes
init method to do this.
If the name is blank--
so if not name-- and we've seen
this kind of syntax before.
If you say in Python,
Pythonically, if not name,
that's doing something like this.
If name equals, equals, quote, unquote--
but I can do this a
little more elegantly.
Just say, if not name,
would be the more Pythonic.
Well, I want to return an error.
I might want to do something like this.
Print missing name.
But this is not good enough.
It does not suffice to
just print out missing name
and then let the rest
of the code go through.
All right, well, what
could I do instead?
In the past, we've seen another
technique I could do sys.exit,
and I could say something like
missing name, and I could go up here
and I could import sys.
But this is a really obnoxious
solution to the problem.
Just because you or maybe
a colleague messed up
and called a function
with an invalid name,
you're going to quit my whole program?
That's really, really
extreme of a response,
and you probably don't want
to do that if your program is
in the middle of running.
You might want to clean some stuff up.
You might want to save files you don't
want to just exit a program sometimes
in some arbitrary line, just
because input was invalid.
So I don't think we
want to do that either.
But we do, now, have a
mechanism for signaling errors.
Unfortunately, I can't
do something like this.
I could try returning none and say,
uh-uh, this student does not exist.
I'm going to hand you back none instead.
But it's too late.
If we scroll back down to where I'm
creating the student, it's on line 17
now where I've highlighted this code.
The student has already been created.
There is an object somewhere
in the computer's memory
that's structured as a student.
It just doesn't have
any values inside of it.
But it's too late,
therefore, to return none.
That ship has sailed.
The object exists.
You can't just suddenly say,
nope, nope, there is no object.
There is an object.
It's up to you to signal an error.
And how do you signal an error?
Well, we've actually seen this
before, but we haven't had occasion
to create our own errors.
It turns out, in Python, there's
another keyword related to exceptions
that Python itself uses to raise
all of those exceptions we've
talked about in the past.
When you've caught things like value
errors or other such exceptions that
come with Python, well, it turns
out you, the programmer can raise--
that is create your own exceptions
when something just really goes wrong--
not wrong enough that you want to
quit and exit the whole program,
but enough that you need to
somehow alert the programmer
that there has been an error.
Something exceptional, in
a very bad way-- something
exceptional has happened, and let them
try to catch that exception as needed.
So let me go back to VS
Code here and propose
that, if the user passes in an
invalid name-- it's just empty,
so there's not a name.
Well, what I really want to do is this.
I want to raise a value error.
And we've seen the value errors before.
We've created value errors
accidentally before.
And generally, you and I have
tried to catch them if they happen.
Well, the flip side of this feature of
exceptions in a language like Python
is that you, the programmer,
can also raise exceptions
when something exceptional happens.
And you can even be more precise.
You don't have to raise a generic value
error and let the programmer figure out
what went wrong.
You can treat value error and all
exceptions in Python like functions
and actually pass to them an explanatory
message like, quote, unquote,
"Missing name," so that at least
the programmer, when they encounter
this error, knows, oh, I messed up.
I didn't make sure that
the user has a name.
And now, what do you want to do instead?
Well, now, if you're the programmer,
you could do something like this.
You could try to create a student
except if there's a value error.
Then you could handle it in some way.
And I'm going to wave my
hand with a dot, dot, dot,
at how you would handle it.
But you would handle it using try and
accept, just like we have in the past,
and that would allow
you, the programmer,
to try to create the student.
But if something goes wrong,
OK, I'll handle it nonetheless.
So what's new here, again,
is this raise keyword,
that just lets you and I
actually raise our own exceptions
to signal these errors.
Well, let me go back to
my code here, and I'm just
going to go ahead and not bother
trying or catching this error.
For now, we'll just focus
on raising it and assume
that, from our recon exceptions,
you could add try and accept
as needed in places.
Let me go back to the code here and
propose that something else could
go wrong with house.
If there is a name, we're good.
But if we're given a
house but it's invalid,
we should probably raise
an exception for that, too.
So what if we do this?
If house is not in the list containing
"Gryffindor," quote, unquote,
"Hufflepuff," quote, unquote--
let's see, "Ravenclaw," quote,
unquote, or "Slytherin,"
quote, unquote, then,
with my colon, let's
raise another type of value error.
But rather than raise
a generic value error,
let's pass in an argument,
quote, unquote, "Invalid house."
And so here we now see
a capability that we
can do with classes that
we can't with dictionaries.
If you add an attribute to a
dictionary, a key to a dictionary,
it's going in no matter what.
Even if the name is empty, even if the
house is a completely random string
of text that's not one
of these four houses,
it's going into that dictionary.
But with a class, and by
way of this init method,
you and I can now control exactly what's
going to be installed, if you will,
inside of this object.
You have a little more
control now over correctness.
And so now let me go ahead and scroll
back down to my terminal window
and clear it.
Let me run Python of student.py.
Let me type in something like Harry.
Let me type in Gryffindor,
Enter, and we see
that, indeed, Harry is from Gryffindor.
What if I made a mistake, though?
What if I ran Python of student.py
and typed Harry as the name,
but this time typed in Number
Four, Privet Drive, which
is where he grew up, instead
of his proper Hogwarts house.
Let me hit Enter now, and
now you see a value error.
But this isn't one that Python
generated for us, per se.
I raised this error.
And therefore, if I went in and wrote
more code in my get_student function,
I could also catch this error
with our usual try except syntax.
So all we have now is not just classes
in our toolkit, but even more powers
when it comes to exceptions, and
not just catching them ourselves
but raising them ourselves, too.
Any questions now on this use of
classes and init and now this ability
to raise exceptions when something goes
wrong inside of the initialization?
AUDIENCE: So what if the
user has a middle name--
name, middle name, and last name?
How would you fix that?
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
If you wanted the student to have a
first name, middle name, and last name,
we could do this in a
bunch of different ways.
The simplest, though, if-- let
me clear my screen here, and let
me just temporarily do this.
Let me propose that the init method take
in a first argument, a middle argument,
and a last argument.
And then what I think I would do down
here is ultimately have first = first,
and then I would do the same
thing for middle and last.
So middle and middle,
and then last and last.
And then what I would
have to do here is,
when I actually ask the
user for their name,
I might need to really go all out.
I might need to ask them
first for their first name
and store that in a variable called
first, and therefore pass in first.
I might similarly need to ask
them for their middle name
and store that in a variable and then
pass in a second argument, middle.
And then lastly, if you will,
let me go ahead and create
a third variable called last, get
the input for their last name,
and pass that in as well.
I could instead just use one input and
just ask them for their whole name.
So type in David Malan, Enter, or
David J. Malan-- all three of them,
and maybe I could use
Python's split function,
maybe a regular expression
to tease it apart.
That's probably going to
be messy because there's
going to be people who don't
have just two or three names.
They might have four or five.
So maybe sometimes it's better
to have multiple prompts.
But that's not a problem
because, with a class,
we have the expressiveness to
take in more arguments if we want.
We could even take a list if we wanted.
But I think we'd probably want to
have even more error checking then,
not just for name but for first,
and then maybe for middle, and then
maybe for last.
So it just is more and more
code, though there would be
ways to perhaps consolidate that, too.
Let me undo all of that and see if there
are other questions now on classes.
AUDIENCE: I assume
classes are something I
might do at the beginning of a project.
Can I just put them in a
different file and import them
into my project, or my
main code as needed?
DAVID J. MALAN: Absolutely.
A really good question.
You could imagine wanting
to use this student
class, not just in student.py but in
other files or other projects of yours.
And absolutely, you can create
your own library of classes
by putting the student class
in your own module or package,
per our discussion in the past
about libraries more generally.
And absolutely, you can do that.
And later today, what
we see is we've actually
been using classes-- you and I--
before, in third party libraries.
So you, too, can absolutely do the same.
How about one more question on classes?
AUDIENCE: Can you have
optional variables in classes?
And two, can you have your
own error names, like--
let's be egotistical and say
I want to raise Eric error?
DAVID J. MALAN: Short answer, yes.
These init functions are just
like Python functions more
generally, even though they're
special in that they're
going to get called
automatically by Python for you.
But if you wanted to
make house optional,
you could do something like this.
You could give it a default value
in the init function's signature
so to speak-- in that first
line of code on line two.
And that would allow me to
not have to pass in house.
In this case, I'm going to continue
to always pass in name and house,
but you could make things optional.
And yes, to your second question, if you
wanted to have your own error message,
like an Eric error, you could actually
create your own Eric error exception.
And we'll see, in a little
bit, that there's actually
a whole suite of exceptions that exist,
and you, too, can invent those as well.
Let me propose, though,
that we now introduce
one other aspect of this whereby we try
printing out what a student looks like.
At the moment, if I scroll
back down to my main function,
I'm still printing the student's
name and house very manually.
I'm going inside of the
object, doing student.name,
and I'm going inside of the object
again and getting student.house,
just to see where the student is from.
But wouldn't it be nice if I
could just print the student,
like I've been printing for weeks--
any, int, or float, or str,
or any other data type?
Well, let's see what happens if
I just try printing the student,
instead of manually going inside and
trying to create that sentence myself.
Well, in my terminal window-- let me
go ahead and run Python of student.py
again.
Let me type in Harry.
Let me type in Gryffindor.
And voila, Harry-- whoa, OK, main
student object at 0x102733e80.
Well, what is going on?
Well, if you were to
run the same code, you
might actually see something
different on your computer
in terms of that number.
But what you're really seeing is the
underlying representation, as a string,
of this specific object.
In particular, you're seeing where
in the computer's memory it is.
This number, 30x102733e80, refers
to, essentially, a specific location
in the computer's memory or RAM.
That's not really that interesting
for me or you or, generally speaking,
programmers, but it's just
the default way of describing,
via print, what this thing is.
But I can override this as well.
It turns out that there are
other special methods in Python
when it comes to classes--
not just underscore underscore,
init, underscore underscore,
but, continuing in that same
pattern, underscore underscore, str,
underscore underscore.
So this, too, is a special method that,
if you define it inside of your class,
Python will just automatically
call this function
for you any time some other function
wants to see your object as a string.
Print wants to see your
object as a string.
But by default, if you don't have
this method defined in your class,
it's going to print out that very
ugly esoteric incarnation thereof,
where it says main__.Student
object at 0x, dot, dot, dot.
Well, how can I then
define my own str function?
Well, here, back in VS Code,
let me propose that I go in
and define not just __ init, but let me
define a second function in this class
here, as follows--
def __ str __.
There are two.
Even though the font in VS Code is
putting the two underscore so close,
it just looks like a longer underscore.
There are indeed two there, on the
left and the right just like for init.
This one only takes one argument that,
by convention, is always called self
so that you have access to it.
And then, indented below
that after a colon,
I'm going to go ahead and create
a format string and return it.
So let me go ahead and return--
how about something generic
first like "a student."
So I'm not going to bother
even trying to figure out
what this student's name or house is.
I'm just going to always
return "a student."
Let me go back now to my earlier code,
which has print (student) on line 16.
Let me clear my terminal window and
rerun Python of student.py, Enter.
Type in Harry, type in Gryffindor.
Last time, I saw that
very cryptic output.
This time, I see, more
generically, "a student."
More readable but not very enlightening.
Which student is this?
Well, notice that the double underscore
str method takes in this self argument
by default. It's just the way the
Python authors designed this method.
It will always be passed a reference
to the current student object.
What do I mean by that?
When this line of code
on line 6 is called,
print, because it's hoping
it's going to get a string,
is going to trigger the underscore
underscore, str, underscore
underscore method to be called.
And Python, for you, automatically
is going to pass into that method
a reference to the object
that's trying to be
printed so that you, the programmer,
can do something like this.
Here's an f string with
double quotes as usual.
I'm going to use some curly
braces and say print out
self.name from self.house.
So there's nothing new
in what I've just done.
It's just an f string--
an f on the beginning,
two double quotes, a couple
of pairs of curly braces.
But because, automatically, this str
method gets passed self, so to speak,
a reference to the current object,
I can go inside of that object
and grab the name.
I can go inside that object
again and grab the house.
So now, when I go back
to my terminal window--
previously it just
printed out a student.
But now, if I run Python
of student.py, Enter--
type in Harry, type in Gryffindor,
and one more time hit Enter,
Harry is again from Gryffindor.
But if I run this yet again--
let's, for instance, do Draco
is from Slytherin, Enter.
Draco's from Slytherin.
Now it's customized to the specific
object that we're trying to print.
Questions on this function here--
this Dunder str method.
AUDIENCE: Is there anything else
that the underscore underscore,
str method can do?
The other question is, what's the
difference between str and repr.
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
So there are many other methods
that come with Python classes
that start with underscore underscore.
We're just scratching the
surface, and we'll pretty much
focus primarily on these.
But yes, there are
many others, and we'll
see at least one other
in just a little bit.
Among the others is one
called repr, which is
a representation of the Python object.
Generally speaking, the
underscore underscore, repr,
underscore underscore method
is meant for developers' eyes.
It typically has more information
than "Harry from Gryffindor."
It would also say what type of
object it is, like a student, capital
S, whereas underscore underscore, str,
underscore underscore is generally
meant for users--
the users of the program, and it's
meant to be even more user-friendly.
But both of those can be
overridden as you see fit.
Well, let me propose now that we pick
up where we've left off on student
and just add even more functionality,
but not just these special methods
like double underscore init
and double underscore str.
Let's create our own methods
because therein lies the real power
and flexibility of classes if
you and I as the programmers
can invent new functionality
that's specific to students.
For instance, students at
Hogwarts, over the time in school,
learn how to cast a
certain type of spell.
So when they say, Expecto
Patronum, something
comes out of their wand
that typically resembles
an animal or something like that.
It's a special spell that they
have to practice and practice.
So let's see if we can't store, not
just the student's name and their house,
but also their "patronus,"
what, actually, they
conjure when using this spell.
Well, let me go ahead and
clear my terminal window.
And in the top of my code here, in the
init method of Student, let me go ahead
and start expecting a third argument,
in addition to self, which automatically
gets passed in, called patronus.
And I'm not going to worry,
for now, on validating
the patronus from an official list
of valid patronuses, or patroni.
I'm instead going to go
ahead and just blindly assign
it to self.patronus
= patronus, and we're
going to let the user type
whatever they want for now.
But I could certainly
add more error checking
if I wanted to limit the patronus
to a specific list of them here.
Let me go ahead now and prompt
the user for this patronus,
as by-- in my get_student
function-- defining a variable
called patronus or anything
else, prompting the user
for input for their patronus.
And now I'm going to go ahead and
pass in that third variable here.
So again, similar in spirit to just
adding more and more attributes
to the class, I'm going
to pass in all three
of these values instead of just two.
I'm not going to do anything
interesting with that value yet.
But just to make sure I haven't made
things worse by breaking my code,
let me run Python of student.py.
I'll type in Harry.
I'll type in Gryffindor.
And it turns out his
patronus was a stag, .
And hit Enter I haven't seen
what his patronus is in my output
because I didn't change
my str method yet.
But at least I don't
have any syntax errors.
So at least I've not
made anything worse.
But suppose, now, I want to
have functionality, not just
for initializing a student
and printing out a student.
If my class is really meant
to be a student, what I can do
is not just remember information
about data about students.
What's powerful about classes,
unlike dictionaries alone,
is that classes can have, not just
variables or instance variables--
those attributes we keep creating.
They can also have
functions built in, a.k.a.
methods.
When a function is inside of a
class, it's called a "method,"
but it's still just a function.
At this point, we've seen two
functions already-- two methods--
called a double underscore
init and double underscore str,
but those are special methods
in that they just work.
If you define them, Python calls
them automatically for you.
But what if you wanted to create
more functionality for a student
so that your class really represents
this real world, or maybe "fantasy"
world notion of a student, where
students not only have names and houses
and patronuses; they
also have functionality.
They have actions they can perform like
casting a charm, a spell, magically.
Could we implement, therefore,
a function called charm, that
actually uses their magical knowledge?
Well, let's go ahead and define
our very own function as follows.
Let me clear my terminal window,
scroll back up to my student class.
And instead of creating yet
another function that's special,
with double underscores, I'm going
to invent my own function, or method,
inside of this class.
I want to give Harry and Hermione
and all of the other students
the ability to cast charms, so I'm
going to define a function that I
can completely, on my own, call charm.
I could call this
function anything I want.
But because it's a
method inside of a class,
the convention is that it's always going
to take at least one argument, called
self, by convention so that you
have access to the current object,
even if you don't plan
to use it, per se.
All right, let me go ahead and propose
that we implement charm in such a way
that the method returns an emoji
that's appropriate for each student's
patronus.
How to implement this-- well,
inside of the charm method,
let's go ahead and
match on self.patronus,
which is the instance variable
containing a string that
represents each student's patronus.
And in the case that it matches a stag,
for instance, for Harry, let's go ahead
and return maybe the closest emoji--
this horse here.
How about in the case of an otter?
Well, in that case, let's go ahead and
return, oh, maybe the closest match
to the otter, which
might be this emoji here.
And let's see, in the case of a--
for Ron, rather than Hermione--
a Jack Russell terrier,
let's go ahead and return--
don't have as many options here.
Why don't we go ahead and return the
cutest available dog in that case.
And in the case of no
patronus recognized,
as might cover someone
like Draco, let's go ahead
and use a default case using
the underscore as in the past,
and let's go ahead and return
for this-- oh, what should happen
if someone doesn't have a patronus?
Why don't we just see
a magical wand that
seems to fizzle out, as in this case?
All right, well, now, rather
than just print the student,
let's go about printing
their actual patronus.
So I'm going to go down
to my main function here.
I'm going to still get a student,
using the get_student function.
But rather than print student, let's go
ahead and declare "Expecto Patronum!"
printing out just that as pure text.
And now let's go ahead and print
out, not the student but, rather,
the return value of
their own charm method.
So let me go back down to my terminal
window and run Python of student.py
and Enter.
Name-- let's start with Harry.
He lives in Gryffindor.
Patronus is a stag.
And let's see--
Expecto Patronum!
And of course, we'd see the stag emoji.
What about someone like Draco,
who, at least in the books,
doesn't have a known patronus?
Well, let's go ahead and
clear my terminal window,
rerun Python of student.py, and this
time, let's type in Draco for name,
Slytherin for house,
and Patronus is unknown.
So I'm just going to
go ahead and hit Enter.
And now, Expecto Patronum!
And it just of sizzles instead.
Well, let me propose, now, that
we remove this patronus code just
to simplify our world and
focus on some of the other core
capabilities of classes.
So at the risk of
disappointing, I'm going
to get rid of all of these
beautiful emoji and charms,
and I'm going to go ahead and stop
asking the user now for their patronus.
And I'm going to stop
passing it into init here.
And I'm going to stop doing this here.
And I'm going to instead just go ahead
and restore our use of print student
here, and I'm going to go ahead
and get rid of patronus down here.
So just essentially undo all of
the fun charms we just created.
So we're now back at the point in the
story where we have a student class,
with only two methods--
init and str.
The first of those
takes, of course, self
as the first argument as it always will,
plus two more now-- name and house,
no more patronus.
We're validating name up here.
We're validating house down here.
And then we're assigning
name and house, respectively,
to two instance variables
called name and house also.
But we use self to get
access to the current object,
to store those values therein.
We then still have our str method
here, which takes one argument--
by default, self, and that's it.
And that function is going to
be called automatically any time
you want to convert a
student object to a string,
just like print might want to do here.
So let me go ahead and just make
sure I haven't broken anything.
Let me run Python of student.py.
I'll type in Harry.
I'll type in Gryffindor, Enter.
OK, we're back in business.
Gone are the charms and patronus,
but at least I'm back to a situation
where I have names and houses.
But it turns out, at the
moment, our use of classes
is not very robust, even though we
have this mechanism, very cleverly,
if I may, in our init
method of making sure
that we're validating name and house,
making sure that name is not blank,
and making sure that house is a valid
house among those four Hogwarts houses.
It turns out that
classes will still let me
get at those attributes, those
so-called instance variables,
using dot notation anyway.
Let me scroll down then and try
to do this a little adversarially.
Suppose that online 16 I go
ahead and call get_student,
which exists as before, and then I
store the return value in a student
variable-- again, on line 16.
That will ensure that get_student gets
called, which calls input and input.
And then it calls the
student constructor,
which invokes, automatically,
this init method.
So by way of how we've
laid out my code, we're
going to ensure that name is not
blank and house is definitely
one of those four values.
My error correction-- or
error checking is in place.
But if I'm a little adversarial,
I can still circumvent it.
Suppose that-- fine, going to require
me to type in Harry and Gryffindor?
I'm going to go ahead
and type in student.house
equals, quote, unquote,
"Number Four, Privet Drive,"
and you're not going
to be able to stop me.
Why?
Well, it turns out,
with classes and objects
thereof, you and I can still
access those instance variables
using this familiar dot notation.
That's how we began the story of
classes-- just setting these attributes
ourselves.
But you can also read
these attributes themselves
and change them later if you want.
And this will effectively circumvent the
if condition and the other if condition
in our init method because that
is only called when you first
create the student object.
There's nothing stopping
me, at the moment,
from just changing the
house or the name after.
So if I now clear my terminal
window and run Python of student.py,
I'll still type in Harry and
Gryffindor to meet my requirements
that the house be one of those four.
But when it's printed, notice,
I've still overridden it.
So it seems that, while classes do allow
us a little more control over the data
we're storing, it doesn't
necessarily prevent the user--
or rather the programmer-- be
it myself or maybe a colleague,
from still messing things up.
So here, too, in the spirit
of programming a little more
defensively, allow me to introduce
another feature of Python as well--
namely properties.
So a property is really
just an attribute
that has even more defense
mechanisms put into place,
a little more functionality implemented
by you to prevent programmers, like me
and you, from messing things
up like these attributes.
So again, a property is going to
be an attribute that you and I just
have more control over.
How?
We just write a little more code,
using some Python conventions.
And how we're going to do that is going
to use, in just a moment, a feature--
a keyword known as @property,
which is technically a function.
Property is a function in Python.
But we're about to see some new @ syntax
that allows you to decorate functions.
And this, too, is a term of art.
In the world of Python,
you can have decorators,
which are functions that modify
the behavior of other functions,
if you will, and we'll leave it at that
without going too much into the weeds.
And we'll see, by, example how
you can use these decorators,
specifically to define properties.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
And let me propose that I do this.
I'm going to go ahead and create--
how about a property
called house as follows.
Inside of my student class, I'm going
to go ahead-- and below my init method
and below my str method, I'm
going to go ahead and define
a function called house that takes, as
it always must, one argument at least,
called self.
And what I'm going to do
now is return self.house.
So I'm just going to
define a method called
house, whose sole purpose in life
is to return the value of house.
But I'm going to define one other
method, curiously also called house,
but that's going to take into,
as arguments, two values--
self as always and also
a value called house.
And I'm going to now do this.
I'm going to do self.house = house.
Now, what have I done?
Well, let me just temporarily
add some comments here.
In a moment, we're going to
start referring to this generally
as a getter.
And down here, I'm going to
refer to this as a setter.
And this is terminology frequently
see in the world of Java.
Some of you have
programmed in Java before.
But as the names imply,
a getter is a function
for a class that gets some attributes.
A setter is a function in some
class that sets some value.
And now, even though we're not done, and
there's a bit of a mistake in the code
I've already written, intuitively,
what we're going to do is this.
We're trying to prevent
programmers, myself included,
from circumventing my
error checking that I
put into place for name and house.
How can I do that?
Well, we don't have that many
building blocks in programming.
We have things like variables for data,
and we have functions for actions.
Well, why don't we do this?
Why don't we somehow require that,
in order to access an attribute,
you go through some function.
And let's require that, in
order to set some attribute,
you go through some function.
And conventionally, those functions are
called a getter function and a setter
function.
And why are we using functions or, in
this case, methods inside of a class?
Well, once you have functions,
those are just actions or verbs
that you and I can create ourselves.
We can put any error correction
I want in these functions
because it's code that's going
to get executed top to bottom.
So how can I now prevent the user from
setting the house to an invalid value?
Let me borrow some logic from before
rather than blindly do this-- just set
self.house equal to the house value
that's passed in-- let's add our error
checking there.
So if house is not in the following
list of Gryffindor or Hufflepuff
or Ravenclaw or
Slytherin, just as before,
let's go ahead and raise a value error,
just to signify that, uh-uh, something
has gone wrong.
I'll be more explicit.
I'll include a message like,
"invalid house," quote, unquote.
Otherwise, I'm going to proceed on,
now, line 21 to set self.house to house.
So I've just copied, if you will,
or retyped my error checking inside
of this so-called setter function.
Now, why have I done that?
Well, to be clear, whenever
the user or the programmer
writes code like this,
student.house equals, what's
about to happen magically
is Python will not just
let the programmer access student
house directly-- that attribute,
that instance variable, a.k.a.
self house.
It's instead going to
magically automatically call
this setter function for me.
How does Python know to do that?
Well, if it's see that, on the
left-hand side, there is self.house,
where house is the name of the getter or
setter, and then it sees an equal sign,
indicating assignment, that's just
enough of a visual clue to say,
wait a minute.
I'm not going to let you
access that attribute directly.
I'm going to use the setter instead.
Why?
Because the equal sign
means I'm trying to set.
I'm trying to assign a value from
right to left into that attribute.
So what Python's is
going to do automatically
is call this function for me.
And that's amazing because now I can
execute code-- an algorithm to check,
do I want to let the user--
the programmer set that
attribute to that value?
If not, I'm going to
raise a value error,
and you're just not going
to be able to do it.
If so fine.
I'll go ahead and set it for you.
But in order to do this, we
need a little more syntax.
And I'm going to get rid of my comment,
and I'm going to use that decorator.
I need to tell Python to
treat this method as a getter.
And then the syntax for the
setter is a little different.
You now say house.setter.
I wish one was getter
and the other was setter.
That's not the way they designed it.
When you want to define a getter, you
just say @property above the function.
And you name the function exactly
like you would like the property
to be called-- quote, unquote, "house."
Once you do that, you can
now use a new decorator
that's automatically created
for you called @house,
because I called it house.
And then you literally
say, @house.setter.
And this whole line, on
line 17, is a clue to Python
that here comes a function,
whose name is identical--
but notice that it takes two arguments--
both self, so you have access
to the contents of the object,
and house, which is just
going to be a str that comes from the
programmer from the human input return
value so that you can
set that value as well.
But there's one fix I
need to make now, here.
Everything else, I think, is still good.
However watch this.
I no longer need this error check here.
Why?
Because, if I scroll back
down to my code here,
I claimed a moment ago that code
like this, with student.house equals,
is going to automatically get
Python to call my setter for me.
Guess what?
Even up here, in my init method,
calling self.house equals
is also going to call my
setter method, which is amazing
because now I can keep all of my error
checking in one place in the setter,
and it will now get called either when
I create the object for the first time,
because of init, or
even if the programmer
tries to circumvent that init method
and change the value of this attribute,
my setter will also get called.
My setter will get called
any time I access .house.
But there's one fix I need to make.
Unfortunately, I have collided names.
Right now, if we go up here, on line
5, this is an instance variable.
It's a string inside of my self,
inside of the current student object,
called name.
And this is another instance
variable called house.
Unfortunately, if I have an instance
variable called name and house,
I cannot also have
functions called house.
They're going to collide.
You've got to decide.
Do you want the variable
to be called house?
Or do you want the function
Unfortunately, you can't
have both because now Python
is going to confuse one for the other.
So the conventional fix
for this is to do this--
to have the setter not store the
value that's passed in self.house,
but to use an almost identical name,
but to use a little indicator that
means you know doing this correctly.
You typically, by
convention, put an underscore
in front of the instance
variable's name.
And when you return it up here,
you similarly put an underscore.
So now, technically, my instance
variable is called _house,
but my property, which is a
fancier attribute, if you will,
is called house alone.
Huge amount of syntax, I know,
but it's a very powerful feature.
And again, this is why you can graduate
from dictionaries alone and have
so much more functionality
at your disposal.
Let me go ahead and clear my terminal
window and run Python of student.py,
Enter, name.
All right, let's go
ahead and type in Harry.
Let's go ahead and type in Gryffindor.
Crossing my fingers as always.
And now, look, "Invalid house."
This is a good thing.
Why?
Because, notice, in
my main function, I'm
still trying, maliciously, if
you will, to change Harry's house
to not be one of the four valid ones.
I'm trying to change it to his childhood
home of Number Four, Privet Drive.
But because Python knows that, wait
a minute, you're trying to assign--
that is, set a value--
and that value, a.k.a.
house, is now defined
as a property you're going to have to
go through the setter function instead
to even let you change that value.
And because I have
this raise ValueError.
If the house is not as
intended, you're not
going to be allowed to change
it to an invalid value.
So I'm protecting the data on the
way in, through the init method,
and I'm even defending the data
if you try to override it there.
So I think the only solution
for me, the programmer,
is, don't try to break my own code.
Let me remove that line because
it's just not going to work.
Let me run Python of student.py
and, again, type in Harry;
type in Gryffindor, Enter, and
Harry's indeed from Gryffindor.
If I did something incorrect,
like Harry from Number Four,
Privet Drive, Enter, we're again
going to see the value error
because my code just doesn't let
that value in via manual input now
or via that adversarial change.
All right, that was a lot.
But any question on properties?
AUDIENCE: Why we are
using getter then setter?
It's just for the purpose
so that we can find
that method, that function in our code.
DAVID J. MALAN: The reason that I'm
going through the trouble of defining
this getter or setter is because I want
to make sure that programmers cannot do
things like this.
If I'm going through the
trouble of validating
the attributes for
these student objects,
I don't want you to be able to go in
there and just change them at will.
I want to have some
control over that object
so that you can just trust that it's
going to be correct as designed.
So using a getter and
setter really just enables
Python to automatically detect when
you're trying to manually set a value.
The equal sign and the dot,
as I've highlighted here,
is enough of a clue to Python
to realize, wait a minute,
you're trying to set a value.
Let me see if this class
has a setter defined.
And if so, I'm going to
call that, and I'm not just
going to blindly assign the
value from right to left.
So it's just giving me more control.
Other questions on properties.
AUDIENCE: When we use getters,
we just have just one argument.
And if we use setters, it's
always going to be two arguments?
Is that normal?
DAVID J. MALAN: Correct.
It's always going to
be one argument-- self
for the getter, two arguments for
the setter-- self and something else.
And the intuition for that
is, if you're getting a value,
you don't need to pass anything else
in because you already know the object.
It's called student in this case.
So you're just going to get
the value of that property.
But if you want to set the
property to something else,
you've got to pass in that argument.
You've got to pass in the value
to which you want to set it.
So it's always 0 or 1.
However, you see it as 1 or 2 because,
again, any function inside of a class,
a.k.a.
a method, is going to be automatically
passed self so that you have access
to that current object in memory.
How about one other
question on properties?
AUDIENCE: Why didn't we use the
same underscore house init method?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
So even though I'm using the
underscore house here, in my setter,
and the underscore house
here, in my getter,
I deliberately did not use it up here.
The reason for that is that, by
using self.house and this equal sign,
that's the same pattern that
I want Python to recognize.
I want Python to
automatically call the setter,
even when I'm passing in the
house via the init method.
If I were to change this to do this,
that would circumvent the setter,
and now there's no error
checking in init whatsoever.
So it's such a fine line.
The only thing standing between us and
error checking or no error checking
is the presence or absence
of this underscore.
But that's typically the convention.
By not using the
underscore there, make sure
that even that assignment
goes through the setter
so that, honestly, I, don't have
to copy paste the same error
checking in two places.
I can put it just in the setter.
So it's a better design, and that's
why I manually retyped it at first,
but then I deleted it from init.
Well, allow me to propose that we
make one other change to this file.
Might as well go ahead and define
a property for name as well.
And let me go ahead and do this--
maybe above the house property
just to keep things in the same
order as I defined them earlier.
Let me give myself another property.
This one is going to be called name.
It's going to take one argument
called self, as always.
And this one, very similarly, is
just going to return self._name.
So I'm going to
anticipate that I'm going
to have to rename name also so that
I don't have that same collision as
before.
But now let me go ahead
and define another setter--
this one for name.
So the convention is @name.setter.
Why name?
Because the property I just
created is called name.
So the getter and setter work in
conjunction in this way, if you will.
Let me go down under that name
setter and define another function,
also called name.
But the key thing here is
that it's not identical.
It's not the exact same function name
and the exact same number of arguments.
The setter, again,
takes a second argument.
And I can call it
anything I want, but I'm
going to call it name because
that's what's being passed in.
And I'm going to put
my error checking here.
If not name, just like we used to do,
let's go ahead and raise a value error,
and let's put an explanatory message
like "Missing name," quote, unquote.
Otherwise, let's go ahead and
update self._name to equal name.
And I don't have to change
init except to get rid
of this duplicate error
checking now because, again,
if I use self.name equals here
and self.house equals here
with no underscore, both
of those assignments
are going to go through my
two setter functions now.
Before we run this, let
me go ahead and remove
this adversarial code, which we know
won't work because we're catching it.
Let me go back down to my terminal
window and run Python of student.py,
Enter.
Let's type in Harry.
Let's type in Gryffindor.
And that seems to work.
Let's try though, again,
to run Python of student.py
with Harry from Number
Four, Privet Drive.
This will not work.
A value error with invalid
house, because that's not
one of the four Hogwarts houses.
And now, for good measure,
let's run it one more time.
And let's not even give it a name.
Let's just hit Enter when prompted.
I can type anything for the house.
I'll go ahead and still
give it Gryffindor, Enter.
And now we get another value error,
but this one is for missing name.
So we seem, now, to have all the
more of a defense mechanism in place
to ensure that name is as we expect.
It's got to have some
value that's not blank.
And house is as we expect.
It's got to have one
of those four values.
But at the risk of
bursting everyone's bubble
and making you wonder, why did
we just go through all of that,
unfortunately Python really focuses
on conventions, not hard constraints.
And by that, I mean this.
If I go back into my main function
after I've gotten a student on line 30
and I try to adversarially do something
like this-- student.house equals
"Number Four, Privet
Drive," we know this
won't work because my setter for
house is going to catch this.
Watch again.
Python of student.py.
Let's type in Harry.
Let's type in Gryffindor,
which will at least pass
our check that's induced by init.
But line 31 is going to trigger
the same setter to be called,
and we're going to raise a value
error saying "Invalid house."
Unfortunately, and if
some of you are already
thinking a little adversarially,
tragically, look what you can do.
You can change .house to be ._house.
Why?
Well, the instance variable
is now called _house.
The property is called
house, no underscore.
But the underlying attribute implemented
as an instance variable is still called
_house.
And tragically, Python of student.py.
Let's type in Harry.
Let's type in Gryffindor,
which is correct.
But watch what happens now.
Oh, my God.
We slip through.
So what was the point of
all of this emphasis from me
on doing things the "right way," the
Python quick way by having this getter
and setter?
Well, unlike languages
like Java, that just
prevent you from doing
things like this, Python
itself allows you to specify that
certain instance variables can
be public and accessible to
anyone's code, or protected,
or private, which means that no one else
should be able to change these values.
In the world of Python,
it's just the honor system.
It's not baked into the
language itself that there's
a notion of visibility, public or
private or even somewhere in between
protected.
Instead, you're on the honor system.
And the convention
generally is, if an instance
variable starts with an
underscore, please don't touch it.
Just don't.
That's on you if you touch
that variable and break things.
The underscore is meant
to signify a convention
that this is meant to be
"private," but it really just
means, please don't touch this.
Sometimes, if there's two
underscores, which you can use,
too, that's an even greater
effort by programmers to say,
really don't touch this.
But technically speaking, there's
nothing stopping you or me
from circumventing all of these
mechanisms, these properties,
these getters and setters.
We're ultimately just
on the honor system
not to do so when we see instance
variables prefixed with one,
or perhaps even two underscores.
All right, so this is
a lot all at once--
this Introduction to
object-oriented programming.
But it might come as quite a
surprise that, even though we
might have identified OOP
by name in weeks past,
we've all been using classes and
objects for weeks now in this class.
In fact, if you think back on one of the
very first things we did in this class,
we used integers and just
got integers from the user.
But if you haven't already--
if you go and dig into the
documentation for integers,
which, again, lives
at this URL here, you
would actually find that int itself
is and has been for weeks a class.
And in fact, this is the signature
of the constructor call for an int,
whereby you pass in x, like a number,
quote, unquote, "50" or, quote,
unquote, something else-- you
pass in optionally the base--
10 for decimal, 2 for
binary or anything else.
And that int function will actually
return to you, all this time,
an object of type int.
That is to say int is a class.
It is a template, a blueprint
for creating integers in memory.
And any time you and I have converted
a string, for, instance to an int,
you and I have been creating an
object of type int that was calling,
apparently, the underscore underscore,
init, underscore underscore method,
that someone else--
the authors of Python--
wrote to give us back
that proper integer.
Besides that, if you can believe
it, strs, strings in Python
have been classes since the
first week of this class as well.
If you look up the
documentation for a str,
which lives at a similar URL there, you
will find that, when you instantiate--
that is, create a str--
it takes, optionally, a
parameter called object here,
the default value of which
is just, quote, unquote,
which allows you to create, in effect,
an empty string, a blank string,
if you will.
But any time you and I have created
strs or even used explicitly
the str function, you are getting
back an object of type str.
Any time you and I have forced a string
to lowercase per the documentation,
using syntax like this, you and I
have been taking an object of type str
and forcing it all to lowercase
by calling a method called lower,
a method that the authors of
Python built into the str class,
but it's been there from the get-go,
so this notion of methods is not
even new today.
You wouldn't have been
doing it for this long.
If you've ever called strip to remove
the leading and the trailing whitespace
from a string in Python, you are calling
another method that came with Python--
written by the authors of Python.
And even though we didn't
call it a class at the time,
a str, all this time, has been a class.
And instances of strings
are, themselves, objects.
And those objects come
therefore with these functions
built in-- a.k.a. methods that
allow us to do things like force
to lowercase and strip whitespace
from the beginning and end.
Let's do another.
list-- any time you've created a
list, either syntactically with square
brackets or literally with L-I-S-T,
open parentheses, closed parentheses,
which is also possible, you
have been using a class.
If you go to the documentation
for list, at this similar URL
here, or more specifically, the
tutorial on lists here in Python,
you will see that a
list is and has been,
since the early weeks of
this class, a class itself.
And that list class takes, as
part of its initialization,
an optional iterable, something that
can be iterated over-- like 1, 2, 3,
or some list of values,
and you can then get back
a list containing those
same iterable values.
If you've ever appended something
to a list in this class,
as I have myself in
the past, you've been
using a method called append that comes
with the list class that, per the x
here, takes an argument that
allows you to append something
to the current list, a.k.a.
Self in the context of that method.
We can do this all day long.
If you've used a dictionary
or a dict in Python--
I've actually, all this time,
been calling them dict objects,
and that's for a reason.
dict itself is a class
in Python, if you pull up
its official documentation here.
And you'll see that it is defined,
indeed, as itself a class.
And that class comes
with methods as well.
And so any time we've
manipulated dictionaries,
we've been underneath the hood,
using all of those same methods.
And in fact, we can see this
if we're really curious.
Let me go back over here to VS Code.
And let me go ahead and create a
new file that, very simply, does
something play around with data types.
And let me go ahead and create
a new file, for instance,
called, say, type.py, just so that I
can poke around inside of some values.
And in type.py, I'm just
going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to print out whatever
the type is of, say, the number 50.
And This is a function you've not
necessarily seen me use already,
and it's not one you would
frequently use in your own code.
There are other ways to
detect, if you need to,
what the type is of a variable.
But in this case, type of 50 is just
going to tell me and then print out
what the data type is of that value.
Now, hopefully, all of us
could guess that 50 is indeed
going to be an integer--
that is, an int, but we
can see it in this way.
And this, too, is what's powerful
about knowing a bit of programming.
If you want to know the
answer to a question,
just try it out, like I am here.
So let me go ahead and run
Python of type.py, Enter.
And there it is.
When you print out the type of the
number 50, you'll see on the screen,
in this cryptic syntax, class 'int.'
This is not something that you
probably want to show to the user.
But if you yourself just want to
poke around and see what's going on
or maybe use that
information somehow, it's
certainly at your disposal to
use this type function for that.
Let's change it around a little bit.
Instead of passing as the
argument to type 50, as an int,
let's type something also
familiar, like "hello, world,"
in double or single quotes.
Let me go back to my terminal
window, clear the screen,
and run Python of type.py again.
And now, voila, there it is.
All this time, a str is also a class.
We can do this a few more times, For.
Instance.
Let's go ahead and change "hello,
world" to just an empty list--
open square bracket,
closed square bracket.
And this is starting to
look a little cryptic,
but, again, notice what I'm doing.
In square brackets is an empty list.
We've done that before.
That is the sole argument
to this new type function.
And that's just being
passed to the print function
so that the return value of
type is the argument to print.
So if I now run this code,
Python of type.py, there it is.
A list is a class, too.
You might recall that I said that
you can also create an empty list
by literally doing list ().
This is a bit of an
inconsistency, as we can now
identify that int and str and now list--
they're technically all lowercase.
And I went to great lengths of creating
my student class to have that capital
S. That's a convention.
Because int and stir and list
and others come with Python,
they decided to make their built-in data
types-- even though they're classes--
all lowercase.
But the convention, the recommendation
in the Python community when creating
your classes is to capitalize
the first letter, as I did,
in something like Student, capital S.
But list () is identical to really just
two empty square brackets.
If I clear my screen and run type.py
again, you see the exact same thing.
The class is called list.
Let's do one more.
Let me change the list to be not
square brackets but curly braces.
We've done this before.
Any time I've done two curly braces with
nothing in between, this, of course,
is an empty dictionary, or
a dict object in Python.
Well, we can see that now.
Let me clear my screen, run
Python of type.py, Enter,
and there it is-- class 'dict."
It's been there this whole time.
We just didn't call it
a class until today.
I can similarly do this one explicitly.
Instead of two curly braces, let's
write out dict with two parentheses.
Now we have a lot of parentheses
again, like with list.
But this is just making even more
clear that the type of a dict object
is indeed the class, dict, itself.
So this is to say that, as new as
a lot of today's idea and syntax,
might be you've actually been using
it, perhaps unbeknownst to you,
for weeks now.
We now just have
terminology to describe what
it is we've been doing all this time.
And you now have the
expressiveness, with some practice,
to create your own classes, inside of
which are your own instance variables,
perhaps wrapped with those properties
and your own instance methods.
But it turns out there's other
types of methods in the world.
Thus far, I've been
deliberate in calling
all of our variables instance variables
and all of our methods instance
methods.
It turns out there's other types
of variables and methods out there,
and one of those is
called class methods.
It turns out that sometimes it's
not really necessary or sensible
to associate a function
with objects of a class,
but rather with the class itself.
An instance, or an object of a class,
is a very specific incarnation thereof.
Again, on that neighborhood that has
a lot of identical looking buildings,
but they're all a little bit different
because of different paint and such,
sometimes you might have
functionality related
to each of those houses that
isn't distinct or unique for any
of the houses.
It's functionality that's
going to be exactly the same no
matter the house in question.
Same in the world of
object-oriented programming.
Sometimes you want some
functionality, some action
to be associated with the class itself,
no matter what the specific object's
own values or instance variables are.
And for that, we have a
keyword called @classmethod.
This is another
decorator-- really, another
function-- that you can use to
specify that this method is not,
by default, implicitly
an instance method that
has access to self, the object itself.
This is a class method that's
not going to have access to self,
but it does know what class it's inside.
So what do I mean by this?
Well, let me go back to VS Code here.
And let me propose that we create
a new file this time implementing
the notion of a-- the sorting hat,
from the world of Harry Potter as well,
to stay on theme.
I'm going to go ahead
and run code of hat.py.
And in hat.py, let's implement
the notion of the sorting hat.
If unfamiliar in the
books and in the films
there is literally a
pointy hat that, when
a student put it's on their head,
that sorting hat, so to speak,
decides what house the
student is in-- whether it's
Gryffindor or something else.
So let's implement, in code, this
notion of a sorting hat such that,
when we pass to the sorting hat the
name of a student, like, quote, unquote,
"Harry" this sorting
hat, implemented in code,
will tell us what house
that student should be in.
Well, let's go ahead and do this.
In hat.py, first, let's go ahead
and define a class called hat,
and then let's get back
to implementing it itself.
And I find this to be a helpful
technique, not just with teaching
but when writing code.
I know I want a hat class.
I don't necessarily know
what I want it to do yet,
so I'm going to create this
placeholder, dot, dot, dot,
so I'll come back to that.
Let's now try to use this
class as though it existed.
And from there, I perhaps
can realize exactly what
functionality that class needs
to have to support my use case.
Let me go ahead and create a
variable called hat in all lowercase
and instantiate a hat object.
So no matter what the hat
class ends up looking like,
this is the common
syntax for instantiating
an object of a certain class.
In the past, we saw
student, all lowercase,
equals capital Student, open
parenthesis, close parentheses,
and then eventually, we added
in things like name and house.
For now, let's assume that the hat
is much simpler than a student,
and it only has sorting capabilities.
So I'm not going to even pass
any arguments there, too.
Let me assume that the sorting hat has
one function-- one method inside of it
called, sort.
And so if I do hat.sort ("Harry"), let's
propose that that prints out what house
that student should be in.
So that's it.
I'm going to encapsulate--
that is tuck away
inside of a hat class--
all of this requisite functionality, and
I'm going to print out onto the screen
what hat--
what house Harry belongs in.
Now I think I need to get into the weeds
of actually initializing this class.
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
If I don't care to parameterize hat--
I just want to, for
instance sort values,
let's go ahead and define
this function, sort, first.
So let's define sort, as
taking a first argument, self,
which is always going to be the case
when defining an instance method as
before.
But the sort method clearly takes one
argument from the programmer, me--
namely the student's name.
And again, we've seen
this dichotomy before.
Even though I'm trying to pass in one
argument, when I define the method,
it's got to take that many
arguments, plus one more--
self which is always going to be
automatically passed in by Python
first.
What do I want to do?
Well, let's go ahead and
do something like this.
Print, this name-- how
about "is in," "some house."
I'm going to, again, use
some placeholder code
for myself because I'm not quite sure
how to finish implementing this sorting
hat.
But I think that's enough to just
test where my code is at now.
Let me go ahead and run Python
of hat.py and hit Enter.
And it looks like, indeed,
Harry is in some house.
We're not done yet because it's
clearly not doing anything interesting,
but it at least is running
correctly with no errors.
Well, let's go ahead
now and decide where--
what house Harry should actually be
in by introducing a bit of randomness
and choosing a house randomly.
While I can do this in a few ways, Let.
Me go ahead and do this.
I need to have a list
of houses somewhere.
So where can I put that?
I could solve this
problem in different ways.
Let me propose that I do this.
Let me define a method called
init, as I've done before,
that takes in self,
but no other arguments.
And whenever the sorting hat
is instantiated, let's do this.
Let's create a houses instance variable,
plural, that equals this list--
Gryffindor, Hufflepuff,
Ravenclaw, Slytherin,
so the exact same list
that we've used before,
and I'm storing it in an instance
variable inside of this class.
I'm not taking any arguments
beyond self to init,
but I just need this list of
values somewhere, for instance.
So what can I do here?
Well, let me go ahead and replace
some house with the actual house.
Well, what could I do here?
Well, I want to put a house there.
Well, let's go ahead and
create a variable called house.
And if you think back to our discussion
of libraries, in the random module,
there is a function called choice
that, if you pass in a list of choices,
like self.houses, that will pick
a random house out of those four.
And then on line 7, I can pass it in.
If I want to tighten this up, let me
just go ahead and highlight that code,
get rid of the variable.
It's technically unnecessary.
And because the line of
code is still pretty short,
I'm OK with just putting
it all in one line.
But I could certainly use the
variable like I did a moment ago.
So what have I done?
In my init function, I have defined
a initialization of the object
that stores in self.houses
the list of four houses.
And then, in sort, I'm
accessing that same list,
but I'm randomly choosing
the set of houses there.
Now, why have I done it in this way?
This, too, is general convention.
Any time you have a list
of things that-- who knows?
Maybe will change over time.
Places like Harvard have constructed
new houses over the years,
so you might have to change
the list of available houses.
It didn't happen in seven books
or eight films of Harry Potter.
But you could imagine
maybe Hogwarts eventually
has a fifth house, so there's generally
some value in putting list of constants
toward the top of your file, toward
the top of the class so it's just
obvious what the list of values is.
You don't want to necessarily
tuck it away in some function,
like sort, especially if you
might want to use that function--
sorry, especially if you want to use
that list in multiple functions, not
just sort.
But if I kept adding to
this class, you might
want to use that same list of
houses in multiple functions.
So let's keep it in the object
itself by storing it in self.houses.
All right, well, we're about to change
the course of history here perhaps.
Let me do Python of hat.py, and I
think we're about to assign Harry
to one of those four houses randomly.
Huh, NameError.
Name 'random' is not defined.
Well, wait a minute,
where did I go wrong here?
Thinking back to our class on libraries,
why did my code break and not tell me
where Harry is to be?
AUDIENCE: You did not
import the random library.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
If the random library or module
is something I want to use,
I need to tell Python that
at the top of my file.
So let me go up here
and do import random.
And then, below that, let me go
ahead and clear my terminal window
and try again.
Python of hat.py, crossing my fingers,
seeing where Harry is going to end up.
And, OK, Harry as of now is
officially in Hufflepuff,
despite everything you've read or seen.
Well, let's run this again.
Let me clear my window and run Python
of hat.py, and now he's in Ravenclaw.
That's consistent with using random.
Let's clear that and run it again.
He's still in Ravenclaw,
but that could happen,
even though there's four choices.
Let's do it again.
Hufflepuff-- back in Hufflepuff.
We can't seem to get the right answer.
Now he's in Gryffindor, albeit randomly.
So we seem to have a program that,
based on these limited tests,
seems to be assigning
Harry to a house randomly.
Now I'm somewhat lazily just
letting sort print out this value.
I could do something else, like return
a string, and then let me, on line 13,
do the printing for me.
But for now, I think we have an
example of a class called hat that,
nonetheless, applies some of our
lessons learned thus far today,
where I've created a class--
because a sorting hat is, frankly--
well, I was about to say
real world entity, but really
a fantasy world entity.
And indeed, that's a, perhaps, common
heuristic or mental model to have.
When should you use a class to
represent something in your code?
Very often, when you're trying to
represent some real world entity
or fantasy world entity, like a student,
which is something in the real world,
like a sorting hat,
which, OK, doesn't exist,
but hat's certainly do, so quite
reasonable to have a class for hat.
And that's not always the case that
classes represent real world entities.
But we've seen thus far that int
and stir and list and dict-- these
are all structures that you
might have in the real world.
We have integers and strings
of text and other things.
So it rather makes sense to represent
even those things, more technically,
using a class as well.
You could use just a dictionary
to represent a student or a hat.
But again, with classes come all
this and even more functionality.
But I honestly am not using classes
in, really, the "right way" here.
Why?
Well, in the world of Harry
Potter there really is only,
to my knowledge, one sorting hat.
And yet, here I have gone and
implemented a class called hat.
And again, a class is like
a blueprint, a template,
a mold that allows you to create
one or more objects thereof.
Now, most of my programs Thus
far have been pretty simple,
and I've just created one student.
But certainly, if I spent
more time and wrote more code,
you could imagine
writing one program that
has a list of students--
many more students
than just the one we keep demonstrating.
Yet it would be a little weird--
it's a little inconsistent
with the real or the fantasy
world of Harry Potter to instantiate
one, two, three or more sorting hats.
There really is just one.
Really one singleton,
if you will, which is
a term of art in a lot of
contexts of programming.
So let me propose that we actually
improve the design of the sorting hat
so that we don't have to instantiate
a sorting hat because right now this
is kind of allowing me to do something
like hat 1 = hat, hat 2 = hat, hat 3 =,
and so forth.
I don't really need that capability.
I really just need to represent
the sorting hat with a class,
but I don't really
need to instantiate it.
Why?
Because it already exists.
I need just one.
So it turns out, in
Python, that, up until now,
we've been using, as I keep
calling them, instance methods--
writing functions inside of classes that
are automatically passed a reference
to self, the current object.
But sometimes you just don't need that.
Sometimes it suffices to
just know what the class is
and assume that there might not
even be any objects of that class.
So in this sense, you can use a
class really as a container for data
and/or functionality that is just
somehow conceptually related--
things related to a sorting hat.
And there's this other decorator
or function called @classmethod
that allows us to do just this.
So let me go back to my code here.
And let me propose that, if I'm not
going to instantiate multiple houses,
I don't really need this init
method because that's really
meant to initialize specific objects
from that blueprint, that template,
that mold.
So let me get rid of this.
But if I get rid of this, I
no longer have access to self.
But that's OK because it turns out,
in addition to their existing class
methods, there are also what
we might call class variables.
And class variables exist
within the class itself.
And there's just one
copy of that variable
for all of the objects thereof.
They all share, if you will, the
same variable-- be it an int or str
or, in this case, a list.
So what I've done here is define, inside
of my hat class, in a class variable
called houses--
I don't say self because
self is no longer relevant.
Self refers to specific objects.
I want a variable inside
of this class, a.k.a.
A class variable that equals that list.
Because it's inside of
this hat, now, class,
I can use that list in
any of my functions.
I've only got one now, called sort.
But if I had more, it would be
accessible to all of those methods
as well.
And with sort, it also
doesn't really make sense
to sort within a specific
sorting hat because, again, I
only want there to be one.
So I can actually specify that this is
class method by saying @classmethod.
And I don't pass in self anymore.
I actually, by convention, pass in
a reference to the class itself.
It's typically written as cls.
Why?
Well, if you wrote C-L-A-S-S, that
would actually conflict with the keyword
"class" that we keep using up here.
So the world realized that, oops, we
can't reuse that same phrase here.
So let's just call this class.
This is useful in some
contexts including this one.
Why?
Well, notice what I can now do.
I can now change self to be just class.
Why?
Because houses now-- not an instance
variable, accessible via self.houses.
It is now a class variable,
accessible via class.houses,
or technically cls.houses in this case.
But now the final flourish is this.
Now, I don't have to instantiate any hat
objects as I used to on here, line 13.
I can just use functionality
that comes with this class.
So I'm going to delete
that line altogether.
I'm going to capitalize the hat on
this new line 13 and just say hat.sort,
("Harry").
So what have I done?
I've not bothered instantiating
an object of type, hat.
I am just accessing a class
method inside of the hat class
that-- you know what?
Is just going to work.
This is how class methods work.
You use the name of the class, capital
letter and all, dot method name,
passing in any arguments you want.
Python is going to automatically
pass in some variable via which
you can refer to that
class in that function
that you've implemented
inside of that class
so that I can do something like this.
It's not that I want a variable called
houses locally in this function,
I want the variable called houses that's
associated with this current class
so I can still access this same
list that I defined on line 6.
And now, if I go back down here to
my terminal and run Python of hat.py,
Enter, Harry is still
in Hufflepuff once more.
Harry is still in Hufflepuff once more.
Harry is back in Gryffindor,
at least randomly.
Questions, now, on these class
variables or these class methods,
which are in contrast with instance
variables and instance methods.
And the one thing, at least,
that's a little strange
here is that, even though there's
a decorator called @classmethod,
there is not one called @instancemethod.
A method is just automatically a
so-called "instant method" when
you define it without any decorator.
AUDIENCE: Can you have a
class inside another class?
DAVID J. MALAN: You can.
You can define one
class inside of another.
Generally speaking, this
isn't done, but there
are cases where it can
be helpful, especially
for larger, more sophisticated programs.
So yes, it is possible.
Other questions.
AUDIENCE: The question
was about the self.houses.
When we remove it and we pass
data, variable is created itself,
s why we remove the self?
DAVID J. MALAN: So in
the previous examples--
both of the hat demonstration
and also all of the student
demonstrations-- we
were creating a student
object by calling Student, capital S,
open parenthesis, close parenthesis,
with, eventually, name
and a house passed in.
And then we were using the
double underscore init method
to initialize the self.name and
the self.house instance variables
therein to those respective values.
In this latest version
of the sorting hat,
I haven't bothered with self anywhere,
only because, conceptually, I
don't need or want there to
be multiple hats in the world.
I'm just using the class as a container
to bundle up this list of houses,
this sorting functionality.
Maybe eventually all add
more functionality to it.
But that's it.
And so sometimes you can use
object-oriented programming
in this somewhat different way when
you want there to be functionality
but it's not specific
to any one specific hat.
It's specific to the sorting hat itself.
How about one other question now, on
these class variables or methods-- just
another way of using object-oriented
programming but to solve
a somewhat different problem?
AUDIENCE: Well, what's the
difference between the class
hat and a function of hat?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
So why are we using a
class at all and not just
having a file called hat.py
with a variable called
houses and a function called sort?
Why are we adding this complexity?
In this particular case, we
don't necessarily need to.
I could absolutely go in here.
I could get rid of the class.
I could undo this indentation.
I could get rid of this decorator.
And I could get rid of hat dot.
And I could just do
this and additionally
let's say, let's get rid of class here.
Let's get rid of class here.
And now run Python of hat.py,
Enter, and it still works.
Put Harry in the wrong house,
but that's what we have--
what happens randomly.
That's fine, too.
What we're introducing today, by
way of object-oriented programming,
is just a different way
of modeling the world.
It's not really compelling
with an example like this,
frankly, that's relatively simple.
It's not very complex.
There's not much functionality.
Honestly, the version that we just typed
up-- these 10 lines-- this is fine.
This solves this problem.
But as our code gets longer, as we
start collaborating with other people,
as the problems we're trying to solve
with code get more sophisticated,
you're going to find that
your code gets messy quickly.
And you're going to find that you have a
huge number of functions, for instance,
in one file.
And some of them are related to each
other, but some of them are not.
Well, at that point, wouldn't
it be nice to just organize them
a little differently?
And in the world of Harry Potter,
let's have a class for student;
let's have a class for Professor;
let's have a class for the sorting hat;
let's have a class for something else.
And so once your world gets
much more complicated than some
of the demonstrations we do here
in class when we want to focus
on individual ideas, object-oriented
programming is just a way
of encapsulating related data--
that is, variables-- related
functionality-- that is, methods--
inside of things that have names.
These things are called classes.
So it's just another
way to solve problems.
And when we focused on libraries
a couple of weeks back,
that, too, was another
solution to the same problem.
You could define your own modules
or packages, put some of your data
and/or functionality in
there, and that's fine, too.
And sometimes which one
you should use overlaps.
If you're familiar with Venn
diagrams, the overlapping region
might mean that you could use a class;
you could use a module or a package;
you could just use a single local file.
Over time, you'll develop
an instinct and maybe even
a personal preference
for which tool to use.
All right, let me propose, now, that we
apply this same idea of a class method
to clean up one other thing as well.
Let me close that hat.py and reopen
student.py as we left it earlier,
and let me go ahead and
simplify it just a little bit.
I'm going to go ahead and
get rid of the properties,
not because there's
anything, wrong with them,
but just because I want us to
focus on some of the key ideas
when we began with this program.
So I'm going to go ahead
and keep main as well.
I'm not going to adversarially try
to change Henry's address there.
I'm going to instead go ahead,
though, and just print the student.
But this is the thing I
want to focus on here.
This, in our previous student
examples, was a missed opportunity
to clean up my code.
Well, what do I mean by that?
Well, up here at the
top of this file-- even
though I've simplified it, but
getting rid of the properties
and all of that error
checking-- because I
want to focus on the essence of this
class now-- just the student's name
and the house and the printing thereof.
This is, by nature of classes
in object-oriented programming,
theoretically, all of my
student-specific functionality.
That is to say, if I have functionality
and data related to a student, you,
the programmer, my
colleague, would assume
that it's all bundled
up, encapsulated, so
to speak, inside of the student class.
And yet, if you scroll
down further, what is this?
There's a function called get_student
that just exists elsewhere
in this file that prompts the user for
a name, prompts the user for a house,
creates the student
object, and then returns.
That's not wrong.
It works.
And we saw many, many
times it kept working.
But this is a little
weird because, if this
is a function that
helps you get a student,
helps you get the name of a student
and the house of a student, why isn't
that functionality in the class itself?
After all, as my code gets more and
more complicated and does more things,
I'm going to be looking
at the student class
for all student-related functionality.
I'm not going to be scrolling down,
expecting that, oh, maybe there's
some other student functionality
just randomly later in this file.
So it's not wrong.
But this is, again, evidence
of maybe bad design--
not so much with this small program.
But this is an example,
again, of code smell.
Something smells a little off here.
This is probably going
to get us in trouble
by separating related functionality.
So again it's a design principle,
not a correctness concern.
But class methods allow
us to address this, too.
Let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to delete get_student
all together, leaving
only main as my other function here.
And inside of my student
class, I'm going to do this.
I'm going to define a function,
even more simply called, get.
And by nature of how
class methods work, it's
going to take in the
name of the class itself
or a reference thereto as an argument.
And I'm going to move the functionality
from get_student into the student
class.
And I'm going to do this-- name equals
input, quote, unquote, name, house
equals input, quote, unquote, house.
And then what this
function is going to do
is return a new student object by
calling class, which, again, is just
an automatically passed-in
reference to the class
itself, passing in name and house.
And I will admit this syntax seems a
little strange that now I'm calling cls
and I'm passing in these arguments.
But let me do one final fix here.
Let me go to the top of
this function and more
explicitly say this is a class method.
This solves a potential chicken
and the egg problem, so to speak,
whereby one needs to come
before the other, potentially.
So what am I doing here?
Inside of my student class, I
now have a function called get.
It is, I shall claim, a class
method what does that mean.
It just means I can call this method
without instantiating a student
object first.
Therein lies the potential
chicken and the egg problem.
And if unfamiliar, that's an expression,
meaning, well, and did the world
have chickens first that laid
eggs, or was there an egg
that then yielded the chickens,
but how did the egg get there?
It's this weird, circular problem.
And that's what we're facing here.
It would be weird if you had to create
a student object in order to call get,
in order to get another student object.
That sounds messy.
Let's just get a student
via a class method
that, by definition, does not require
you to create a student object first.
Just like the hat, in its final
form, we use the hat class
to just say Hat, capital H, dot sort.
We didn't need to create a hat first.
We just used the class itself.
So what am I going to do here now?
Let me go down to main.
And instead of saying get_student,
notice what I can now do.
Student.get, and everything
else can stay the same.
All I've done now is I've
migrated all of my logic
from get_student, which was
this own standalone function,
but clearly related to students by name.
I've moved the same
code, really, to inside
of the student class in a more
simply named function called get.
But I could still call
it get_student if I want.
It just seems a little redundant to
call it get_student in a student class,
so I'm simplifying.
So I have a method called get,
but I'm calling it a class method
to avoid that chicken
and the egg problem.
I want to be able to call a get without
having a student object in my universe
already.
And the syntax for that is @classmethod.
The convention is to give this
method at least one argument,
by convention called cls for
class, which is just going
to be a reference to the class itself.
Lines 11 and 12 are identical
to what they've always been.
And get_student-- the only
new syntax here is this,
but this, again, is one of the features
of object-oriented programming.
You can now instantiate a student object
by just using cls that's passed in.
I technically could
use Student, capital S,
but it turns out I'm doing what's
more conventional because this
will both solve and avoid problems down
the line with more complicated code.
This line here, on line 13, just means
create an object of the current class.
What class is that?
Well, whatever cls is.
Well, that, by definition of how it
all works, is going to be student.
And I want you to initialize it,
as always, with name and house.
So now, scrolling down, my code is this.
And this is just nice to read.
You perhaps have to acquire a taste for
this-- and I sound a little odd saying,
this is nice to read.
But indeed, student.get just
tells me what's going on.
I'm going to get a student.
I don't need a separate function written
by me called get_student in the file
itself.
The get functionality
is built into the class.
All my student-related
code now is together.
So let me go down to my terminal window
and run Python of student.py, Enter.
Let's type in Harry.
Let's type in Gryffindor.
And we're back to where we began.
But, but, but everything related to
students, now, is in this here class.
The only other thing in the file
is main and this conditional
that we always use to avoid accidentally
executing main when we're making
a module or a package or the like.
So again, a solution to a problem--
not a big one in the case of a
relatively small program, but one
that you will eventually
encounter as your programs
get longer and longer, with more
and more entities to represent.
Questions now on this
use of a class method.
MICHAEL: Does the class have to be
defined before the main function,
in terms of the order of the program?
DAVID J. MALAN: A really good question.
So when in doubt, let's try this.
So let's try to change the order.
Let's move main to the top,
which I've often encouraged.
So let's go ahead and,
above the class, do this.
And notice now that,
technically, line two
is mentioning student, which does
not exist until line 6 and below.
Let me go ahead and clear my terminal
and run Python of student.py.
So far, so good.
Harry-- Gryffindor, OK.
Indeed, Harry's from Gryffindor.
The reason, Michael, it
does not matter in this case
is because we're not actually
calling main until the very end.
And just as in the past, that means that
Python has a chance to read everything,
top to bottom, left to right.
So everything exists.
I would say, generally classes are
defined at the top of the file.
However, it would be even maybe
cleaner to move the Classes definition
to its own file and then
import it, so essentially
to make reusable code by putting
it into your own module or package
so that not just this
program but many others
can use that definition
of student as well.
Other questions now on classes,
class methods, or the like.
AUDIENCE: I wanted to ask, is there
a way to declare all the possible--
all the possible
attributes of the class?
Because it looks so inconsistent.
DAVID J. MALAN: Well,
so my takeaway there
is this is Python's approach
to these principles.
Different languages, like Java,
just take a different approach
but have very similar features.
The syntax just tends to vary.
And this is how the Python community
chose to implement this idea.
The right mental model, ultimately,
is that these instance variables,
instant methods belong to or
operate on specific objects--
a specific student, a specific hat.
Class variables and class methods
operate on the entire class
itself or, in turn, all
objects of that class, which
we've not seen a demonstration of,
but it's a higher level concept.
So it turns out, besides
these class methods,
which are distinct from those
instance methods, which, to be fair,
do not have their own decorator-- they
just are, by default, instance method,
there's yet other types of Methods
You can have in classes in Python.
They tend to be called static
methods, and they, too,
come with another decorator
called @static method, which
is a rabbit hole we won't go down.
But realize that there is
yet other functionality
that you can leverage within
object-oriented programming.
But what we thought we'd do is focus
really on some final core features
that you see not just in Python
but other languages as well.
And perhaps one of the most compelling
features of object-oriented programming
that we haven't yet used explicitly--
though it turns out we've seen
implicitly over the past weeks--
is this notion of inheritance.
It turns out, via
object-oriented programming,
there's actually an opportunity
to design your classes
in a hierarchical fashion, whereby
you can have one class inherit from
or borrow attributes-- that is,
methods or variables from another class
if they all have those in common.
So what do I mean by this here?
Well, let me propose that we
implement, over in VS Code here,
a brand new file called wizard.py.
Let me go ahead and
run code of wizard.py.
And then let's start as before,
defining a class called student.
And let's go ahead and first define
the underscore underscore, init method,
which of course, is minimally going
to take an argument traditionally
called self.
And in this case, let's also have it
take as before a name and a house.
And then in this init
method, let's go ahead
and assign the instance
variables-- self.name = name,
and self.house = house.
Let's assume that there's
some other functionality
in this class as well-- dot, dot, dot.
But let's move on now to implementing
the notion of a professor
in the wizarding world as well.
So for this class,
let's call it Professor.
And a professor, let's
say, is also going
to have its own initialization method.
So __ init.
It's going to take self--
always as the first argument.
A professor also has a name.
So we'll pass that in second, too.
And even though some
professors are heads of houses,
let's assume that a professor
is really identified
by their name and their subject
area-- the class that they teach.
So we'll call this
third argument, subject.
Now, as before, let's go ahead
and assign self.name = name,
and let's assign
self.subject = subject here.
And as before, let's assume that there's
some more functionality associated
with professors as well.
Well, what do you notice already
here in my definitions of students
and professors?
Typically, we're a bit reluctant to
allow for any redundancy in our code.
And here, I feel like my init method
is taking a name for students;
my init method is also taking
a name for a professor;
and I have these identical lines
of code, like self.name = name.
And this is only going to get
exacerbated if I now go and add
some error checking.
So for instance, how
about if not name, we
should probably be in the
habit of raising something
like a value error in an explanatory
message, like "Missing name."
And you know what?
If a professor is missing
their name, I should probably
copy, paste that code down here.
And that's where red
flags should be going off,
whereby, as soon as you
start copy pasting code,
there's probably a better way so that
we can write the code once and perhaps
reuse it in some way.
And here, too, object-oriented
programming offers a solution.
It turns out that object-oriented
programming in Python
also supports inheritance, whereby
you can define multiple classes that
somehow relate to one another.
They don't need to exist
in parallel in this way.
There could actually be
some hierarchy between them.
So for instance, in
the wizarding world, we
could argue that both a student and a
professor are, at the end of the day,
Wizards.
So maybe what we should really
define is a third class,
for instance, called
wizard, that has any
of the common attributes for
students and professors alike.
And for now, we've kept
it relatively simple.
The only thing they have in
common is a name and a name,
in student and professor, respectively.
So why don't we minimally
factor that out first?
All right, so let me go ahead here.
And just to keep things organized,
at the top of my file, let's
define a third class called Wizard.
And a wizard will have its
own initialization method.
So def __init__(self), as always.
And a wizard, let's say
for now, is only going
to be initialized with
their name in this way.
And now, I'm going to go ahead and
do some of that error checking.
So if not name will raise a
value error in the wizard class.
Otherwise, we'll go ahead
and do self name equals name,
and, heck, dot, dot, dot, maybe
some other functionality as well.
But not a subject, which is specific
to professors, and not a house,
which I've claimed is
specific to students.
Now, I think we can
begin to maybe remove
some of the redundancies
in our other classes here.
So for instance, down
with student, why don't I
go ahead and remove this error
checking here and remove this error--
this assignment of self.name
= name because I'm already
doing that in Wizard.
And similarly, down here, in
Professor, why don't I do the same?
Let's get rid of the error checking.
Let's get rid of self.name = name
because, again, I'm doing that already
up there for Wizard as well.
But at the moment, even though
they're all in the same file,
I haven't told Python that a student is
a wizard and a professor is a wizard.
So I really need to
link these two together.
And the way you can prescribe
inheritance, whereby one class should
inherit from another,
or conversely, one class
should descend from
another-- we can do this.
I can say class Student.
But before the colon, I can
go in and say in parentheses,
a student inherits from, or is a
subclass of wizard, which, conversely,
is the superclass of the student class.
So this just means that, when
I define a student class,
go ahead and inherit all of the
characteristics of a wizard as well.
And I'm going to do the
same thing for Professor.
So (Wizard) after the
class name Professor,
and that's going to give me access
to some of that same functionality.
But because my student
class and my professor class
still have their same
init methods, those
are the methods that
are going to get called.
Whenever I create a student in code
or I create a professor in code,
I need to somehow
explicitly say that I also
want to use the functionality in
the Wizard class's init method.
And the way to do this
in Python is as follows.
Let me go into my init
method for Student,
and let me call super,
with no arguments, which
is a reference to the
superclass of this class.
So if this class is Student,
the superclass-- that is,
the parent class-- is Wizard.
So super() will have the effect
of accessing the superclass.
And then I'm going to go ahead and
explicitly call its init method,
and I'm going to pass to
the Wizard's init method
the name that the student's
init method was passed.
And I'm going to go ahead and
do the same down here in Wizard.
This is one line of copy, paste.
But I think I'm OK with
it here because it's still
allowing me to do all
of the name assignment
and the error checking up
in the Wizard class instead.
I think we're OK now by just
calling super.init for both student
and Professor alike.
Now, admittedly, this syntax is
definitely out there-- the fact
that we're calling super
in parentheses and dots
and underscore underscore on the
left and the right of init here,
but it's just a combination
of these two ideas.
super() is a way of programmatically
accessing a current class's parent
class, or superclass, and __init, of
course, is just referring to, now,
that class's own initialization method.
Now, per the dot, dot,
dot-- so there could be
a lot more going on in these classes.
But what's nice now is
that Wizard as a class
is taking care of all of the
assignment of a wizard's name,
whether that wizard is a
student or a professor.
And it's even doing some
error checking to make
sure the name was actually passed in.
Meanwhile, student is inheriting
all of that functionality
and using it by calling the
superclass's own init method.
But it's additionally taking
the house, that's presumably
passed into the student
constructor function,
and assigning it to its own
instance variable-- self.house,
and similarly, professor,
or restoring in self.subject
the subject that was passed
into that one as well.
Now, how might we use these classes?
Well, we'll continue to wave our hands
with a little bit of detail here.
But at the bottom of this file, or
any other file that imports this one,
I could now write code like this.
I could create a student
variable and assign
it the return value of the
student constructor call.
and maybe that student is named
Harry and that student's house,
for instance, might be Gryffindor.
And meanwhile, I might do something like
this. professor = Professor over here.
And notice, the lowercase S on
the left, capital S on the right.
Same for professor on the left--
lowercase and uppercase on the right
respectively.
Professor, quote, unquote,
"Severus," and how
about Defense Against the
Dark Arts will be his subject?
And meanwhile, if we
want, more generically,
just a wizard, who, at the moment
is neither student nor professor
teaching classes actively,
we could even do that.
We could do wizard = Wizard in
capital W on the right-hand side
of the equal sign, because
it's the name of the class.
And someone like Albus--
passing in only Albus's name--
not a house, not a subject, because, in
this case, he's known only as a wizard.
Meanwhile, with each of these
calls, this line of code
here will ensure that the init method
for the wizard class is called.
This line of code here will ensure
that the init method of the student
class and, in turn, the init method
of the superclass wizard is called.
And then lastly, on
this final line of code,
will this syntax ensure that the
init method of the professor class
is called, which, in turn, calls the
init method of the superclass as well.
Any questions now on
this idea of inheritance,
which is a key feature of a lot of
object-oriented programming languages?
MICHAEL: From what I've seen so far, a
lot of times, there's a lot of nesting.
If you do super, does it go one up?
Is there any situation where it's nested
in another class as well, above Wizard,
let's say?
DAVID J. MALAN: A really good question.
If you were to have a
super superclass-- so
your hierarchy is even taller
than the two levels of hierarchy
that we currently have, absolutely.
What's nice about inheritance,
as the name implies, is,
just as you might have inherited
certain traits as a human
from your grandfather and
grandmother or your great-grandfather
or great-grandmother,
some of those properties
can actually trickle down to you
in the context of code as well.
So when you descend from another class--
that is, when you subclass a
superclass or a super superclass,
you actually do inherit
all of the functionality,
not just from one level above
you but from two or three,
so you can indeed access some
of that functionality as well.
And you can even override it if
you want some of these classes
to behave a little bit
differently than others.
Other questions on inheritance.
AUDIENCE: So it's
similar to the last one,
but can you have two
parents on the same level?
DAVID J. MALAN: A really good question.
So there are ways to implement
descendants from multiple parents.
And there's different ways to do this,
not just in Python but other languages.
We've kept things simple here, though,
by having a single inheritance path.
A good question.
How about one more
question on inheritance?
AUDIENCE: Can we have multiple
arguments in super.__init?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yes, but in this case,
I'm only passing a name on line 18,
and I'm only passing in name on line 10.
Why?
Because, on line 2, when I define
the init method for the Wizard class,
I only expect a single argument.
But I could absolutely have
other common functionality.
I could add in a patronus.
If both students and
professors have patronuses
that can come out of their wands,
I could have two arguments instead.
We've been using this feature
of object-oriented programming
now for quite some time
in the form of exceptions.
Indeed, if you look at the official
documentation for exceptions in Python,
you'll see that there's not even
the ones we've seen in class,
like value error and others.
There's any number of others as
well, but they are all, themselves,
hierarchical in nature.
This is just a subset of the available
exceptions that come built into Python.
And you can actually, as a programmer,
create your own exceptions as well.
But as this chart here
captures hierarchically,
all exceptions we've seen
thus far actually descend from
or inherit from superclasses already.
So for instance, at
the bottom of this list
here is ValueError, which
we've seen quite a bit.
And if you follow the line straight up
on this ascii rendition of this chart,
you'll see that ValueError has a parent,
class, or superclass, called exception.
And the exception class, meanwhile, has
a parent class called base exception.
Why did the authors of Python do this?
Well, it turns out that, whether you
have a value error or a key error
or an assertion error
or any number of others,
there's a lot of functionality common
to all of those types of errors
that you want--
that you want a programmer
to be able to use.
And so it turns out that the authors
of Python decided, you know what?
Let's not have a dozen
or more different classes
that all just have copy,
pasted similar functionality.
Let's create this
hierarchy so that, even
though the exceptions toward the
bottom of this list are very precise,
they at least inherit--
that is, borrow some very
common functionality up above.
So it turns out that, when you use the
Try and the Accept keyword in Python,
generally speaking, we've tried
to catch very specific exceptions,
like ValueError.
But technically, you could
capture the parents or even
the grandparent exception
for a given exception,
especially if you're not necessarily
sure which one is going to get raised.
Or, better yet, there could be
many exceptions that get raised,
but you want to handle
them all the same,
and you don't want to
necessarily enumerate them
in parentheses, separated by commas.
You want to say you want to handle
all exceptions of a certain superclass
in much the same way.
So this has been latent this
whole time, any time we've
seen or used or caught or, now, raised
exceptions, and built into Python
is this hierarchy.
And if you were to invent
your own exception,
generally, you wouldn't
want to start from scratch.
You would want to descend from-- that
is, subclass, one of these existing
exceptions and add your own twist on
it, your own functionality as well.
Well, there's one final feature
of object oriented programming
that we'd like to share
with you today, and then it
will perhaps be quite the eye opener
as to what you can really do now
that you have classes at your disposal.
And this, too, surprise,
has been a feature
you and I have been taking
for granted for weeks now.
This has just worked, but
it's been implemented in a way
that you can now leverage yourself.
It turns out that Python, and
some other languages, too,
support this notion of
operator overloading, whereby
you can take very common symbols, like
plus or minus or other such syntax
on the keyboard, and you can implement
your own interpretation thereof.
Plus does not have to equal addition.
And minus does not have
to equal subtraction.
And in fact, you and I have
already seen another context
in which plus means something else.
Plus has not always, in
Python, meant addition, per se.
What else has Python used plus for?
AUDIENCE: Concatenation?
DAVID J. MALAN: For concatenation.
For joining two strings, for adding
to a list can you use plus as well.
So plus has actually been, funny enough,
overloaded by the authors of Python
for us.
And so we can use the same symbol
in much the same way as addition
but with different data types to
solve slightly different problems.
Well, let me propose that we
go back over to VS Code here,
and let me go ahead and create a
new final file called vault.py.
So code of vault.py.
And let me propose that we
implement the idea of a vault
at Gringotts, keeping on
theme, wherein there's
a bank in the world of Harry Potter.
And within this bank,
families and individuals
have vaults containing all sorts
of money in the wizarding world.
And the type of money that exists
in the world of Harry Potter
are coins called galleons
and sickles and Knuts,
and those are in
descending order of value.
And so inside of a vault might
be a whole bunch of coins--
gold, silver, and bronze, essentially,
each in those denominations,
tucked away.
So how can I go about implementing,
first of all, the idea of a vault
so that I can store, for instance,
for Harry Potter, how much coinage
is in his family's vault,
or for Ron Weasley the same?
Well, let me go ahead
and vault.py and first
create a class called Vault, essentially
meant to represent a bank vault.
Perfect, another real
world, or fantasy world,
entity that I want to
represent with code.
I could use a tuple or
a list or a dictionary.
But again, I'm going to get a lot
more functionality with classes,
and we'll see one final
flourish with operators.
Inside of this vault class,
let's go ahead and do this.
Let me define my init method,
taking its first argument of self.
And let me define three
arguments to this.
When you create a
vault, in my code here,
I want to be able to initialize it with
some number of galleons, some number
of sickles and, some number of Knuts.
I want the user, the programmer,
to be able to pass in one or more
of those values ideally.
But they can be optional,
so I'll give them defaults.
So let's go ahead and define
a parameter called galleons,
whose default value will be 0; sickles,
whose default value will also be 0;
and knuts, whose default
value will be 0 as well.
So the programmer can pass in one or
two or three or even none of those,
and they'll all have
some implied defaults.
How do I want to remember those
values that are passed in?
Well, let me do this.
self.galleons = galleons.
And self.sickles = sickles.
And self.knuts = knuts.
And so I could add some error checking,
especially if you don't pass in.
A number I could turn these into
properties to do even more validation.
But let's keep it simple and, as
always, focus only on the new ideas.
So I'm just going to trust that
these values were passed in,
and I'm going to immediately assign
them to these instance variables.
What, now, do I want to do?
Well, let's come up with
a way of printing out
what is in someone's vault, ultimately.
But first let's do this.
Let's create a vault for the Potters by
creating, via assignment, a new vault.
And let's say that the potters have
100 galleons, 50 sickles, and 24 knuts.
And that's in that vault. And let's
print out, for instance, potter.
All right, let's run this
code and see how it works now.
Let me go ahead and run
Python of vault.py, Enter.
Seems to work.
No syntax errors or anything else.
But this is not very enlightening.
How do I fix this, thinking
back to what we've done before?
AUDIENCE: You have to use the __str.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
I need to use one of those special
methods that comes with classes
and define for myself how I want
a vault to be printed as a string.
So let me go ahead and do that.
Let me define the str method taking
in self as its sole argument here.
And let's just return
a very simple string
that just reveals what's in the vault.
So I'm going to return
a formatted f string,
inside of which is self.galleons
and then the word galleon,
so I know which those are.
Then let's do self.sickles, and
let's output the word, sickles.
And then lastly let's output
self.knuts, and then knuts here.
So I know, in this string, just
how many of each of those coins
I have in this particular family's
vault. All right, let me go ahead
and run Python of vault.py, changing
nothing else except the str method.
And now, , we, see indeed that Harry has
100 galleons, 50 sickles, and 25 knuts.
All right, well, let's
do one thing more here.
Below that, let's go ahead
and define a Weasley variable.
And Ron never seemed to have quite as
much money in the vault as did Harry.
So let's say that the Weasley
vault will have 25, 50, and 100.
So I'll just reverse the
order of those denominations,
rather than Harry's 100, 50, 25.
And now let me go ahead and
print Weasley like this.
And let's go ahead and clear my
terminal window, run Python of vault.py.
This time, that str method
will be invoked twice, once
for each of those vault objects.
And we'll see, indeed, that
the first one for Harry
has got 100, 50, and 25,
respectively, versus Ron's 25, 50,
and 100, respectively.
But now let's do something interesting.
Suppose that you wanted to combine
the contents of two vaults,
be it Harry's and Ron's
or any other two people.
How would you go about
doing this in code?
Well, if I wanted to combine the
vaults for someone, I could do this.
Well, I could do galleons equals--
let's do potter.galleons
+ weasley.galleons.
That gives me a variable
called galleons that has
the sum of Harry and Ron's galleons.
Let's next do sickles =
potter.sickles + weasley.sickles.
And then lastly, let's do knuts
= potter.knuts + weasley.knuts.
I've got three variables.
What can I now do with these values?
Well, let's create a third--
a new vault. Total will
be the name of this variable equals
a new vault, Capital V, notice.
And now, let's pass in
those three new variables--
galleons, sickles, and knuts.
And that's it, and let's
print out this total vault.
So we should now see three
vaults-- one for Harry, for Ron,
and the combination--
the addition of the two.
Let me go ahead and rerun Python
of vault.py, and there we have it.
What was 100, 50, 25 and 25, 50, and
100, combined through addition now,
is 125, 100, 125.
So pretty straightforward,
using techniques from weeks
ago, where we're just declaring a few
new variables and doing some addition.
But wouldn't it be cool if I
could do something like this?
Wouldn't it be cool if
I could just somehow,
not manually create my own vault and
do all of this annoying math up here--
what if I could just do potter + weasley
and get rid of all of this logic here?
Wouldn't it be nice if I
overload the operator--
we know as plus, just
like str does, just
like list does-- to allow me
to add two vaults together
on the left and the right.
Well, it turns out in Python and
through operator overloading,
there is a way to do just this.
If you consult the
documentation, there's
this and so many other special
methods that come with classes.
The third one we'll see
here is this one here--
__add__.
And you'll see that it very
generically is described
in the documentation is working for
any object, be it a vault or str
or a list or something else.
By convention, it's going to take
a first argument called self,
and then it's going to take some other
argument, by convention, called other.
self, in effect, is going
to be referring to whatever
object is on the left of a plus sign.
other is going to be
referring to whatever
is on the right-hand
side of a plus sign,
thereby giving us a way of
describing, in code, the operand
on the left and the operand on the
right of the operator, plus, in between.
That is to say, if I go
back to VS Code here,
what I'm trying to do is
implement support for this.
Well, let me try, without
writing any other code just yet--
Python of vault.py, Enter--
TypeError: unsupported operand
type(s) for +: 'Vault' and 'vault.'
That is to say Python, at this
moment, does not know what
it means to add two vaults together.
You and I might have an instinct.
Probably want to combine the galleons
and the sickles and the knuts
respectively.
Python doesn't know that.
It just knows that you have
a new class called Vault.
But let's teach Python to do this.
Let me clear my terminal window.
Let me scroll back up to the class
itself, where, at the moment,
I only have two special
methods-- init and str.
But let's add this third.
Let me go into the class here and define
__add__ and then specify its first
parameter as self, as before, and then
a second parameter for this particular
method called, by convention, other.
Now, as always, I could name
those parameters anything
I want, but I'm going to
stick with convention here.
And now, inside of
this method, am I going
to have to now add together
the contents of two vaults?
Well, what two vaults?
Well, if we scroll down to our
goal at hand, the goal, of course,
is to add this vault plus
this other vault-- potter
plus weasley, respectively.
Well, it turns out, in Python, that,
when you do overload an operator like
plus, what's going to
happen automatically,
as soon as Python sees that, is it's
going to call that __add__ method,
and it's going to pass
into it to arguments--
whatever the operand is on the
left-- potter, in this case--
and whatever the operand is on
the right-- weasley, in this case.
And those values are going to get passed
in as self and other, respectively.
What that means is that we can
access their contents up here
in our implementation of add as follows.
Let me go ahead and define a local
variable called galleons and set that
equal to, for instance,
the sum of self.galleons--
whatever's in Potter's
vault in this case,
plus whatever is in Wesley's
vault in this case, which
would be other.galleons.
Let me do the same for sickles.
self.sickles + other.sickles.
And let me lastly do that for knuts.
So self.knuts + other.knuts.
But at the end of the
day, I'm going to need
to return a brand new bigger vault
that contains all of those contents
together.
And if we ultimately want to assign that
bigger vault to a variable like total
here, on the left, we'd better
return a value from this add method.
So I'm going to go ahead and give myself
a brand new vault, as by returning
capital Vault, which of course, is going
to call my vault function into which
I can now pass some of those
initialization arguments.
Well, how many galleon,
sickles, and knuts do
I want this brand new vault to contain?
Well, I want it to contain this
many galleons this many sickles,
and this many knuts.
So ultimately, what we're
doing in this implementation
of add is adding together those
galleons, sickles, and knuts, passing
them to the vault function so that
we get a brand new bigger vault,
and return that altogether.
So now I've defined
this new special method
called add that should now just
make plus work for two vaults.
Let's see.
Let me run down to my terminal window,
Python of vault.py and hit Enter.
And voila, and now we've implemented
an overloaded operator, plus,
to do what you and I
as humans would hope
would be the case when you
add two vaults together.
But I've now written the
code more specifically
to teach Python what it means
concretely to add two vaults together.
And it's with very
similar code in effect,
underneath the hood, that Python
is doing this for two strings,
to concatenate them together, to joining
two lists into a new list with list,
and so many other classes as well.
Any questions now on operator
overloading or this example here.
AUDIENCE: How would
you go about creating
a function for adding a student and
a vault for two separate classes?
Would that be possible?
DAVID J. MALAN: Let me
see what happens here.
I don't know offhand.
Let's do this.
Let's create a str and see what happens.
If I add Potter plus a str--
str object.
Yeah, so it would work.
I'm just figuring this
out as I go here, Eric.
So just to be clear,
what I did was I just
changed weasley to str
just to see what would
happen when I add a vault plus a
str, and it will work, theoretically.
Why?
Because so long as the type of value on
the left has an add method implemented,
other can be any type that you want.
You just have to decide
and code what it's
going to mean conceptually to
add a vault plus a string, which,
in this case, probably doesn't make
any sense at all, but it's possible.
It's going to be the
operand on the left.
And I'm inferring that.
I did not know the answer a moment ago.
I'm inferring that because what I got
was an attribute error here on line 11
because Python did not like
this. other.galleons didn't work,
but I could make it work
by figuring something out.
Really good question.
Didn't know that one myself.
Other questions on operator overloading?
AUDIENCE: Can you define
new operators in Python?
DAVID J. MALAN: I don't think so.
There is a very long but precise list
of operators that you can overload.
I do not believe you can
assign arbitrary characters
to be operators in Python.
Let me defer to Carter in the chat to--
OK, I'm seeing two of my colleagues
are saying, no, not possible.
So I'm going to go with
my first instinct, no.
Otherwise, that'd be kind of cool.
You could make emoji do
whatever you want to.
How about one final question
on operator overloading?
AUDIENCE: Is that the only
operation you can do as far as--
can you do a subtraction as well?
DAVID J. MALAN: You can.
You can do so many others let me.
If, Carter, you don't mind
pulling up this URL here--
so this link here-- special
method names and today's slides,
you'll see a long list of all of
the operators that you can overload.
You can do less than, equals
than, plus equals, minus equals.
Pretty much any symbol you've
seen me type on the screen
can be overloaded in
the context of classes.
So even though, today,
we focused entirely
on object-oriented programming, this
is a technique that we've been using,
really, since the first week of
the class because those ints,
those strs, those floats, those
lists, those dictionaries,
and so much more were already underneath
the hood this whole time-- classes
and objects thereof.
But you now, as a
programmer, have the ability
to create your own classes with your
own instance or class variables,
with your own instance or class
methods, with your own properties,
and even with your own custom
behavior for operators.
So ultimately, you can
absolutely continue
using those simple tuples or lists or
those dictionaries or other structures
as well.
But object-oriented programming, and
with it, classes and now these objects
is just another tool in your toolkit.
And daresay, as your code
gets more sophisticated
and your problems get
bigger, you'll find
that being able to model these real
world or even fantasy world entities
with classes and related
data and functionality
will ultimately just allow you to define
code that's not just correct but ever
well-designed as well.
This was CS50.