Crea is a powerful and free digital art
application that can be used to create
stunning paintings drawings and even
animations but learning Crea can be
challenging especially if you're new to
digital art or you don't have a lot of
time to practice that's why I created
this course to teach you the essentials
of working with cre in a fun and easy
way in this course you'll learn how to
use C from scratch including the basics
of crea's user interface how to create
and use brushes how to select and mix
colors how to work with layers and masks
how to add effects and textures how to
export your work to a variety of formats
how to record time lapses of your
process and much more see the course
syllabus for everything I
cover by the end of this course you'll
have an excellent foundation in cre that
you can use to bring your imagination to
life this course is suitable for artists
of all skill levels and it's designed to
be interactive and engaging you'll get
access to three hours of video lessons
custom brushes and content for cre and
template files you can use to follow
along with me though it was a lot of
work I've chosen to make this course
very affordable to give artists who are
on a budget an opportunity to learn
digital art there is a minimum price but
you can choose to pay what you want I
encourage you to support the content I
create if you're able to if you want to
learn CA this is one of the best places
to start check out the link in the
description of this video or go to Aaron
ron.com and start learning creative
today thanks for watching and I look
forward to what you'll create with
c