splitting video clips in shotcut is easy
hover over this icon it's the split at
playhead and when we click this it will
split the video clip into two parts
wherever the playhead is at
we can also press the s key on the
keyboard for the shortcut to split a
video clip if we right click on a new
clip and go to remove it'll just remove
that clip now we've just created an edit
to jump from one part of the video clip
to another part
while the playhead is advancing we can
press the s key on the keyboard to
create multiple splits in the clip if we
want to
we can then pause the video and go back
click on clip hit the delete key on the
keyboard and it'll just delete that clip
leaving a blank space in the timeline
then we can move the different clips
around if we want to by left-clicking
and holding by left-clicking on the
mouse or we can right-click and go to
remove to remove an empty space
shotcut is a 100 free and open source
video editing software and you can learn
how to use it for free here on this
channel tjfree just check out the links
below to get started with the free video
playlist thanks for watching
you