so you've heard pretty cool things about
dark table and you've decided to try it
out you load your first capture and wait
what the sky is pink the c is pink dark
table is rubbish the sun is clearly
yellow as displayed in this 2d graph
so why is dark table turning the sun
pink and what can we do to fix it the
most common culprit of pink areas in
your capture is
highlight clipping at the sensor
this is what happens when you have too
much fun in the sun
part of the data you captured hit the
ceiling of the sensor's upper limit and
the sensor said yep i'm full write
maximum values in all these areas
when we load a camera native data file
also known as raw into dark table
we apply certain processes
so we can visualize the data captured
i'm going to try and investigate why the
highlights turn pink so bear with me or
skip to the chapter in the video where i
attempt to fix the pink highlights
let's say that this is our capture with
a bit of overexposure i will disable all
modules that i can disable
so we can see what's happening step by
step
i'm also going to skip the mosaic as
this throws us off a little bit
and
i'm going to set the raw black and white
point to pass through
now we can work this process from the
bottom up
at this point we're pretty much
visualizing the data values in our raw
file
if we zoom in to a stupid percentage we
can see the photosite pattern
each photosite contains a single numeric
value
right now if we look at the raw black
white point module we can see that the
largest photosite value
three 65535 gets a white square and the
lowest value zero
gets a black square
our squares at this point are a certain
shade of gray because we are not using
the whole range between zero and six
five five 65535
the camera that i shot with can only
write 14 bit data files
which means the maximum value is
16 383
if i drag the slider back to the
manufacturer recommended value of 16 300
you will notice that we are simply
marking where our useful data ends and
where it begins
if i reset this module the values will
change depending on the camera they came
from
now we're going to take a step that is
going to be a bit confusing
because we know the bare filter pattern
of our sensor we can give these values
an arbitrary color i would give them
different colors other than green red
and blue but i don't have a choice at
this point so here it is
remember
we cannot deduce color information from
a single value this is just a
visualization a colorful chart if you
will you will notice that every second
square is green this is the bayer
pattern of the sensor it is called the
cfa color filtration array the most
common one is red green green blue why
there are more green squares than red
and blue bryce bear's patented pattern
included an additional green filter per
every red green and blue filter to mimic
the physiology of the human eye which
uses m and l cones to perceive luminance
they are most sensitive to green light
so how do we get something useful out of
these squares well first we need to
debayer
which is synonymous to the mosaic we
have quite a few algorithms to choose
from
that in a nutshell take information from
adjacent squares and approximate a value
so instead of one value per square we
want to have three values per square
three is the magic number here as
coincidentally we will end up with three
channels that make an image red green
and blue
also known as rgb
but right now we're still in large
number land
now let's do mosaic we will use a
debayering algorithm but will not
account for the fact that we have more
green squares than red and blue squares
we just want to get three values per
square instead of one value each i'll
select rcd for the mosaic king because
it's the default
and here it is it's as if we averaged
all the squares in a fancy way to get a
smooth visualization of the data in the
raw file the only thing that is missing
now is to take into account that we have
more green squares than red and blue
squares we need to scale the three
values accordingly
i'm going to do this manually for
maximum effects and that's aha moment
but it's best to keep this module at d65
notice how everything appears to be
green
except for the sun and the clouds
they look white
keep that in mind
now watch what happens when i move the
tint slider and make the preview less
green and more pink
as i move the tint slider towards pink
the visually green areas move towards
white
the visually white areas move towards
pink
since this operation is still simply
mathematical and is not performed in the
color space or constraint by a display
we are able to get values above 1 or 255
because we perform these operations
non-destructively
later on in the pipeline we take these
values and usher them into a gamut
finally giving them try stimulus meaning
in simpler terms we are finally in rgb
land and our values begin to hold
meaning
technically it happened a bit earlier
since i'm not able to turn the module
off you can imagine that up to the input
color profile module everything is black
and white values that we haven't applied
any meaning to
nice we manually produced the ping
highlights and now we know that it's not
a result of something being broken but a
result of being non-destructive
that's it
let me reset the unfortunately called
white balance module in its default and
let me enable the color calibration
module as well
right it's time to do something about
that pink sky
let's first assume our default filmic
rgb workflow
i will move to reconstruction tab as i
will need to reconstruct the areas that
were clipped at the sensor
i will enable the mask preview
as it is important to select the area
we're working on
right now it's black
because nothing is selected
i'll walk the threshold slider back
until i see the over exposed areas turn
white
i will adjust the transition so i can
almost see the rest of the objects in
the picture
now for the reconstruction bit
i've already went over these sliders and
what they do in other two videos that i
will link in the description
right now i will gloss over their
function
as i search for the best result
we can turn the mask off
for the first slider let's keep the
reconstruction technique in the middle
between structure and texture the second
slider
i will attempt to reconstruct instead of
bloom first because i feel there is
enough detail for some reconstruction
there in the highlights and as always i
will go full gray on the last slider
our color information is mangled due to
clipping and i'm not going to bother
preserving something i don't care about
full grain
okay we still have the pink sky and pink
c
that means that our threshold is too
high
i will walk that back slightly
until it's completely gone
okay it looks better but i can feel it
looks a bit harsh still let's try to
favor more bloom instead of
reconstructing
there we go
nice and smooth we can even increase the
white relative exposure a little bit
which will likely bring back a bit of
pink highlights
but we can fix that once again by
adjusting the threshold
there we go
problem fixed
often there are times where we don't
want to use filmic rgb for example
exporting exhaust to use with other
software
if we turn off filmic color balance rgb
color calibration
we end up with ping highlights again
but worry not because we have a
highlight
the construction module
let's turn that on
and i will clear the search term
now we have the most basic of methods
enabled which is called clip highlights
after we have scaled our photoside
values and if any value exceeded our
threshold it will be clipped simple as
that this will result in a flat pancake
with hue shifts everywhere
it also pretty much matches the areas
that were clipped at the center we can
preview that with this little sensor
clipping preview button
if we reduce the exposure later on in
the pipeline
we will see that it has no effect on the
clipped area
it just gets darker
the next a more intelligent option is to
reconstruct an lch
it will attempt to recover some
information from the remaining unclipped
channels it is a much better option in
my opinion even though the reconstructed
highlight contains no color information
we can recover data that we can work
with if i reduce the exposure now
you will see that we managed to recover
some detail i prefer this setting for my
exr exports when i need them
the penultimate one is reconstruct color
which gives a similar result to
reconstruct in lch
but gains the values based on
surrounding areas you get some notion of
color back but the results aren't always
stable
and the last one is guided laplacians it
is the most resource intensive
but in theory it should produce the best
results however it should be reserved to
cases where you don't have large areas
that were clipped at the sensor
otherwise it's not very effective
okay that's all the material i've
prepared for you today i hope you found
this useful and hopefully you've learned
something new today so see you soon
bye
you