welcome to this tutorial series in
this series we'll be learning how to use
from a very basic very beginner
level if you don't already have
installed you can get it for free on
windows linux and mac check out my other
video where I show how to download and
get it installed on your computer but
once it's installed and you open it up
for the first time it'll probably look
like this you've got separate windows so
it brings up three different windows
with tools in them we have a toolbox
over here with some different tool icons
we can click on as we click on those it
shows options for the tool at the bottom
of this dialog and then to the right
side there's some different tools too
that actually have different tabs we can
click on and it changes the different
tool we're on like channels and layer
and our undo history all of this stuff
can be customized how you like it so you
could move this to a different part of
your screen for example if you have
multiple monitors you could move it to a
different monitor but for the purposes
of this video I'm going to use a
different window mode and to do that
we're just gonna click on Windows and go
down to this single window mode and
check this box and what that will do is
throw all the tools into one window and
so if we resize this it's going to have
everything in one window we don't have
to worry about accidentally closing a
tool box or anything
everything's just in one big window so
again to do that it's under windows and
check this box called single window mode
I'm gonna be in single window mode this
entire tutorial series to get started
with a project we can come up here to
the top left hand corner and click on
file and there's a bunch of different
options we have we can create a new
project or we can open an existing image
on our computer and apply some changes
to it let's click on new and it brings
up this dialog here it lets us create a
new blank image that's gonna have a
width of 2000 and a height of 1984
that's in pixels which is a little dots
on your screen we can change this unit
if you're feeling more comfortable using
inches or maybe millimeters or
centimeters we can change to whatever
unit we want if we want to do inches
then that's about six and a half by six
and a half inches but we could do it we
can maybe change this and do an 8 by 10
so we have 8 inches wide by 10 inches
tall
now there's also Advanced Options here
but let's not worry about these right
now but if we click on Advanced Options
it brings in some more options for
creating our document for now let's just
click OK it really doesn't matter what
size you're working with and so we have
a nice eight we see there's a ruler
across the top here starting at 0 and
going over to 8 so this is 8 inches wide
and then the height is 10 inches we see
over here is a zero and if we scroll
down it's to about 10 inches so we have
a nice 8 by 10 almost like a page right
here and we can select some of these
tools maybe we come over here there's
this brush tool this paintbrush if we
left click on that we now have the
paintbrush tool selected we know that
because our mouse cursor changes to have
a little paintbrush on it now if we left
click and hold it kind of creates some
different shapes here or some different
that drawing whatever we want to draw
and so we can draw on here if we want to
undo you can hit control Z on your
keyboard and it'll undo the last stroke
you did ctrl Z on your keyboard does
that you can also go up here to the top
left under edit and click on edit and
just go to undo paintbrush and it'll
undo what we've done a stroke by stroke
so now we're back to blank and maybe we
want to click on this pencil instead if
we hover over this pencil tool it says
pencil hard edge painting using a brush
capital n that means if we click on it
we can use the paintbrush or if we're if
we're on a different tool we can always
hit the N key on our keyboard to quickly
get back to the paintbrush I mean I'm
sorry the pencil tool if we hover over a
paintbrush it also has a shortcut P so
press P on the keyboard we're now using
our paintbrush and on the keyboard we're
now using our pencil tool and those are
actually customizable if you don't like
those shortcuts you can change them you
don't have to use the shortcuts hover
over this tool right here is called the
eraser tool if we left click on eraser
we can now erase different things here
but we see we're erasing kind of small
if we want our eraser to be bigger we
can change the size all the different
settings for these tools are found right
below these tools in this little
dialogue here it's a little bit cramped
in here right now
if we want to see this differently we
can hover over in between right next to
the ruler and this toolbox
over here left click and hold and we can
drag this out so it's larger we get it
as large as we want and it's sort of
reset rearranges these columns and rows
for the different tools maybe that's a
good one there so that we can read more
what's happening with these so let's see
eraser tool if you want to change the
size we can click plus over here or - to
change the size we can also just double
click within the number and type in a
value so if we click in here and then we
can erase that and type in like 100 for
example now the size is going to be 100
I think that's in pixels anyway and so
we can now erase this we can also scroll
our mouse wheel in here I'm just using
the scroll wheel on my mouse to increase
the size so now it's even larger and we
can erase much larger and as another way
to change this we can just click in here
click and hold our left mouse button and
move our mouse from right to left and
that'll also change the size so now our
erase is very very large and we can come
in here and erase this if we
accidentally erase something we didn't
want to erase we can hit ctrl Z on the
keyboard to bring it back or if we
wanted to redo that erase we can go up
to edit and we can do redo erase or it's
control Y is the shortcut for that but
redo will rearrange the and control Y we
can toggle back and forth between undo
and redo our history keeps track of
our history and we can find it over here
we see our different history and we can
look through this history and see all
the different changes we've made and we
can jump to certain points in our
history but don't pay much attention to
that now other than knowing there's
layers and history and different things
we can toggle on these different
toolbars and that's just going to be
something very similar on every
different dialog there's these little
icons we can click to get to different
points of them so just be aware of that
these are all customizable we can move
them around and change them but for now
let's just ignore everything over here
to the right and let's only play with
clicking on different tools here and
then looking at the settings they have
below another good setting we can look
at or another good tool is this
magnification this is zoom this
magnifier glass
when this is selected we can click and
left-click and zoom either out or zoom
in so we can zoom in very far here and
I've zoomed in really far so I'm just
seeing white so if I want to zoom out I
can come over to the options for this
tool and click the zoom out with my left
mouse button and now I can left-click
and we'll slowly start to zoom out and
see get to a certain part if this is how
sumed and we want to be we can stay at
this point select maybe our pencil tool
and left-click and draw with it and we
see it's taking on the brush settings
that we apply it to the eraser so if we
want to make this smaller we can come
over to the size and left-click and
change it to small or we can reset it to
the default by clicking this little icon
here if we hover over it tells us what
this does reset the aspect ratio reset
the spacing so we can reset the size and
now it's small again if we want to get
to a different portion of our drawing we
can use these sliders over here we can
left-click and slide up and down to get
to a lower part then we can keep drawing
and then slide down and there's also a
slider across the bottom as well so we
didn't slide from left to right another
way to do that is just hold down the the
control wheel on your mouse and it
creates this sort of hand grab icon it's
like grabbing the entire canvas and just
moving to a certain point and there's
lots of different shortcuts we'll learn
but for now it's good to get familiar
with just using the different tools we
can zoom out here and left-click and
quickly zoom out we're going to talk
about changing the color in the next
video that's just right here we click
and we can change our color but we'll
learn more about this it gets a little
bit complex and will sort of take that
apart and learn it in the next video for
now I just want to show you if we get
something drawn like this and we want to
save our project we can go to the top
left hand corner again and go to file
and this time we can go to save or we
can go to export it depends on what we
want to do with this picture if we want
to save it and work on it later we click
save that brings up this dialog box that
lets us save the project on our computer
we see that last three letters is a dot
xcf file which is a project
file so we just changed the first part
of this to my project or whatever you
want to call it and then it will save it
in documents is where I'm saved that you
can change put it in pictures maybe or a
certain folder on your computer and I'll
click Save and then that will save it to
the documents in my computer but again
it's a project file so where's my
documents right here so here's this file
that we've created that Sadaat xcf it's
not going to be really compatible people
can't open this with just everyday
software they have to have a or a
program that can open this type of file
so we don't want to send this to someone
in an email or upload it to a blog or a
web page we can't really print this very
easily without using we want to
convert this if we want to share this
what we would do is export this image
instead so to do that we go file and we
go to export and that's sort of like
developing the picture as it's sort of
like when it's set in stone and we're
done making changes to it then we go to
export and you can export and save it's
a good idea to save your project and
then also export and so again now we see
under the export options it's a dot PNG
which is an image file we can change
that as well but we'll just leave it
call it whatever you want to make sure
it's a dot PNG file and hit export and
then it brings up this dialog with some
more advanced options just leave
everything how it is here and hit export
and then it exports this image don't get
overwhelmed in settings
is very well organized from the
beginning to just leave everything at
default and then as you get more
comfortable and more advanced I'm using
it you can maybe play with and tweak
some of those advanced settings and so
now we can minimize this and go to the
location on our computer that we've
saved I saved it in My Documents and we
see we have to now a project file which
is dot xcf if we click on this it'll
open it up in and then we also have
an image file they look the same but the
image file is a more compatible format
we can send we can upload to our blog or
a website or we can print this take it
to like Walgreens or summer and have it
printed and
be like what but this is just like a PNG
image okay and it's just being displayed
we can't make changes to it right here
it's just an image file and you can
learn if you're not familiar with that
this may be outside the scope of this is
learning about different image formats
but just know there's two different ways
in we do file save to save our
project and work on it in the future and
then export exports a final finished
image and you can make changes and
export it as many times as you want we
could now export and call it something
different but we'll play with that more
in the future too so play with these
brushes play with the eraser tool learn
how to go ahead and play with some of
these different things like spacing and
hardness and see how it affects your
brush and in the next video we'll be
learning about color and some more of
different tools that we can use in
leave your questions or comments below
if you have any and I'll catch you in
the next video