hello welcome back for the part 3 of the
deepish dive into filmic rgb in this
video i'm going to be attempting to
develop a tricky capture
a capture where we have the sun shining
through the very colorful petals
as well as this huge area that's in the
shadow the goal or intention of the
final image is going to be one
make the photo feel warm as the sky is
clear and we have a lovely sunshine two
make the tree look colorful
try to convey the feeling that it was
incredibly colorful without making it
look deep fried
and three maintain the contrast as much
as possible since it was a bright and
sunny day i want to convey the strong
shadows that were present that day
i don't want the final image to look
flat or hdr like
and this might take some time
okay the image is loaded i'll make a
duplicate
and i'll also take a snapshot so we can
compare it later
let's go straight to filmic rgb
options
let's get rid of the prominence
preservation
this will immediately get rid of some of
the artifacts
that we can see around this pole
if i turn back to max rgb
you will see there are a couple of weird
straight lines
and of course the the great big glaring
magenta sun
if we turn that off
you'll see that the issue is no longer
there
again we're sacrificing the preservation
of the rgb ratios but we are preserving
the feeling of brightness smooth
gradients and overall a more natural
feeling let's not forget we're doing
creative photography here if i had to do
brand work that include brand colors in
photography or cg renders i would
possibly consider using the max rgb
preservation method however what we're
doing here is far from it and trying to
scan the real world is not my priority
my priority is a good image a good
picture a good photo
if one wants to get the best experience
of
being there i suggest google street view
while we're at it i'm not a big fan of
mark's rgb preservation method being the
default so let's change that really
quickly
click on the burger menu store new
preset call it
no
preservation
and auto apply this preset to matching
images and leave the settings at the
default
this will apply this preset to every
image that's entering darkroom
okay
now that we got that out of the way
let's get back to developing
we'll jump to exposure
and increase it quite a bit
so about here
now that we can see what we're working
on i can go to color calibration
and adjust the temperature first let's
turn on the color assessment mode
set the illuminant to d
daylight
and adjust the temperature
my goal here is to get as neutral colors
as possible
we'll worry about warmth
a bit later
okay that looks about right now we can
jump back to filmic rgb
we've lost a bit of visual contrast when
we increase the exposure
so i would like to bring some of that
back let's move to the look tab
first i would like to reduce the
latitude to a minimum
that will give us a bit more flexibility
with the contrast as well as give us
smoother transitions between shadows
tones and highlights
now increase the contrast
until i am happy
okay 1.5 seems to be the magic number
let's do a couple of slight adjustments
to the white and black relative exposure
i need less details and highlights
and more details in shadows
let's decrease the white relative
exposure
i'll zoom in a little bit
that's too much
okay that looks about right and in the
shadows
i will increase
or decrease depending on how you look at
it i will push this slider to the left
it's about here
now we might have set the contrast
correctly but our project still looks
dull and uninteresting
we're going to need to do some color
work
for that let's jump to color balance rgb
module
we have three elements in this photo the
plant
the house and the sky
i would like to control the color of the
plant and the sky separately so let's
separate them in a quick and dirty way
i will select the plant based on its
color as we have nothing else in our
frame that's of this violet hue
let's jump to the parametric mask
section
i'll use the picker to draw a window
where we have a lot of this hue
we can enable the mask preview
okay so we selected a lot of this plant
and a bit of the roof
but that's just because it is reflecting
this aggressive violet color
i'll add a bit of feathering
and a bit of blurring
i did say it was quick and dirty
okay that will do
unfortunately most of the plant is in
the shadow but i want to be able to
control the color with higher
granularity which means i'm going to set
the shadows the mid-tones and the
highlights a bit further down in the
shadows
for that let's go to the masks tab
first i know i want the strongest
separation between the highlights and
the shadows therefore i will make the
shadow and the highlight fall of curves
steeper
like that
we can enable each mask and see what we
get
masks shows us that there's still too
much of the plant in the shadow because
almost all of it is selected and
non-transparent
the mid-tone mask reveals that there's
almost nothing in the mid tones except a
bit of the plant around the edges
lastly the highlights mass reveals that
the highlights are just around the edge
of the plant
so we want to adjust the middle gray
fulcrum
and see more of the plant gets included
in the highlights
and
less of the plant gets included in the
shadows
and you can also see our mid-tones slide
around the image
in a wave
this is an excellent tool i love it
okay we have our mask set we have our
shadows here
highlights here and everything in
between is the midtones
now we can go back to the master tab
now i can increase the chroma to make
the plant feel a bit more colorful
and that will make our plant feel
brighter as well that's due to something
called
the
schoolhouse effect i'll link that in the
description now i have to be really
careful here
i want to make the plant feel colorful
without making it look uncanny or
overcooked this is exactly why i
separated the sky and the house from the
plant the context of a color is very
important
if we have too many saturated colors in
the image it will become a sensory
overload and it will look flat
the feeling of colorfulness is not
created by pumping the saturation value
to the max it just has to be more
colorful compared to its surroundings
that's why i'm going to
increase the global chroma i'm going to
decrease the chroma in the highlights
quite drastically
and i'm going to pump the chroma in the
shadows
and i might want to adjust the
perceptual brilliance just a little bit
so our plant
is a little bit lighter
now let's make a new instance of the
color rgb module and let's take care of
the sky
again let's enable the parametric mask
let's go to the
hue channel
and let's select a large area of the sky
i'll enable the mask preview
okay again feathering radius
blurring radius
and that will do for us
the accuracy doesn't matter too much
here we're not doing anything radical
just slight adjustments first i will
shift the hue slightly so it contrasts
with the plant
right now i feel that the sky
is a bit too purple
the hue slide is really sensitive so
it's best to
take small steps
okay
that looks
that looks good
we'll give it a bit more chroma
so we have a nice gradient between the
edge of the image
and the center of the sun
remember the gradient is how we convey
brightness
okay i think we nailed the contrast and
the colorfulness
but our overall image still feels a bit
cold you know what to do
create another color balance rgb
instance
this time let's go to the four ways tab
adjust the hue in the highlights gain to
something warm
and increase the chroma ever so slightly
we can zoom in
into our sun and check before
and after
zoom out
before and after
i think after looks much nicer
now
did we manage to achieve our intentions
so number one
did we make the photo feel warm with
bright sun and clear blue sky
i'm pretty sure we did
two did we make the tree look colorful
let's say 50 50 on this one
we could push more global brilliance
but we're risking breaking the balance
of the image
i think it's best to keep it this way
and three did we maintain the contrast
as much as possible
i'd say yes i tried to resist pushing
the exposure more and the difference
between the bright and the dark is
enough to make the image not look
flat we can compare our image to what
we've started with
i think the image is saved and will
serve its purpose as an example for this
tutorial
and a reminder of the lovely time i had
that day taking photos that's it i think
i've touched everything i wanted to
touch regarding the filmic rgb module
and a bit more
fun was had discussions were started
people were informed i thank you for
your time watching this hope you learned
something new and hope to see you next
time bye