in this video we'll be using caden live
and the mask effect to create this
surreal image of an ocean inside of a
mug
so we'll drag to our video track one
this image of a coffee mug and then also
this video of the ocean on the on the
upper track we'll adjust the coffee mug
to be the same length as our video
and then go to effects and search for
mask we want this alpha shapes mask
and we'll change the shape to ellipse
and then we can move this around and
it'll just show only that part of the
video
within this ellipse we'll change this
transition width which is really
feathering
it can also be called
just for those edges and then we'll make
it the size of this and this this one
works pretty easy because it's just a
nice simple shape there's more advanced
masking we can do
and then we play the video it will just
show this video of the ocean only over
this part of the image it's actually
really cool
if you want to follow along you can find
these images and video in the
description of this video you can
download and kind of do these same
things
but that's it caden live is free in open
source software and i have tutorials
teaching how to use it from a very basic
level
thanks for watching look forward to
catching you in the next video