in the last lecture we created a
multi-page document now I will save the
pages as a PDF
I go to file save as
behind save as type I choose portable
document format I will choose the
highest pdf version
if you want your text to stay text so it
can be selected and copied choose embed
fonts otherwise choose convert text to
paths if you used blur for example for
making a shadow or you applied a filter
you will have to rasterize these effects
if you want them displayed in your PDF
because I save for print I will set
rasterize filter effects to 300 DPI it
is also possible to save a PDF with
extra space around each page called
bleed as indicated in the menu you can
set page bleed with the page tool which
can be found below margins
keep in mind that for creating PDF files
with multiple Pages you can also use a
dedicated desktop publishing software
like Scripps
I have a complete course about scribus
on this channel
I created spreads in inkscape so I also
would like to view spreads in acrobat
to do this I can click on the show two
pages side by side icon
or I can go to view page display to page
view
[Music]
foreign