in the last lecture we saw how to clone
objects now we will look at cloning text
I want to be able to adjust the size and
kerning of the percent sign at a later
point with many instances it would take
a long time to adjust all glyphs
individually so I will clone the glyph
to be flexible
I select the text tool and click on the
canvas I want the number to be right
aligned then it will always align to the
percent sign I make the font size 30
point I select the text tool again and
click on the canvas
now I want left aligned text I type the
glyph and make it 18 point I'll place
the new text on top and make it white I
alt click to select the old text below
and press delete
now I will clone the glyph
I lower the Clone and drag the parent
down
to increase the size I drag the middle
Arrow at the right side
this way I do not change the distance
between the texts when sizing I hold
Ctrl when I resize
and to adjust the kerning I double click
on the glyph I hold down alt and use my
left and right arrow keys I will make
the text a group so I can easily move
the text around I duplicate the text to
enter the group I double click on it and
I double click on the number to change
it I can now change the size of all
instances and I can turn the text and
change the height holding Alt