in lecture 12 I assigned the shortcut
control y to toggle between normal and
outline mode as it is an
illustrator in inkscape this function
doesn't have a shortcut by default I
also want inkscape and scribus to
have the same shortcuts for the same
tools to change shortcuts I go to edit
preferences I open interface and click
on keyboard if you would like to have
the shortcuts from another software
program behind keyboard file there is a
list with options
I would like the illustrator shortcuts
toggling between normal and outline mode
by default doesn't have a shortcut set
so I will add it in the search window I
type toggle I see that display mode
toggle doesn't have a shortcut yet to
add it I click at the right in the
shortcut column I now see the text new
accelerator I type control y if the
shortcut is already used you can choose
to reuse it for another function so I
click on yes and I close the
window