in this lecture I will add the nose tail
and scutes using the pencil tool I
select it I click on the green Swatch at
the top right I click on the snapping
icon to activate it and in the pencil
menu I will activate the interactive
icon this option will let me improve the
curve after drawing it let's draw the
tail when I hold my mouse above the edge
of the body I see the text handle the
path
this means the tool will snap to the
path Edge when I start drawing I keep my
mouse pressed down and follow the Curve
when I see the text handle to corner I
reach the corner of the body I let go of
the mouse
as we see right now my curve is not
smooth
so I will improve it by increasing
smoothing let's try 70. now let's make
the nose
this time I start from the corner
I smooth the curve even more by setting
smoothing to 100. now I draw the skews I
select the brown Swatch I set smoothing
to 60. when I stop drawing I see I am
missing the lower part of the scutes to
continue drawing I hold my mouse above
the last point of the path which will
become red I draw below the body and end
at the first point of the skews I press
the space bar to go to the select tool I
click on Lower to bottom I will give the
new parts a name to quickly localize the
parts hold alt and move your mouse over
the elements I will place the nostrils
on top in the next lecture I will add
the dots by using the spray tool