if you are working on different logo
ideas and you're running out of space
you can make the page bigger to do this
click on the pages tool now I can simply
drag out a corner to make the artboard
larger you can also create a multi-page
file which you can then export as a PDF
I have my page set to A4 to change the
page size I right click to open document
properties if I click behind format I
can choose from a list of standard
formats I can also give it a size I
prefer to work in millimeter but I can
choose another measurement
I select the pages tool
I want to create two spreads I click on
the new page icon
to connect the pages I drag a page until
it snaps
I open document properties again I
deselect show Shadow I create a new page
in snapping I enable alignment
I drag the new page below the spread and
I add a fourth page
I'll place it against the page below
I will also Place some margins
I type 15 millimeters
I give all four pages a margin
you can also drag margins
or you can set a specific value
I can scroll with my scroll wheel
the margins are magnetic
in the next lecture we will export a
multi-page PDF