when I draw a shape I can give it a fill
and a stroke
to hide the fill click on the Red Cross
and to hide the stroke shift-click on
the Red Cross I shift-click on black
again the width of the stroke is two
millimeter
when I hold my mouse above the value and
scroll forward I increase the stroke
width it is clear that the stroke is in
front of the fill I can place the stroke
behind the fill
I click on the stroke width value behind
order I click on the second icon
here I have text with a stroke when I
increase the stroke it will obfuscate
the text so I click on the second icon
the corners of the stroke are rounded
you can also choose bevel or miter to
get another look
and the text is still editable