in this lecture I will add some text to
the logo I want the text to stay
editable and also the curvature of the
text to stay editable
before we used pathfx to curve text
for path effects however you need to
convert the text to a path I could also
clone the text and work with a clone
that still wouldn't give me the control
I want to rotate text I need my text to
be on a circle I select the text tool
and click on the canvas for text
alignment I choose centered I use Grand
hotel which is a free Google font I type
coffee Boutique I make the size 90 point
I select the dropper tool and Sample the
darker brown
now let's place the text on a path I
select the ellipse tool I hold Ctrl and
drag a circle
I go to path object to path
in fill and stroke I set Alpha to one
percent
I shift-click on the text I go to text
put on path if I click on the circle
again I can rotate the text
the text is now on top of the circle I
want to place the text on the bottom so
I want to place the text on the inside
of the circle
to do this I click on the flip
horizontal icon
now I rotate the circle
if I click on the Node tool I see the
text is on the inside of the circle
I press the space bar
by dragging at the top I can determine
the curvature of the text
if I drag the circle the text will move
with it
but when I move the text the circle will
stay in place
I can now curve the text without the
circle being over the logo
and I can still adjust the text
[Music]