now let's Place some dots
I will use the spray tool for this I
start by drawing an ellipse and I will
give it an orange color I right click on
the Swatch and choose pin color
now I copy the ellipse to place it in
memory then I select the spray tool I
click on spray clones of the selection
so I can manipulate the result
afterwards
I do not want the dots to overlap
so I click on prevent overlapping
objects
the orange circle is the spray area to
make the spray area larger increase
width the rest of the values are all
maxed out to get maximum variation
when I spray I see I get very small and
very large ellipses I need the dots to
be more uniform so I set scale to 50.
this is better
also on average the dots are a bit too
large
so I press the space bar to go to the
select tool if I make the parent ellipse
smaller the children will follow this is
about right now I spray over the body if
I don't like a result I click control
set and spray again and I can still
change the color I delete the original
to place the ellipses in a group I right
click on one then I choose select same
fill color
I right click again and choose group
I will call the group dots in the next
lecture we will shade the drawing